<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE gamebook SYSTEM "gamebook.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % general.links SYSTEM "genlink.mod">
 %general.links;
 <!ENTITY % xhtml.links   SYSTEM "htmllink.mod">
 %xhtml.links;

 <!ENTITY % general.inclusions SYSTEM "geninc.mod">
 %general.inclusions;
]>

<gamebook xml:lang="en-UK" version="0.12">

<meta>
 <title>Rules Handbook</title>
 <creator class="short">Project Aon Staff</creator>
 <creator class="medium">Project Aon Staff</creator>
 <creator class="long">
  <p>The <a href="&link.project.website;">Project Aon</a> Team is the group of fan-volunteers dedicated to publishing online the gamebooks by Joe Dever et al. They have co-authored this booklet in order to make the gamebooks more accessible and more enjoyable.</p>
 </creator>
 <publisher>Project Aon</publisher>
 <date class="publication"><year>2003</year><month>3</month><day>6</day></date>
 <description class="publication">
  <p>Published by <a href="&link.project.website;">Project Aon</a>.</p>
 </description>
 <rights class="copyrights">Copyright <ch.copy/> 2002<ch.endash/>2003 The Project Aon Team.</rights>
 <rights class="license-notification">
  <p>
   <line>Copyright <ch.copy/> 2002<ch.endash/>2003 Project Aon.</line>
   <line>Distribution of this Internet Edition is restricted under the terms of the <a idref="license">Project Aon License</a>.</line>
  </p>
 </rights>
</meta>

<section id="toc">
 <meta />
 <data />
</section>

<section id="title">
 <meta>
  <title>Title Page</title>
  <link class="next" idref="acknwldg" />
 </meta>

 <data>

  <section class="frontmatter" id="dedicate">
   <meta>
    <title>Dedication</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="title" />
    <link class="next" idref="acknwldg" />
   </meta>

   <data>

    <p class="dedication">To all those who created such a fantastic world.</p>

   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="frontmatter" id="acknwldg">
   <meta>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="title" />
    <link class="next" idref="preface" />
   </meta>

   <data>

    <p>We would like to thank all those who have worked to make this booklet the useful tool that it is.</p>

    <dl>
     <dt>Contributors</dt>
      <dd>
       <line>Jonathan Blake</line>
       <line>Jeff Dougan</line>
       <line>Joe Grocott-James</line>
       <line>Simon Osborne</line>
       <line>Thomas Wolmer</line>
      </dd>
    </dl>

   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="frontmatter" id="preface">
   <meta>
    <title>Preface</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="acknwldg" />
    <link class="next" idref="kairulz" />
   </meta>

   <data>
    <p>In writing the Lone Wolf series, Joe Dever created a system of rules that is both simple and satisfying in its completeness. The rules seek to find a balance between being simple enough to learn in one sitting and being able to deal with situations encountered by the player in a reasonable, realistic and predictable way.</p>
    <p>However, the rules for the Lone Wolf books are not perfect, nor are they perfectly understandable to the first time reader. Many new readers are intimidated by the rules<ch.apos/> level of complexity, skip over them and try to forget they ever existed. Although the Lone Wolf books can be enjoyed without following the rules, the reader will find greater enjoyment if the rules are understood and applied. For readers who understand the basic rules, there are inconsistencies and situations not covered by the rules. These inconsistencies and omissions can be frustrating for the conscientious.</p>
    <p>This Rule Handbook is intended to help both groups: new readers encountering the rules for the first time, and experienced readers encountering confusion about how to apply the rules in a particular situation. It is organized with the intention of helping you find the information you need when you need it.</p>
    <p>This booklet is divided up into sections based on the different series of gamebooks written and edited by Joe Dever: the <a idref="kairulz">Lone Wolf Kai series</a> (books 1<ch.endash/>5), the <a idref="mkrulz">Lone Wolf Magnakai series</a> (books 6<ch.endash/>12), the <a idref="gmrulz">Lone Wolf Grand Master series</a> (books 13<ch.endash/>20), the <a idref="norulz">Lone Wolf New Order series</a> (books 21<ch.endash/>28), the <a idref="wrldrulz">World of Lone Wolf series</a> and the <a idref="fwrulz">Freeway Warrior series</a>. Each section goes through the rules sequentially as presented in the books.</p>
    <p>A composite version of the rules for each series is written from beginning to end in its section. This composite appears without indentation. Where comment is necessary, it is inserted in indented text and <em>italic typeface</em>. For example:</p>
    <hr />
    <p>You keep a record of your adventure on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em> The <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> is a set of tables which contain all information about your character such as items carried, skills possessed, etc. The <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> can take many forms. You may use a specialized program like StatsKeeper to help you keep track of character statistics. You may use a spreadsheet document. You may print out the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> that appears in the Internet Editions of the books and fill in the blanks. As you become familiar with the rules, you may want to create your own by hand on paper. The method you choose doesn<ch.apos/>t matter as long as you<ch.apos/>re comfortable with it.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <hr />
    <p>Links are also provided to helpful information in the <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a>. For the first time reader, as you read through the rules, you can refer to this booklet to find explanations of the things you read in the order which you read them.</p>
    <p>In areas where there is more than one reasonable way to interpret rules, we will present justifications for the most reasonable interpretations and let you decide for yourself. The Rules Handbook is not here to dictate the One True Way. Find what you are comfortable with and follow it.</p>
    <p>The <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a> which follows the several rules composites is an alphabetical listing of topics in need of clarification.</p>
    <p>We hope that you find this booklet helpful in better understanding the rules and finding greater enjoyment in Joe Dever<ch.apos/>s gamebooks. If this booklet doesn<ch.apos/>t answer all your questions, please <a href="&link.staff.contact;">contact us</a> with your question.</p>
    <p><strong>The Project Aon Team</strong></p>
    <ul>
     <li><a idref="kairulz">The [Kai] Game Rules</a></li>
     <li><a idref="mkrulz">The [Magnakai] Game Rules</a></li>
     <li><a idref="gmrulz">The [Grand Master] Game Rules</a></li>
     <li><a idref="norulz">The [New Order] Game Rules</a></li>
     <li><a idref="wrldrulz">The [World of Lone Wolf] Game Rules</a></li>
     <li><a idref="fwrulz">The [Freeway Warrior] Rules</a></li>
     <li><a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a></li>
    </ul>
   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="mainmatter" id="kairulz">
   <meta>
    <title>The [Kai] Game Rules</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="preface" />
    <link class="next" idref="kaidisc" />
   </meta>

   <data>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>Theses rules do not come from any particular book. They are a generic set of rules designed to help new readers familiarize themselves with the rules<ch.emdash/>not walk the reader through a particular book. The details of the rules in each book will differ from what you find here.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>You keep a record of your adventure on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
    <p>During your training as a Kai Lord you have developed fighting prowess<ch.emdash/><a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and physical stamina<ch.emdash/><a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>. Before you set off on your adventure you need to measure how effective your training has been. To do this take a pencil and, with your eyes closed, point with the blunt end of it on to the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>. If you pick 0 it counts as zero.</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>If you have already completed an adventure with your character, you should not pick his <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> again. You should use those scores already picked.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>The first number that you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> in this way represents your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. Add 10 to the number you picked and write the total in the <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. (i.e. if your pencil fell on the number 4 in the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> you would write in a <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of 14.) When you fight, your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> will be pitted against that of your enemy. A high score in this section is therefore very desirable.</p>
    <p>The second number that you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> represents your powers of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>. Add 20 to this number and write the total in the <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. (i.e. if your pencil fell on the number 6 on the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> you would have 26 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points.)</p>
    <p>If you are wounded in combat you will lose <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. If at any time your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points fall to zero or below, you are dead and the adventure is over. Lost <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points can be regained during the course of the adventure, but your number of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points can never go above the number with which you start your adventure.</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>You start each adventure with your maximum <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point score. (see <a idref="lwcn1987summer">Lone Wolf Club Newsletter: Summer Special 1987</a>)</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>If you have successfully completed any previous book of the Lone Wolf series, you will already have your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>, <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points and Kai Disciplines which you can now carry over with you to this book. You may also carry over any <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> and <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> that you held at the end of the previous book and these should be entered on your new <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> (you are still limited to two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> and eight <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a>).</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>You may also carry over any <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a> and <a idref="topics-currency">Currency</a> (e.g. <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a>) that you possessed at the end of the last adventure. Some readers feel that you should not carry over Meals since they are perishable, but this is not even hinted at in the rules, so this is optional.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>You may choose one bonus Kai Discipline to add to your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> for every Lone Wolf adventure you have successfully completed; then read the section on equipment for this book carefully.</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>You may add <em>one</em> Discipline if you have completed a previous adventure successfully. In other words, you earn one new Discipline each time you complete an adventure successfully.</em></p>
    </blockquote>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="kaidisc">
     <meta>
      <title>Kai Disciplines</title>
       <link class="prev" idref="kairulz" />
       <link class="next" idref="keqpmnt" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>Over the centuries, the Kai monks have mastered the skills of the warrior. These skills are known as the Kai Disciplines, and they are taught to all Kai Lords. You are a Kai initiate which means that you have learnt only five of the skills listed below. The choice of which five skills these are, is for you to make. As all of the Disciplines will be of use to you at some point on your adventure, pick your five with care. The correct use of a Discipline at the right time can save your life.</p>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>If you have already completed one or more adventures, you will already have picked your five initial Disciplines. You may add more Disciplines to your initial five as described later. It is quite possible that a particular Discipline will be of no use to you at all in a particular book which means that you should pick your Disciplines with even greater care.</em></p>
      </blockquote>

      <p>When you have chosen your five Disciplines, enter them in the Kai Discipline section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidiscc">
       <meta>
        <title>Camouflage</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>This Discipline enables a Kai Lord to blend in with his surroundings. In the countryside, he can hide undetected among trees and rocks and pass close to an enemy without being seen. In a town or city, it enables him to look and sound like a native of that area, and can help him to find shelter or a safe hiding place.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Camouflage</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidiscu">
       <meta>
        <title>Hunting</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>This skill ensures that a Kai Lord will never starve in the wild. He will always be able to hunt for food for himself except in areas of wasteland and desert. This skill is very useful for it also enables a Kai Lord to move with great speed and dexterity.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Hunting: no need for a Meal when instructed to eat</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidiscs">
       <meta>
        <title>Sixth Sense</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>This skill may warn a Kai Lord of imminent danger. It may also reveal the true purpose of a stranger or strange object encountered in your adventure.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Sixth Sense</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidisct">
       <meta>
        <title>Tracking</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>This skill enables a Kai Lord to make the correct choice of a path in the wild, to discover the location of a person or object in a town or city and to read the secrets of footprints or tracks.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Tracking</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidisch">
       <meta>
        <title>Healing</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>This Discipline can be used to restore <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost in combat. If you possess this skill you may restore 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point to your total for every numbered section of the book you pass through in which you are not involved in combat. (This is only to be used after your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> has fallen below its original level.) Remember that your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> cannot rise above its original level.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill write <quote><a idref="topics-healing">Healing</a>. + 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point for each section without combat</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>(see the <a idref="topics-healing">Healing</a> entry in the <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a>)</em></p>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidiscw">
       <meta>
        <title>Weaponskill</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>Upon entering the Kai monastery, each initiate is taught to master one type of weapon. If Weaponskill is to be one of your Kai Disciplines, pick a number in the usual way from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> on the last page of the book, and then find the corresponding <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> from the list below. This is the <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> in which you have skill. When you enter combat carrying this <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, you add 2 points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</p>
        <ul class="unbulleted">
         <li>0 = <a idref="topics-dagger">Dagger</a></li> 
         <li>1 = <a idref="topics-spear">Spear</a></li>
         <li>2 = <a idref="topics-mace">Mace</a></li>
         <li>3 = <a idref="topics-shortsword">Short Sword</a></li>
         <li>4 = <a idref="topics-warhammer">Warhammer</a></li>
         <li>5 = <a idref="topics-sword">Sword</a></li>
         <li>6 = <a idref="topics-axe">Axe</a></li>
         <li>7 = <a idref="topics-sword">Sword</a></li>
         <li>8 = <a idref="topics-quarterstaff">Quarterstaff</a></li>
         <li>9 = <a idref="topics-broadsword">Broadsword</a></li>
        </ul>
        <p>The fact that you are skilled with a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> does not mean you set out on the adventure carrying that particular <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>. However, you will have opportunities to acquire <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> in the course of your adventures. You cannot carry more than 2 <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Possessing Weaponskill doesn<ch.apos/>t <strong>necessarily</strong> mean that you start out with that <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, but you might.</em></p>
        </blockquote>

        <p>You cannot carry more than 2 <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>. If you choose this skill, write <quote>Weaponskill in <ch.blankline/> + 2 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points if this <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidiscd">
       <meta>
        <title>Mindshield</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>The Darklords and many of the evil creatures in their command have the ability to attack you using their Mindforce. The Kai Discipline of Mindshield prevents you from losing any <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points when subjected to this form of attack.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Mindshield: no points lost when attacked by Mindblast</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidiscl">
       <meta>
        <title>Mindblast</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>This enables a Kai Lord to attack an enemy using the force of his mind. It can be used at the same time as normal combat <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> and adds two extra points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. Not all the creatures encountered on this adventure will be harmed by Mindblast. You will be told if a creature is immune.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Mindblast: + 2 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidisca">
       <meta>
        <title>Animal Kinship</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>This skill enables a Kai Lord to communicate with some animals and to be able to guess the intentions of others.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Animal Kinship</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaidiscm">
       <meta>
        <title>Mind Over Matter</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>Mastery of this Discipline enables a Kai Lord to move small objects with his powers of concentration.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Mind Over Matter</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <p><strong>If you successfully complete the mission as set in this book of Lone Wolf</strong>, you may add a further Kai Discipline of your choice to your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> in the next book. This additional skill, together with your other skills and any <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> that you have found, may then be used in the next adventure in the Lone Wolf series.</p>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="keqpmnt">
     <meta>
      <title>[Kai] Equipment</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="kaidisc" />
      <link class="next" idref="kaicmbt" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>The way in which you obtain your equipment before the adventure varies greatly from book to book. What follows is a fairly common scenario intended to give you a feel for what to expect, but it may be very different from a particular book you read. Please carefully read the Equipment section of the book you are playing to find out its particular details.</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Before leaving on your journey, you are given a map of the area and a pouch of gold. To find out how much gold is in the pouch, pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>. Now add 10 to the number you have picked. The total equals the number of <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> inside the pouch, and you may now enter this number in the <quote><a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></quote> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. (If you have successfully completed previous Lone Wolf adventures, you may add this sum to the total of any Crowns you may already possess. Remember you can only carry a maximum of fifty Crowns.)</p>
      <p>You may take your pick of the following items (in addition to those you already possess, but remember you may only carry two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>). You may take up to three of the following:</p>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>(see <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a> for details about a particular item)</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>List the three items you choose on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>, under the heading given in brackets, and make a note of any effect it may have on your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points or <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</p>
      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaihwcry">
       <meta>
        <title>How to carry equipment</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>Now that you have your equipment, the following list shows you how it is carried. You don<ch.apos/>t need to make notes but you can refer back to this list in the course of your adventure.</p>
       <blockquote>
        <p><em>(see <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a> for details about a particular item)</em></p>
       </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaimhcry">
       <meta>
        <title>How much can you carry?</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a></dt>
          <dd><p>The maximum number of <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> that you may carry is two.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a></dt>
          <dd><p>These must be stored in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. Because space is limited, you may only keep a maximum of eight articles, including Meals, in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a> at any one time.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a></dt>
          <dd><p><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> are not carried in the <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. When you discover a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, you will be told how to carry it.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></dt>
          <dd><p>These are always carried in the <a idref="topics-beltpouch">Belt Pouch</a>. It will hold a maximum of fifty crowns.</p></dd>
         <dt>Food</dt>
          <dd><p>Food is carried in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. Each Meal counts as one item.</p></dd>
        </dl>
        <p>Any item that may be of use and can be picked up on your adventure and entered on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> is given capital letters in the text. Unless you are told it is a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, carry it in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaihowuz">
       <meta>
        <title>How to use your equipment</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a></dt>
          <dd><p><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> aid you in combat. If you have the Kai Discipline of Weaponskill and the correct <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, it adds 2 points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. If you enter a combat with no <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>, deduct 4 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and fight with your bare hands. If you find a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> during the adventure, you may pick it up and use it. (Remember you can only carry two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> at once.)</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a></dt>
          <dd><p>During your travels you will discover various useful items which you may wish to keep. (Remember you can only carry eight items in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a> at once.) You may exchange or discard them at any point when you are not involved in combat.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a></dt>
          <dd>
           <p>Each <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> has a particular purpose or effect. You may be told this when the item is discovered, or it may be revealed to you as the adventure progresses. <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> are not usually carried in the <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. When you discover a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, you will be told how to carry it. If you have successfully completed previous Lone Wolf books, you may already possess <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a>.</p>
           <blockquote>
            <p><em>(see the <a idref="topics-safekeeping">Safekeeping</a> entry in the <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a>)</em></p>
           </blockquote>
          </dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></dt>
          <dd><p>The local currency is the Crown, which is a small gold coin. <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> can be used on your adventure to pay for transport, food or even as a bribe! Many of the creatures that you will encounter possess <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a>, or have them hidden in their lairs. Whenever you kill a creature, you may take any <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> that it has and put them in your <a idref="topics-beltpouch">Belt Pouch</a>.</p></dd>
         <dt>Food</dt>
          <dd><p>You will need to eat regularly during your adventure. If you do not have any food when you are instructed to eat a Meal, you will lose 3 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. If you have chosen the Kai Discipline of Hunting as one of your five skills, you will not need to tick off a Meal when instructed to eat unless you are in an area of wasteland or desert.</p></dd>
         <dt>Healing Potion</dt>
          <dd><p>This can restore 4 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to your total when swallowed after combat. There is only enough for one dose. If you discover any other potions during the adventure, you will be told then of their effect. All Healing Potions are <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a>.</p></dd>
         </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="kaicmbt">
     <meta>
      <title>[Kai] Rules for Combat</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="keqpmnt" />
      <link class="next" idref="mkrulz" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>There will be occasions on your adventure when you have to fight an enemy. The enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points are given in the text. Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s aim in the combat is to kill the enemy by reducing his <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to zero while losing as few <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points as possible himself.</p>
      <p>At the start of a combat, enter Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s and the enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points in the appropriate boxes on the Combat Record section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
      <ol class="paragraphed">
       <li><p>Add any extra points gained through your Kai Disciplines to your current <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> total.</p></li>
       <li>
        <p>Subtract the <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of your enemy from this total. The result is your <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a>. Enter it on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <p>Example</p>
        <p>Lone Wolf (<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> 15) is ambushed by a Winged Devil (<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> 20). He is not given the opportunity to evade combat, but must stand and fight as the creature swoops down on him. Lone Wolf has the Kai Discipline of Mindblast, so he adds 2 points to his <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>, giving a total <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of 17.</p>
        <p>He subtracts the Winged Devil<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> from his own, giving a <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> of <ch.minus/>3 (17 <ch.minus/> 20 = <ch.minus/>3). <ch.minus/>3 is noted on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> as the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a>.</p>
       </li>
       <li><p>When you have your <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a>, pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>.</p></li>
       <li>
        <p>Turn to the <a idref="topics-combatresultstable">Combat Results Table</a>. Along the top of the chart are shown the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> numbers. Find the number that is the same as your <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> and cross-reference it with the random number that you have picked (the random numbers appear on the side of the chart). You now have the number of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost by both Lone Wolf and his enemy in this round of combat. (E represents points lost by the enemy; LW represents points lost by Lone Wolf.)</p>
        <p>Example</p>
        <p>The <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> between Lone Wolf and Winged Devil has been established as <ch.minus/>3. If the number taken from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> is a 6, then the result of the first round of combat is:</p>
        <ul>
         <li>Lone Wolf loses 3 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points</li>
         <li>Winged Devil loses 6 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points</li>
        </ul>
       </li>
       <li><p>On the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>, mark the changes in <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to the participants in the combat.</p></li>
       <li><p>Unless otherwise instructed, or unless you have an option to evade, the next round of combat now starts.</p></li>
       <li><p>Repeat the sequence from Stage 3.</p></li>
      </ol>
      <p>This process of combat continues until the <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points of either the enemy or Lone Wolf are reduced to zero, at which point the one with the zero score is declared dead. If Lone Wolf is dead, the adventure is over. If the enemy is dead, Lone Wolf proceeds but with his <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points reduced.</p>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>It is not necessarily true that Lone Wolf will lose any <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> in combat. He may go unscathed.</em></p>
      </blockquote>

      <p>A summary of Combat Rules appears in the back of this book.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kvasion">
       <meta><title>Evasion of Combat</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>During your adventure you may be given the chance to evade combat. If you have already engaged in a round of combat and decide to evade, calculate the combat for that round in the usual manner. All points lost by the enemy as a result of that round are ignored, and you make your escape. Only Lone Wolf may lose <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points during that round, but then that is the risk of running away! You may only evade if the text of the particular section allows you to do so.</p>
       </data>
      </section>
     </data>
    </section>

   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="mainmatter" id="mkrulz">
   <meta>
    <title>The [Magnakai] Game Rules</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="kaicmbt" />
    <link class="next" idref="mkdisc" />
   </meta>

   <data>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>Theses rules do not come from any particular book. They are a generic set of rules designed to help new readers familiarize themselves with the rules<ch.emdash/>not walk the reader through a particular book. The details of the rules in each book will differ from what you find here.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>You keep a record of your adventure on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
    <p>During your training as a Kai Master you have developed fighting prowess<ch.emdash/><a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and physical stamina<ch.emdash/><a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>. Before you set off on your adventure you need to measure how effective your training has been. To do this take a pencil and, with your eyes closed, point with the blunt end of it on to the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>. If you pick 0 it counts as zero.</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>If you have already completed an adventure with your character, you should not pick his <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> again. You should use those scores already picked.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>The first number that you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> in this way represents your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. Add 10 to the number you picked and write the total in the <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. (i.e. if your pencil fell on the number 4 in the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> you would write in a <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of 14.) When you fight, your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> will be pitted against that of your enemy. A high score in this section is therefore very desirable.</p>
    <p>The second number that you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> represents your powers of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>. Add 20 to this number and write the total in the <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. (i.e. if your pencil fell on the number 6 on the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> you would have 26 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points.)</p>
    <p>If you are wounded in combat you will lose <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. If at any time your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points fall to zero, you are dead and the adventure is over. Lost <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points can be regained during the course of the adventure, but your number of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points can never rise above the number you started with.</p>
    <p><strong>If you have successfully completed any of the previous adventures in the Lone Wolf series</strong>, you can carry your current scores of <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points over to this book. You may also carry over any <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> and <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> you have in your possession at the end of your last adventure, and these should be entered on your new <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> (you are still limited to two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> and eight <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a>).</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>You may also carry over any <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a> and <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> that you possessed at the end of the last adventure. Some readers feel that you should not carry over Meals since they are perishable, but this is not hinted at in the rules so this is optional.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>You many choose one bonus Magnakai Discipline to add to your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> for every Lone Wolf Magnakai adventure you successfully complete (Books 6<ch.endash/>12).</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>You may add <em>one</em> Magnakai Discipline if you have completed a previous Magnakai adventure successfully. In other words, you earn one new Magnakai Discipline each time you complete a Magnakai adventure successfully.</em></p>
    </blockquote>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="mkdisc">
     <meta>
      <title>Magnakai Disciplines</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="mkrulz" />
      <link class="next" idref="mkeqpmnt" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>During your training as a Kai Lord, and in the course of the adventures that led to the discovery of <cite>The Book of the Magnakai</cite>, you have mastered all ten of the basic warrior skills known as the Kai Disciplines.</p>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>If you have completed the first five books of the Lone Wolf series, you can continue to use the Kai Disciplines acquired in those books. (see the following Lone Wolf Club Newsletters: <a idref="lwcn1987summer">Summer Special 1987</a>, <a idref="lwcn10">No. 10</a> and <a idref="lwcn28">No. 28</a>) If you have not completed all of the first five books, use your personal judgement whether or not you should benefit from Kai Disciplines which you didn<ch.apos/>t choose in the books you did complete. If you have completed all five books of the Kai series, remember that you now possess all ten Kai Disciplines including the last one that you hadn<ch.apos/>t chosen previously. If that left over Discipline was Weaponskill, remember to chose a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> with which you are skilled as detailed in the Kai series books.</em></p>
       <p><em>Some Kai Disciplines have measureable bonuses that are useful to you in the Magnakai series. Other Kai Disciplines have less tangible effects and are assumed by the book (e.g. the Kai Discipline of Camouflage doesn<ch.apos/>t have a measureable bonus and the books assume you have this skill). The Kai Disciplines that are useful in the Magnakai series are:</em></p>
       <ul>
        <li><em>Hunting<ch.emdash/>may be used to automatically find food in fertile areas, but still doesn<ch.apos/>t function in areas of wasteland or desert.</em></li>
        <li><em><a idref="topics-healing">Healing</a><ch.emdash/>may be used to heal 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point while not in combat.</em></li>
        <li><em>Weaponskill<ch.emdash/>adds 2 points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> if using the <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> with which you are skilled.</em></li>
        <li><em>Mindblast<ch.emdash/>adds 2 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points to your total when used against an opponent who isn<ch.apos/>t immune.</em></li>
       </ul>
       <p><em>These bonuses are replaced by their Magnakai Discipline equivalent (e.g. acquiring Weaponmastery in your Weaponskill <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> gives you a +3 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> bonus<ch.emdash/>not +5).</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>After studying <cite>The Book of the Magnakai</cite>, you have also reached the rank of Kai Master Superior, which means that you have learnt <em>three</em> of the Magnakai Disciplines listed below. It is up to you to choose which three skills these are. As all of the Magnakai Disciplines will be of use to you at some point on your adventure, pick your three with care. The correct use of a Magnakai Discipline at the right time can save your life.</p>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>If you have already completed one or more Magnakai adventures, you will already have picked your three initial Disciplines. You may add more Disciplines to your initial three as described later. It is quite possible that a particular Discipline will be of no use to you at all in a particular book which means that you should pick your Disciplines with even greater care.</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The Magnakai skills are divided into groups, each of which is governed by a separate school of training. These groups are called <quote><a idref="topics-lorecircles">Lore-circles</a></quote>. By mastering all of the Magnakai Disciplines in a particular <a idref="topics-lorecircles">Lore-circle</a>, you can gain an increase in your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points score. (See the section <quote><a idref="topics-lorecircles">Lore-circles</a> of the Magnakai</quote> for details of these bonuses.)</p>
      <p>When you have chosen your three Magnakai Disciplines, enter them in the Magnakai Disciplines section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="wpnmstry">
       <meta><title>Weaponmastery</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>This Magnakai Discipline enables a Kai Master to become proficient in the use of all types of <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>. When you enter combat with a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> you have mastered, you add 3 points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. The rank of Kai Master Superior, with which you begin the Magnakai series, means you are skilled in <em>three</em> of the <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> in the list below.</p>
        <ul class="unbulleted">
         <li><a idref="topics-spear">Spear</a></li>
         <li><a idref="topics-dagger">Dagger</a></li>
         <li><a idref="topics-mace">Mace</a></li>
         <li><a idref="topics-shortsword">Short Sword</a></li>
         <li><a idref="topics-warhammer">Warhammer</a></li>
         <li><a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a></li>
         <li><a idref="topics-quarterstaff">Quarterstaff</a></li>
         <li><a idref="topics-broadsword">Broadsword</a></li>
         <li><a idref="topics-axe">Axe</a></li>
         <li><a idref="topics-sword">Sword</a></li>
        </ul>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>When using a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>, you are typically asked to choose a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> to determine the success of your shot. If you choose Weaponmastery with the <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>, you may add 3 to the number chosen.</em></p>
        </blockquote>
        <p>The fact that you are skilled with three <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> does not mean that you begin the adventure carrying any of them. However, you will have opportunities to acquire <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> during your adventure. For every Lone Wolf book that you complete in the Magnakai series, you may add an additional <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> to your list.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Possessing Weaponmastery doesn<ch.apos/>t <strong>necessarily</strong> mean that you start out with that <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, but you might.</em></p>
        </blockquote>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Weaponmastery: + 3 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>, and tick your chosen <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> on the <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> list. You cannot carry more than two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>) These improvements and those for subsequent Magnakai Disciplines are listed here for your convenience.</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Tutelary (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Tutelaries are able to use defensive combat skills to great effect when fighting unarmed. When entering combat without a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, Tutelaries lose only 2 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>, instead of the usual 4 points.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Mentora (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Mentoras skilled in Weaponmastery are more accurate when using all missile <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>, whether fired (e.g., a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>) or thrown (e.g., a <a idref="topics-dagger">Dagger</a>). When using a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> or thrown <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> and instructed to pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>, add 2 to the number picked if you are a Mentora with the Magnakai Discipline of Weaponmastery.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Scion-kai (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>When entering combat with a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> they have mastered, Scion-kai may add 4 points (instead of the usual 3 points) to their <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. Also, when in combat without a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, they only lose 1 point from their <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="anmlctrl">
       <meta><title>Animal Control</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>This Magnakai Discipline enables a Kai Master to communicate with most animals and to determine their purpose and intentions. It also enables a Kai Master to fight from the saddle with great advantage.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Animal Control</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Primate (4 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Primates with this Magnakai Discipline are able to repel an animal that is intent on harming them by blocking its sense of taste and smell. The level of success is dependent on the size and ferocity of the animal.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Principalin (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Principalins with this skill are able to call on a woodland animal (if nearby) to aid them, either in combat, or to act as a messenger or guide. The number of animals that can be summoned increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Archmaster (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Archmasters with this skill are able to command most animals to do their bidding, although effectiveness is diminished when attempting to control a hostile creature.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="curing">
       <meta><title>Curing</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>The possessor of this skill can restore 1 lost <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point to his total for every numbered section of the book through which he passes, provided he is not involved in combat. (This can only be done after his <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> has fallen below its original level.) This Magnakai Discipline also enables a Kai Master to cure disease, blindness and any combat wounds sustained by others, as well as himself. Using the knowledge mastery of this skill provides will also allow a Kai Master to identify the properties of any herbs, roots and potions that may be encountered during the adventure.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Curing: + 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point for each section without combat</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>(see the <a idref="topics-healing">Healing</a> entry in the <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a>)</em></p>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Primate (4 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Primates with this skill have the ability to delay the effects of poisons, including venoms, that they may come into contact with. Although a Kai Primate with this skill is not be able to neutralize a poison he is able to slow its effect, giving him more time to find an antidote or cure.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Mentora (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Mentoras with this skill are able to neutralize the effects of any poisons, venoms or toxins with which they come into contact.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Archmaster (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Archmasters are able to use their healing power to repair serious wounds sustained in combat. If, whilst in combat, their <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> is reduced to 6 points or less, they can use their skill to restore 20 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. This ability can only be used once every 100 days.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="invsblty">
       <meta><title>Invisibility</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>This Magnakai skill allows a Kai Master to blend in with his surroundings, even in the most exposed terrain. It will enable him to mask his body heat and scent, and to adopt the dialect and mannerisms of any town or city that he visits.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Invisibility</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Tutelary (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Tutelaries are able to increase the effectiveness of their skill when hiding from an enemy by drawing the enemy<ch.apos/>s attention to a place other than that in which they are hiding. The effectiveness of this ability increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Principalin (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Principalins are able to mask any sounds made by their movements while using this skill.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Scion-kai (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
          <dd><p><em>Scion-kai are able to alter their physical appearance at will in order to deceive an enemy. The duration and effectiveness of this deception increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="hntmstry">
       <meta><title>Huntmastery</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>This skill ensures that a Kai Master will never starve in the wild; he will always be able to hunt for food, even in areas of wasteland and desert. It also enables a Kai Master to move with great speed and dexterity and will allow him to ignore any extra loss of <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points due to a surprise attack or ambush.</p>
         <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Huntmastery</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Primate (4 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Primates with this skill have a greatly increased agility and be able to climb without the use of climbing aids, such as ropes, etc.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Principalin (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Principalins with this Magnakai Discipline are able to intensify their eyesight at will, giving them telescopic vision.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Archmaster (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Archmasters who possess this ability benefit from greatly increased senses of hearing, smell, and night vision. These senses become even more acute upon attaining the rank of Kai Grand Master.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="pthmnshp">
       <meta><title>Pathsmanship</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>In addition to the basic skill of being able to recognize the correct path in unknown territory, the Magnakai skill of Pathsmanship will enable a Kai Master to read foreign languages, decipher symbols, read footprints and tracks (even if they have been disturbed), and detect the presence of most traps. It also grants him the gift of always knowing intuitively the position of north.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Pathsmanship</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Tutelary (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Tutelaries with this skill can detect an enemy ambush within 500 yards of their position unless their <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score is low due to wounds sustained or lack of food.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Mentora (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Mentoras who possess this Magnakai Discipline are able to cross any kind of terrain on foot without leaving any tracks, even if the ground is covered in snow.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Scion-kai (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Scion-kai with this ability are able to converse with any sentient creature. They are also able to make themselves invisible when subjected to any psychic or magical spells of detection.</em></p></dd>
      </dl>
        </blockquote>
      </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="psisurge">
       <meta><title>Psi-surge</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>This psychic skill enables a Kai Master to attack an enemy using the force of his mind. It can be used as well as normal combat <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> and adds 4 extra points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</p>
        <p>It is a powerful Discipline, but it is also a costly one. For every round of combat in which you use Psi-surge, you must deduct 2 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. A weaker form of Psi-surge called Mindblast can be used against an enemy without losing any <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points, but it will add only 2 extra points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. Psi-surge cannot be used if your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> falls to 6 points or below, and not all of the creatures encountered on your adventure will be affected by it; you will be told if a creature is immune.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Psi-surge: +4 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points but <ch.minus/>2 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points per round</quote> and <quote>Mindblast: +2 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Primate (4 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Primates with the Magnakai Discipline of Psi-surge will, by concentrating their psychic powers upon an object, be able to set up vibrations that may lead to the disruption or destruction of the object.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Principalin (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Principalins using this skill in combat are able to confuse an enemy by planting seeds of doubt in its mind. The effectiveness of this ability increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Archmaster (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>When using their psychic ability to attack an enemy, Archmasters may add 6 points to their <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> instead of the usual 4 points. For every round in which Psi-surge is used, Archmasters need only deduct 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point. When using the weaker psychic attack<ch.emdash/>Mindblast<ch.emdash/>they may add 3 points without loss of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. Archmasters cannot use Psi-surge if their <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score falls to 4 points or below.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="psiscrn">
       <meta><title>Psi-screen</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Many of the hostile creatures that inhabit Magnamund have the ability to attack you using their Mindforce. The Magnakai Discipline of Psi-screen prevents you from losing any <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points when subjected to this form of attack and greatly increases your defence against supernatural illusions and hypnosis.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Psi-screen: no points lost when attacked by Mindforce</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Tutelary (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Tutelaries with this skill develop mental defence against magical charms and hostile telepathy. These defences increase in strength as a Kai Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Mentora (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Mentoras with this ability can protect themselves from evil spirits and other non-corporeal beings that attack with psychic energy. The effectiveness of this ability increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Scion-kai (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>When engaging in psychic combat Scion-kai are able to absorb and control some of the energies directed at them. By deflecting or inducing the hostile energy they can either reduce the damage they sustain, or increase the power of their own psychic attacks.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="nexus">
       <meta><title>Nexus</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Mastery of this Magnakai skill will enable you to withstand extremes of heat and cold without losing <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points and to move items by your powers of concentration alone.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Nexus</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Primate (4 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Primates with the skill of Nexus will be able to offer a far greater resistance than before to the effects of noxious gases and fumes.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Principalin (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Principalins with this ability can extinguish fires by force of will alone. The size of the fire, and the number that can be extinguished using Nexus increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Archmaster (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Archmasters with the skill of Nexus are able to withstand extremes of heat and cold, and possess limited immunity to harmful elements, such as flames, toxic gases, and corrosive liquids. The duration of this immunity increases greatly upon attaining Grand Mastership.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="dvnation">
       <meta><title>Divination</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>This skill may warn a Kai Master of imminent or unseen danger or enable him to detect an invisible or hidden enemy. It may also reveal the true purpose or intent of a stranger or strange object encountered in your adventure. Divination may enable you to communicate telepathically with another person and to sense if a creature possesses psychic abilities.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Divination</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="mkimprv">Improved Magnakai Disciplines</a> and <a idref="mklevels">Levels of Magnakai Training</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Tutelary (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Tutelaries who possess this Magnakai Discipline are able to recognize objects or creatures with magical skills or abilities. However, this improved Discipline can be negated if the creature or object is shielded from detection.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Mentora (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Mentoras who possess this skill are able to detect psychic residues lingering in a place where a dramatic event, such as a battle, a murder, a ritual sacrifice or a ritual ceremony, has taken place. By meditating at the scene of the incident, a Kai Mentora is able to visualize the event, even though it may have occurred in the distant past.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Scion-kai (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Scion-kai are able to leave their body in a state of suspended animation and, in spirit form, explore their immediate surroundings unhindered by physical limitations. This ability is called <quote>spirit walking</quote>. The length of time a Kai Master can spirit walk increases as he rises in rank. When the spirit is separated from the body in this fashion, the body remains inanimate and vulnerable to attack. If a Kai Master<ch.apos/>s body is killed whilst he is spirit walking, his spiritual self will also cease to exist, and vice versa.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <p><strong>If you successfully complete the mission as set in this book of the Lone Wolf series</strong>, you may add a further Magnakai Discipline of your choice to your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> in the next book. This additional skill, together with your other Magnakai skills and any <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> that you have found and been able to keep during your adventures may then be used in the next adventure in the Lone Wolf Magnakai series.</p>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="mkeqpmnt">
     <meta>
      <title>[Magnakai] Equipment</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="mkdisc" />
      <link class="next" idref="mkcmbt" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>The way in which you obtain your equipment before the adventure varies greatly from book to book. What follows is a fairly common scenario intended to give you a feel for what to expect, but it may be very different from a particular book you read. Please carefully read the Equipment section of the book you are playing to find out its particular details.</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Before leaving on your journey, you are given a map of the area, and a pouch of gold. To find out how much gold is in the pouch, pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>. Add 10 to the number you have picked. The total equals the number of <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> inside the pouch, and you should now enter this number in the <quote><a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></quote> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. If you have successfully completed previous Lone Wolf adventures, you may add this sum to the total sum of Crowns you already possess. You can carry a maximum of only fifty Crowns, but additional Crowns can be left in <a idref="topics-safekeeping">safekeeping</a> at your Kai monastery.</p>
      <p>You are offered a choice of equipment to aid you on your perilous mission. You can take three items from the list below, again adding to these, if necessary, any you may already possess. However, remember that you can carry a maximum of two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> and eight <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a>.</p>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>(see the <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a> for details about a particular item)</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>List the three items that you choose on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>, under the heading given in brackets, and make a note of any effect they may have on your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points or <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="mkhwcry">
       <meta><title>How to Carry Equipment</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>Now that you have your equipment, the following list shows you how it is carried. You do not need to make notes, but you should refer back to this list in the course of your adventure.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>(see the <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a> for details about a particular item)</em></p>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="mkmhcry">
       <meta><title>How Much Can You Carry?</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a></dt>
          <dd><p>The maximum number of <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> that you may carry is two.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a></dt>
          <dd><p>These must be stored in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. Because space is limited, you may keep a maximum of only eight articles, including Meals, in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a> at any one time.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a></dt>
          <dd>
           <p><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> are not carried in the <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. When you discover a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, you will be told how to carry it.</p>
           <p>The maximum number of <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> that can be carried on any adventure is twelve. Surplus <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> may be left for safekeeping at your Kai monastery.</p>
          </dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></dt>
          <dd><p>These are always carried in the <a idref="topics-beltpouch">Belt Pouch</a>. It will hold a maximum of fifty Crowns.</p></dd>
         <dt>Food</dt>
          <dd><p>Food is carried in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. Each Meal counts as one item.</p></dd>
        </dl>
        <p>Any item that may be of use and can be picked up on your adventure and entered on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> is given initial capitals (e.g. Gold Dagger, Magic Pendant) in the text. Unless you are told it is a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, carry it in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="mkhowuz">
       <meta><title>How to Use Your Equipment</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a></dt>
          <dd><p><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> aid you in combat. If you have the Magnakai Discipline of Weaponmastery and a correct <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, it adds 3 points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. If you enter a combat with no <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>, deduct 4 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and fight with your bare hands. If you find a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> during the adventure, you may pick it up and use it. (Remember that you can only carry two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> at once.)</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> and <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrows</a></dt>
          <dd>
           <p>During your adventure there will be opportunities to use a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> and <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrow</a>. If you equip yourself with this <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, and you possess at least one <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrow</a>, you may use it when the text of a particular section allows you to do so. The <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> is a useful <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, for it enables you to hit an enemy at a distance. However, a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> cannot be used in hand-to-hand combat, therefore it is strongly recommended that you also equip yourself with a close combat <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, like a <a idref="topics-sword">Sword</a> or <a idref="topics-mace">Mace</a>.</p>
           <p>In order to use a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> you must possess a <a idref="topics-quiver">Quiver</a> and at least one <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrow</a>. Each time the <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> is used, erase an <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrow</a> from your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. A <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> cannot, of course, be used if you exhaust your supply of <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrows</a>, but the opportunity may arise during your adventure for you to replenish your stock of <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrows</a>.</p>
           <p>If you have the Magnakai Discipline of Weaponmastery with a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>, you may add 3 to any number that you choose from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>, when using the <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>. If you enter combat armed only with a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>, you must deduct 4 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and fight with your bare hands.</p>
          </dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a></dt>
          <dd><p>During your travels you will discover various useful items which you may wish to keep. (Remember you can only carry a maximum of eight items in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a> at anytime.) You may exchange or discard them at any point when you are not involved in combat.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a></dt>
          <dd>
           <p><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> are not carried in the <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. When you discover a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, you will be told how to carry it. If you have successfully completed previous Lone Wolf books, you may already possess <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a>.</p>
           <p>The maximum number of <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> that a Kai Master can carry during an adventure is twelve. Surplus <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> may be left in safekeeping at your Kai monastery.</p>
          </dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></dt>
          <dd><p>The currency of Anari is the Lune, but <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> are readily accepted at an exchange rate of four Lune for every 1 <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crown</a>.</p></dd>
         <dt>Food</dt>
          <dd>
           <p>You will need to eat regularly during your adventure. If you do not have any food when you are instructed to eat a Meal, you will lose 3 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. If you have chosen the Magnakai Discipline of Huntmastery as one of your skills, you will not need to tick off a Meal when instructed to eat.</p>
           <blockquote>
            <p><em>Hunting may also be useful as noted in <a idref="mkdisc">Magnakai Disciplines</a>.</em></p>
           </blockquote>
          </dd>
         <dt>Potion of <a idref="topics-laumspur">Laumspur</a></dt>
          <dd><p>This is a healing potion that can restore 4 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to your total when swallowed after combat. There is enough for one dose only. If you discover any other potion during the adventure, you will be informed of its effect. All potions are <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a>.</p></dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="mkcmbt">
     <meta>
      <title>[Magnakai] Rules for Combat</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="mkeqpmnt" />
      <link class="next" idref="mklevels" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>There will be occasions during your adventure when you have to fight an enemy. The enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points are given in the text. Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s aim in the combat is to kill the enemy by reducing his <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to zero while losing as few <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points as possible himself.</p>
      <p>At the start of a combat, enter Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s and the enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points in the appropriate boxes on the Combat Record section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
      <p>The sequence for combat is as follows:</p>
      <ol class="paragraphed">
       <li><p>Add any extra points gained through your Magnakai Disciplines and <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> to your current <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> total.</p></li>
       <li>
        <p>Subtract the <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of your enemy from this total. The result is your <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a>. Enter it on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <p>Example</p>
        <p>Lone Wolf (<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> 15) is attacked by a Nightstalker (<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> 22). He is not given the opportunity to evade combat but must stand and fight as the creature leaps on him. Lone Wolf has the Magnakai Discipline of Psi-surge to which the Nightstalker is not immune, so Lone Wolf adds 4 points to his <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>, giving a total <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of 19.</p>
        <p>He subtracts the Nightstalker<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> from his own, giving a <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> of <ch.minus/>3. (19 <ch.minus/> 22 = <ch.minus/>3). <ch.minus/>3 is noted on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> as the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a>.</p>
       </li>
       <li><p>When you have your <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a>, pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>.</p></li>
       <li>
        <p>Turn to the <a idref="topics-combatresultstable">Combat Results Table</a> on the inside back cover of the book. Along the top of the chart are shown the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> numbers. Find the number that is the same as your <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> and cross-reference it with the random number that you have picked (the random numbers appear on the side of the chart). You now have the number of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost by both Lone Wolf and his enemy in this round of combat. (E represents points lost by the enemy; LW represents points lost by Lone Wolf.)</p>
        <p>Example</p>
        <p>The <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> between Lone Wolf and the Nightstalker has been established as <ch.minus/>3. If the number taken from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> is a 6, then the result of the first round of combat is:</p>
        <ul>
         <li>Lone Wolf loses 3 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points (plus an additional 2 points for using Psi-surge)</li>
         <li>Nightstalker loses 6 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points</li>
        </ul>
       </li>
       <li><p>On the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>, mark the changes in <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to the participants in the combat.</p></li>
       <li><p>Unless otherwise instructed, or unless you have an option to evade, the next round of combat now starts.</p></li>
       <li><p>Repeat the sequence from Stage 3.</p></li>
      </ol>
      <p>This process of combat continues until the <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points of either the enemy or Lone Wolf are reduced to zero, at which point the one with the zero score is declared dead. If Lone Wolf is dead, the adventure is over. If the enemy is dead, Lone Wolf proceeds but with his <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points reduced.</p>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>It is not necessarily true that Lone Wolf will lose any <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> in combat. He may go unscathed.</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>A summary of Combat Rules appears in the back of this book.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="mkvasion">
       <meta><title>Evasion of Combat</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>During your adventure you may be given the chance to evade combat. If you have already engaged in a round of combat and decide to evade, calculate the combat for that round in the usual manner. All points lost by the enemy as a result of that round are ignored, and you make your escape. Only Lone Wolf may lose <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points during that round, but then that is the risk of running away! You may only evade if the text of the particular section allows you to do so.</p>
       </data>
      </section>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="mklevels">
     <meta>
      <title>Levels of Magnakai Training</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="mkcmbt" />
      <link class="next" idref="mklore" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>The following table is a guide to the rank and titles that are achieved by Kai Masters at each stage of their training. As you successfully complete each adventure in the Lone Wolf Magnakai series, you will gain an additional Magnakai Discipline and progress towards the ultimate distinction of a Kai Warrior<ch.emdash/>Kai Grand Mastership.</p>
      <ol>
       <li>Kai Master</li>
       <li>Kai Master Senior</li>
       <li>Kai Master Superior<ch.emdash/><em>You begin the Lone Wolf Magnakai adventures with this level of training</em>.</li>
       <li>Primate</li>
       <li>Tutelary</li>
       <li>Principalin</li>
       <li>Mentora</li>
       <li>Scion-kai</li>
       <li>Archmaster</li>
       <li>Kai Grand Master</li>
      </ol>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="mklore">
     <meta>
      <title>Lore-circles of the Magnakai</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="mklevels" />
      <link class="next" idref="mkimprv" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>In the years before their massacre, the Kai Masters of Sommerlund devoted themselves to the study of the Magnakai. These skills were divided into four schools of training called <quote><a idref="topics-lorecircles">Lore-circles</a></quote>. By mastering all of the Magnakai Disciplines of a <a idref="topics-lorecircles">Lore-circle</a>, the Kai Masters developed their fighting prowess (<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>), and their physical and mental stamina (<a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>) to a level far higher than any mortal warrior could otherwise attain.</p>
      <p>Listed below are the four <a idref="topics-lorecircles">Lore-circles</a> of the Magnakai and the skills that must be mastered in order to complete them.</p>
      <dl>
      <dt>Circle of Fire</dt>
       <dd>Weaponmastery <ch.ampersand/> Huntmastery</dd>
      <dt>Circle of Light</dt>
       <dd>Animal Control <ch.ampersand/> Curing</dd>
      <dt>Circle of Solaris</dt>
       <dd>Invisibility, Huntmastery <ch.ampersand/> Pathsmanship</dd>
      <dt>Circle of the Spirit</dt>
       <dd>Psi-surge, Psi-screen, Nexus <ch.ampersand/> Divination</dd>
      </dl>
      <p>By completing a <a idref="topics-lorecircles">Lore-circle</a>, you may add to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> the extra bonus points that are shown below.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="lcbonus">
       <meta><title>Lore-circle bonuses</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl>
         <dt>Circle of Fire</dt>
          <dd>+1 <a idref="topics-cs"><typ class="attribute">CS</typ></a> +2 <a idref="topics-ep"><typ class="attribute">EP</typ></a></dd>
         <dt>Circle of Light</dt>
          <dd>0 <a idref="topics-cs"><typ class="attribute">CS</typ></a> +3 <a idref="topics-ep"><typ class="attribute">EP</typ></a></dd>
         <dt>Circle of Solaris</dt>
          <dd>+1 <a idref="topics-cs"><typ class="attribute">CS</typ></a> +3 <a idref="topics-ep"><typ class="attribute">EP</typ></a></dd>
         <dt>Circle of the Spirit</dt>
          <dd>+3 <a idref="topics-cs"><typ class="attribute">CS</typ></a> +3 <a idref="topics-ep"><typ class="attribute">EP</typ></a></dd>
        </dl>
        <p>All bonus points that you acquire by completing a <a idref="topics-lorecircles">Lore-circle</a> are additions to your basic <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> scores.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="mkimprv">
     <meta>
      <title>Improved [Magnakai] Disciplines</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="mklore" />
      <link class="next" idref="gmrulz" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>As you rise through the higher levels of Magnakai training you will find that some of your skills will steadily improve. If you have reached the rank of Primate (four skills), Tutelary (five skills), Principalin (six skills), Mentora (seven skills), Scion-kai (eight skills), or Archmaster (nine skills), you will now benefit from improvements to the following Magnakai Disciplines:</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="primate">
       <meta><title>Primate</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Animal Control</dt>
          <dd><p>Primates with this Magnakai Discipline are able to repel an animal that is intent on harming them by blocking its sense of taste and smell. The level of success is dependent on the size and ferocity of the animal.</p></dd>
         <dt>Curing</dt>
          <dd><p>Primates with this skill have the ability to delay the effects of poisons, including venoms, that they may come into contact with. Although a Kai Primate with this skill is not be able to neutralize a poison he is able to slow its effect, giving him more time to find an antidote or cure.</p></dd>
         <dt>Huntmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Primates with this skill have a greatly increased agility and be able to climb without the use of climbing aids, such as ropes, etc.</p></dd>
         <dt>Psi-surge</dt>
          <dd><p>Primates with the Magnakai Discipline of Psi-surge will, by concentrating their psychic powers upon an object, be able to set up vibrations that may lead to the disruption or destruction of the object.</p></dd>
         <dt>Nexus</dt>
          <dd><p>Primates with the skill of Nexus will be able to offer a far greater resistance than before to the effects of noxious gases and fumes.</p></dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="tutelary">
       <meta><title>Tutelary</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Weaponmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Tutelaries are able to use defensive combat skills to great effect when fighting unarmed. When entering combat without a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, Tutelaries lose only 2 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>, instead of the usual 4 points.</p></dd>
         <dt>Invisibility</dt>
          <dd><p>Tutelaries are able to increase the effectiveness of their skill when hiding from an enemy by drawing the enemy<ch.apos/>s attention to a place other than that in which they are hiding. The effectiveness of this ability increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Pathsmanship</dt>
          <dd><p>Tutelaries with this skill can detect an enemy ambush within 500 yards of their position unless their <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score is low due to wounds sustained or lack of food.</p></dd>
         <dt>Psi-screen</dt>
          <dd><p>Tutelaries with this skill develop mental defence against magical charms and hostile telepathy. These defences increase in strength as a Kai Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Divination</dt>
          <dd><p>Tutelaries who possess this Magnakai Discipline are able to recognize objects or creatures with magical skills or abilities. However, this improved Discipline can be negated if the creature or object is shielded from detection.</p></dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="prncpln">
       <meta><title>Principalin</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Animal Control</dt>
          <dd><p>Principalins with this skill are able to call on a woodland animal (if nearby) to aid them, either in combat, or to act as a messenger or guide. The number of animals that can be summoned increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Invisibility</dt>
          <dd><p>Principalins are able to mask any sounds made by their movements while using this skill.</p></dd>
         <dt>Huntmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Principalins with this Magnakai Discipline are able to intensify their eyesight at will, giving them telescopic vision.</p></dd>
         <dt>Psi-surge</dt>
          <dd><p>Principalins using this skill in combat are able to confuse an enemy by planting seeds of doubt in its mind. The effectiveness of this ability increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Nexus</dt>
          <dd><p>Principalins with this ability can extinguish fires by force of will alone. The size of the fire, and the number that can be extinguished using Nexus increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="mentora">
       <meta><title>Mentora</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Weaponmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Mentoras skilled in Weaponmastery are more accurate when using all missile <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>, whether fired (e.g., a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>) or thrown (e.g., a <a idref="topics-dagger">Dagger</a>). When using a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> or thrown <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> and instructed to pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>, add 2 to the number picked if you are a Mentora with the Magnakai Discipline of Weaponmastery.</p></dd>
         <dt>Curing</dt>
          <dd><p>Mentoras with this skill are able to neutralize the effects of any poisons, venoms or toxins with which they come into contact.</p></dd>
         <dt>Pathsmanship</dt>
          <dd><p>Mentoras who possess this Magnakai Discipline are able to cross any kind of terrain on foot without leaving any tracks, even if the ground is covered in snow.</p></dd>
         <dt>Psi-screen</dt>
          <dd><p>Mentoras with this ability can protect themselves from evil spirits and other non-corporeal beings that attack with psychic energy. The effectiveness of this ability increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Divination</dt>
          <dd><p>Mentoras who possess this skill are able to detect psychic residues lingering in a place where a dramatic event, such as a battle, a murder, a ritual sacrifice or a ritual ceremony, has taken place. By meditating at the scene of the incident, a Kai Mentora is able to visualize the event, even though it may have occurred in the distant past.</p></dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="scion">
       <meta><title>Scion-kai</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Weaponmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>When entering combat with a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> they have mastered, Scion-kai may add 4 points (instead of the usual 3 points) to their <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. Also, when in combat without a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, they only lose 1 point from their <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</p></dd>
         <dt>Invisibility</dt>
          <dd><p>Scion-kai are able to alter their physical appearance at will in order to deceive an enemy. The duration and effectiveness of this deception increases as a Kai Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Pathsmanship</dt>
          <dd><p>Scion-kai with this ability are able to converse with any sentient creature. They are also able to make themselves invisible when subjected to any psychic or magical spells of detection.</p></dd>
         <dt>Psi-screen</dt>
          <dd><p>When engaging in psychic combat Scion-kai are able to absorb and control some of the energies directed at them. By deflecting or inducing the hostile energy they can either reduce the damage they sustain, or increase the power of their own psychic attacks.</p></dd>
         <dt>Divination</dt>
          <dd><p>Scion-kai are able to leave their body in a state of suspended animation and, in spirit form, explore their immediate surroundings unhindered by physical limitations. This ability is called <quote>spirit walking</quote>. The length of time a Kai Master can spirit walk increases as he rises in rank. When the spirit is separated from the body in this fashion, the body remains inanimate and vulnerable to attack. If a Kai Master<ch.apos/>s body is killed whilst he is spirit walking, his spiritual self will also cease to exist, and vice versa.</p></dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="archm">
       <meta><title>Archmaster</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Animal Control</dt>
          <dd><p>Archmasters with this skill are able to command most animals to do their bidding, although effectiveness is diminished when attempting to control a hostile creature.</p></dd>
         <dt>Curing</dt>
          <dd><p>Archmasters are able to use their healing power to repair serious wounds sustained in combat. If, whilst in combat, their <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> is reduced to 6 points or less, they can use their skill to restore 20 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. This ability can only be used once every 100 days.</p></dd>
         <dt>Huntmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Archmasters who possess this ability benefit from greatly increased senses of hearing, smell, and night vision. These senses become even more acute upon attaining the rank of Kai Grand Master.</p></dd>
         <dt>Psi-surge</dt>
          <dd><p>When using their psychic ability to attack an enemy, Archmasters may add 6 points to their <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> instead of the usual 4 points. For every round in which Psi-surge is used, Archmasters need only deduct 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point. When using the weaker psychic attack<ch.emdash/>Mindblast<ch.emdash/>they may add 3 points without loss of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. Archmasters cannot use Psi-surge if their <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score falls to 4 points or below.</p></dd>
         <dt>Nexus</dt>
          <dd><p>Archmasters with the skill of Nexus are able to withstand extremes of heat and cold, and possess limited immunity to harmful elements, such as flames, toxic gases, and corrosive liquids. The duration of this immunity increases greatly upon attaining Grand Mastership.</p></dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

     </data>
    </section>

   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="mainmatter" id="gmrulz">
   <meta>
    <title>The [Grand Master] Game Rules</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="mkimprv" />
    <link class="next" idref="gmdisc" />
   </meta>

   <data>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>Theses rules do not come from any particular book. They are a generic set of rules designed to help new readers familiarize themselves with the rules<ch.emdash/>not walk the reader through a particular book. The details of the rules in each book will differ from what you find here.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>You keep a record of your adventure on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
    <p>During your training as a Kai Master you have developed fighting prowess<ch.emdash/><a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and physical stamina<ch.emdash/><a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>. Before you set off on your adventure you need to measure how effective your training has been. To do this take a pencil and, with your eyes closed, point with the blunt end of it on to the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>. If you pick 0 it counts as zero.</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>If you have already completed an adventure with your character, you should not pick his <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> again. You should use those scores already picked.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>The first number that you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> in this way represents your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. Add 25 to the number you picked and write the total in the <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. (i.e., if your pencil fell on the number 6 in the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> you would write in a <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of 31.) When you fight, your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> will be pitted against that of your enemy. A high score in this section is therefore very desirable.</p>
    <p>The second number that you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> represents your powers of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>. Add 30 to this number and write the total in the <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. (i.e., if your pencil fell on the number 7 on the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> you would have 37 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points.)</p>
    <p>If you are wounded in combat you will lose <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. If at any time your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points fall to zero, you are dead and the adventure is over. Lost <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points can be regained during the course of the adventure, but your number of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points can never rise above the number you started with.</p>
    <p><strong>If you have successfully completed any of the previous adventures in the Lone Wolf series</strong>, you can carry your current scores of <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points over to this book. You may also carry over any <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> and <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> you have in your possession at the end of your last adventure, and these should be entered on your new <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> (you are still limited to two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>, but you may now carry up to ten <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a>).</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>You may also carry over any <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a> and <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> that you possessed at the end of the last adventure. Some readers feel that you should not carry over Meals since they are perishable, but this is not hinted at in the rules so this is optional.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>However, only the following Special Items may be carried over to the Lone Wolf Grand Master series (Book 13 onwards):</p>
    <ul>
     <li>Crystal Star Pendant</li>
     <li>Sommerswerd</li>
     <li>Silver Helm</li>
     <li>Dagger of Vashna</li>
     <li>Silver Bracers</li>
     <li>Jewelled Mace</li>
     <li>Silver Bow of Duadon</li>
     <li>Helshezag</li>
     <li>Kagonite Chainmail</li>
     <li>Korlinium Scabbard</li>
    </ul>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>Late in the Grand Master series, this list undergoes some alterations to reflect events of the stories. If you begin the Grand Master series with Book 13, use this list throughout. If you begin later in the Grand Master series, then use the list as published in the appropriate book.</em></p>
	</blockquote>
    <p>You many choose one bonus Grand Master Discipline to add to your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> for every Lone Wolf Grand Master adventure you successfully complete (Books 13<ch.endash/>20).</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p><em>You may add <em>one</em> Grand Master Discipline if you have completed a previous Grand Master adventure successfully. In other words, you earn one new Grand Master Discipline each time you complete a Grand Master adventure successfully.</em></p>
    </blockquote>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="gmdisc">
     <meta>
      <title>Grand Master Disciplines</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="gmrulz" />
      <link class="next" idref="gmeqpmnt" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <section class="frontmatter" id="mksumary">
       <meta>
        <title>Kai and Magnakai Disciplines</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>During your distinguished rise to the rank of Kai Grand Master you have become proficient in all of the basic Kai and Magnakai Disciplines. These Disciplines have provided you with a formidable arsenal of natural abilities which have served you well in the fight against the agents and champions of Naar, King of the Darkness. A brief summary of your skills is given below.</p>

        <dl>
         <dt><a idref="wpnmstry">Weaponmastery</a></dt>
          <dd>Proficiency with all close combat and missile weapons. Master of unarmed combat; no <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> loss when fighting bare-handed.</dd>
         <dt><a idref="anmlctrl">Animal Control</a></dt>
          <dd>Communication with most animals; limited control over hostile creatures. Can use woodland animals as guides and can block a non-sentient creature<ch.apos/>s sense of taste and smell.</dd>
         <dt><a idref="curing">Curing</a></dt>
          <dd>Steady restoration of lost <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points (to self and others) as a result of combat wounds. Neutralization of poisons, venoms and toxins. Repair of serious battle wounds.</dd>
         <dt><a idref="invsblty">Invisibility</a></dt>
          <dd>Mask body heat and scent; hide effectively; mask sounds during movement; minor alterations of physical appearance.</dd>
         <dt><a idref="hntmstry">Huntmastery</a></dt>
          <dd>Effective hunting of food in the wild; increased agility; intensified vision, hearing, smell and night vision.</dd>
         <dt><a idref="pthmnshp">Pathsmanship</a></dt>
          <dd>Read languages, decipher symbols, read footprints and tracks. Intuitive knowledge of compass points; detection of enemy ambush up to 500 yards; ability to cross terrain without leaving tracks; converse with sentient creatures; mask self from psychic spells of detection.</dd>
         <dt><a idref="psisurge">Psi-surge</a></dt>
          <dd>Attack enemies using the powers of the mind; set up disruptive vibrations in objects; confuse enemies.</dd>
         <dt><a idref="psiscrn">Psi-screen</a></dt>
          <dd>Defence against hypnosis, supernatural illusions, charms, hostile telepathy, and evil spirits. Ability to divert and re-channel hostile psychic energy.</dd>
         <dt><a idref="nexus">Nexus</a></dt>
          <dd>Move small items by projection of mind power; withstand extremes of temperature; extinguish fire by force of will; limited immunity to flames, toxic gases, corrosive liquids.</dd>
         <dt><a idref="dvnation">Divination</a></dt>
          <dd>Sense imminent danger; detect invisible or hidden enemy; telepathic communication; recognize magic-using and/or magical creatures; detect psychic residues; limited ability to leave body and spirit-walk.</dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <blockquote>
       <p><em>If you have completed the first twelve books of the Lone Wolf series, you can continue to use the Magnakai Disciplines acquired in those books. (see the following Lone Wolf Club Newsletters: <a idref="lwcn1987summer">Summer Special 1987</a>, <a idref="lwcn10">No. 10</a> and <a idref="lwcn28">No. 28</a>) <!-- JDOUGAN: Jon, do these references need updating? (probably) --> If you have not completed all of the first twelve books, use your personal judgement whether or not you should benefit from Magnakai Disciplines that you didn<ch.apos/>t choose in the books you did complete. If you have completed all twelve books of the Kai series, remember that you now possess all ten Magnakai Disciplines, including the last one that you hadn<ch.apos/>t chosen previously. Be certain to adjust your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> to reflect the bonuses of the last Lore-Circle.</em></p>
       <p><em>At times, the text will explicitly give you the option of using a Magnakai Discipline. At other times, some Magnakai Disciplines may have measureable bonuses that are useful to you in the Grand Master series but which are not explicitly prompted by the text. Other Magnakai Disciplines have less tangible effects and are assumed by the book (e.g. the Magnakai Discipline of Invisibility doesn<ch.apos/>t have a measureable bonus and the books assume you have this skill). The Magnakai Disciplines that can provide "tangible" bonuses in the Grand Master series are:</em></p>
       <ul>
        <li><em><a idref="hntmstry">Huntmastery</a><ch.emdash/>may be used to automatically find food (unless the text explicitly notes otherwise)</em></li>
        <li><em><a idref="topics-healing">Curing</a><ch.emdash/>may be used to heal 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point (per numbered section of the book) while not in combat.</em></li>
        <li><em><a idref="wpnmstry">Weaponmastery</a><ch.emdash/>adds 3 points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> (4 if you reached the Magnakai rank of <a idref="scion">Scion-Kai</a>) if using the <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> with which you are skilled.</em></li>
        <li><em><a idref="psisurge">Psi-surge</a><ch.emdash/>adds 4 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points to your total when used against an opponent who isn<ch.apos/>t immune, at the cost of 2 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points per round of combat. Mindblast can still be used to add two points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> without loss of endurance points. (If you reached the Magnakai rank of Archmaster, Psi-surge will add 6 points to <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> at the cost of 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point per round of combat and Mindblast will add 3 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points at no <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> penalty.)</em></li>
       </ul>
       <p><em>These bonuses are replaced by their Grand Master Discipline equivalent (e.g. acquiring <a idref="gwpnmtry">Grand Weaponmastery</a> in a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> with which you have <a idref="wpnmstry">Weaponmastery</a> gives you a +5 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> bonus<ch.emdash/>not +8).</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Now, through the pursuit of your new skills and the further development of your innate Kai abilities, you have set out upon a path of discovery that no other Kai Grand Master has ever attempted with success. Your determination to become the first Kai Supreme Master, by acquiring total proficiency in all twelve of the Grand Master Disciplines, is an awe-inspiring challenge. You will be venturing into the unknown, pushing back the boundaries of human limitation in the pursuit of greatness and the cause of Good. May the blessings of the gods Kai and Ishir go with you as you begin your brave and noble quest.</p>
      <p>In the years following the demise of the Darklords you have reached the rank of Kai Grand Defender, which means that you have mastered four of the Grand Master Disciplines listed below. It is up to you to choose which four Disciplines these are. As all of the Grand Master Disciplines will be of use to you at some point during your adventure, pick your four skills with care. The correct use of a Grand Master Discipline at the right time could save your life.</p>
      <p>When you have chosen your four Disciplines, enter them in the Grand Master Disciplines section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>If you have already completed one or more Grand Master adventures, you will already have picked your four initial Disciplines. You may add more Disciplines to your initial four as described later. It is quite possible that a particular Discipline will be of no use to you at all in a particular book which means that you should pick your Disciplines with even greater care.</em></p>
      </blockquote>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="gwpnmtry">
       <meta><title>Grand Weaponmastery</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>This Discipline enables a Grand Master to become supremely efficient in the use of all weapons. When you enter combat with one of your Grand Master weapons, you add 5 points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. The rank of Kai Grand Defender, with which you begin the Grand Master series, means you are skilled in two of the weapons listed overleaf.</p>
        <illustration class="inline">
         <meta>
          <creator>Brian Williams</creator>
         </meta>
         <instance class="html" src="weapons.gif" width="386" height="310" />
         <instance class="pdf" src="weapons.pdf" width="386" height="310" />
         <instance class="text" src="none" width="none" height="none" >
          <ul class="unbulleted">
           <li>Spear</li>
           <li>Dagger</li>
           <li>Mace</li>
           <li>Short Sword</li>
           <li>Warhammer</li>
           <li>Bow</li>
           <li>Quarterstaff</li>
           <li>Broadsword</li>
           <li>Axe</li>
           <li>Sword</li>
          </ul>
         </instance>
        </illustration>
      
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>When using a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>, you are typically asked to choose a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> to determine the success of your shot. If you choose Grand Weaponmastery with the <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>, you may add 3 to the number chosen. <!-- JDOUGAN: Does this supersede any relevant missile bonuses from Magnakai Disciplines? --></em></p>
        </blockquote>
        <p>The fact that you are skilled with two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> does not mean that you begin the adventure carrying any of them. However, you will have opportunities to acquire <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> during your adventure. For every Lone Wolf book that you complete in the Grand Master series, you may add an additional <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> to your list.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Possessing Grand Weaponmastery doesn<ch.apos/>t <strong>necessarily</strong> mean that you start out with that <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, but you might.</em></p>
        </blockquote>

        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>) These improvements and those for subsequent Grand Master Disciplines are listed here for your convenience.</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Sun Knight (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Knights with this discipline are able to wield <a idref="topics-twohandedweapons">two-handed weapons</a> (e.g. Broadsword, Quarterstaff, Spear, etc.) with full effect, using only one hand.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Lord (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Lords with this Discipline are able to cause the metal edge of any non-magical weapon to ignite and burn fiercely. When a weapon thus affected is used in combat, it inflicts an additional 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point loss upon an enemy in every successful round of combat. This ability cannot be used with a wholly wooden weapon such as a quarterstaff.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Crown (10 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Grand Crowns with this discipline are consummate masters of unarmed combat. When fighting bare-handed i.e., without any weapons, they may add 3 points to their <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="anmlmstr">
       <meta><title>Animal Mastery</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Grand Masters have considerable control over hostile, non-sentient creatures. Also, they have the ability to converse with birds and fishes, and use them as guides.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Kai Grand Guardian (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Grand Guardians with this discipline are able to  summon a limited number of forest animals to their location. The creatures so summoned will become loyal and willing allies, willing to do the Kai Grand Guardian<ch.apos/>s bidding. This ability can only be used in an outdoor setting.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Thane (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Thanes with this Discipline are able to command an animal to fall asleep at will. Some hostile animals may be able to resist this command, but most will be affected by it in some way. The duration of effect and the number of animals which can be affected at one time will increase as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Crown (10 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Crowns with this ability are able to plant in the mind of any animal the image of their most-feared predator or adversary. Under the influence of this illusion the animal will believe, with all of its senses, that it is being confronted by such a creature instead of a Kai Grand Crown.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Prince (11 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Sun Princes with this Discipline are able to alter their appearance, including clothing and equipment, to take on the guise of any animal that they may come into contact with. This physical change will only be witnessed by the animal in question.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="deliver">
       <meta><title>Deliverance (Advanced Curing)</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Grand Masters are able to use their healing power to repair serious battle wounds. If, whilst in combat, their <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> is reduced to 8 points or less, they can draw upon their mastery to restore 20 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. This ability can only be used once every 20 days.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>(see the <a idref="topics-healing">Healing</a> entry in the <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a>)</em></p>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Sun Knight (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Knights who possess this skill are able to repair serious wounds sustained by creatures other than themselves. By the laying of hands upon the affected creature<ch.apos/>s body, a Sun Knight can cause an open wound (or other serious injury) to mend itself. The speed at which this healing takes place increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Thane (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Thanes who possess this skill are able to conduct a Kai Exorcism. This ritual will banish any evil supernatural force that has taken possession of any goodly creature or object.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Thane (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Thanes with this Discipline are able to call upon the God Kai for divine assistance should a situation warrant it. Kai cannot intervene to save a Grand Thane from physical danger, but he can give signs which may help a Grand Thane chose the best course of action. A Grand Thane can call upon the God Kai for assistance no more than once every month. The frequency of divine audiences will increase as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Prince (11 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Princes with this ability are able to cause the regeneration of lost body parts, i.e. hands, feet, arms, legs, bones and internal organs.  This improved Discipline can be used to repair a Sun Prince<ch.apos/>s own body, or that of another person or creature. The time required to effect regeneration depends on the size and relative importance of the body part affected.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="assimila">
       <meta><title>Assimilance (Advanced Invisibility)</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Grand Masters are able to effect striking changes to their physical appearance, and maintain these changes over a period of a few days. They have also mastered advanced camouflage techniques that make them virtually undetectable in an open landscape.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Kai Grand Guardian (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Grand Guardians who possess this skill are able to create a cloud of fog-like vapour within 15 yards of their location. This fog will obscure both normal and infra-vision. The duration of the fog increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Lord (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Lords who possess this skill are able to cause the outline of their bodies to become blurred and indistinct. By so doing, they can greatly increase their chances of avoiding magical and/or non-magical missiles directed at them.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Thane (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Thanes who possess this skill are able to protect themselves from detection by creatures using infra-vision (the ability to see the heat radiating from a person or thing), or ultra-vision (the ability to detect objects or movement in the ultra-violet spectrum of light).</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Prince (11 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Sun Princes who possess this Discipline are able to create an illusory double of themselves and project this image up to a range of thirty feet. The Sun Prince must remain in visual contact with his/her image in order to maintain the illusion. Physical, magical, and psychic attacks upon the illusory image will cause no injury. The range of this ability increases substantially when a Sun Prince attains the rank of Kai Supreme Master.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="ghntmstr">
       <meta><title>Grand Huntmastery</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Grand Masters are able to see in total darkness, and have greatly heightened senses of touch and taste.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Kai Grand Guardian (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Grand Guardians with this skill enjoy increased mobility when travelling across all types of terrain, whether on foot or on horseback. This improved ability is very useful when used to outdistance a pursuing enemy.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Lord (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Sun Lords with this skill are able to see, with acute accuracy, light in the infrared spectrum, i.e. they can see complex patterns generated by heat in near or total darkness. They can also see light in the ultraviolet spectrum.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Thane (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Sun Thanes with this skill are able to protect themselves from the effects of being struck by natural electrical discharges, i.e. <!-- JDOUGAN: what we want here is e.g., not i.e. -->lightning.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Prince (11 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Sun Prince are able to control their direction and rate of movement when subjected to strong currents of air or water, or when venturing through non-material planes of existence, e.g., Shadow Gates.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="gpthmnshp">
       <meta><title>Grand Pathsmanship</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Grand Masters are able to resist entrapment by hostile plants, and have a super-awareness of ambush, or the threat of ambush, in woods and dense forests.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Sun Knight (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Sun Knights with this skill are able to repel at will all normal-sized insects within a radius of three yards. The range and numbers of insects so affected increases considerably as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Thane (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Thanes who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to alter the temperature of water by touch. By using this skill they are able to transform water into ice and vice versa. The volume of water affected, and  the duration of effect, both increase as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Crown (10 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Crowns with this skill are able to create a clear passageway through dense undergrowth, forest, or jungle. Once having passed through this passageway, the plant material will revert to its normal state. This skill can also be employed by a Kai Grand Crown against magical foliage, or to counter any plant material ranged against him by an enemy.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaisurge">
       <meta><title>Kai-surge</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>When using their psychic ability to attack an enemy, Grand Masters may add 8 points to their <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. For every round in which Kai-surge is used, Grand Masters need only deduct 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point. When using the weaker psychic attack<ch.emdash/><a idref="kaidiscl">Mindblast</a><ch.emdash/>they may add 4 points without loss of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. (Kai-surge, <a idref="psisurge">Psi-surge</a>, and <a idref="kaidiscl">Mindblast</a> cannot be used simultaneously.)</p>
        <p>Grand Masters cannot use Kai-surge if their <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score falls to 6 points or below.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Kai Grand Guardian (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Grand Guardians who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to attack up to three enemies in psychic combat simultaneously.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Lord (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Lords who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to launch a Kai-Blast<ch.emdash/>a pulse ofintense psychic energy which is capable of affecting both psychically active and inactive enemies. This form of psychic attack is very effective, more so than a usual Kai-surge, Psi-surge or Mindblast. It can cause an enemy to lose between 2 and 18 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points in one attack. However, use of a Kai-Blast will reduce a Sun Lord<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points total by 4. It cannot be used in conjunction with any other form of psychic attack.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Thane (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Thanes with this skill are able to focus their mind-power upon inanimate breakable objects, e.g., bottles, windows, all ceramics, urns, jugs etc, and cause them to explode violently. Any person or creature in close proximity to such an explosion risks injury from flying shrapnel.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Prince (11 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Princes who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to focus their psychic power into a Kai-Ray: a laser-like beam of mental energy capable of penetrating the strongest of psychic defences. This ability can be used once during a combat to reduce an enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score by 15 points. However, use of this Kai-Ray will also reduce a Sun Prince<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score by 4  points. It cannot be used if a Sun Prince<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score is 10 or less and it cannot be used in conjunction with any other form of psychic attack.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kaiscrn">
       <meta><title>Kai-screen</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>In psychic combat, Grand Masters are able to construct mind fortresses capable of protecting themselves and others. The strength and capacity of these fortresses eases as a Grand Master advances in rank.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Kai Grand Guardian (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Kai Grand Guardians who possess this Discipline are able to exercise a defensive psychic skill known as Mindblend. This cloaking ability enables them to both protect and hide their minds from being detected by a hostile psychic probe.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Thane (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Thanes who possess this Discipline are able to erect a special psychic defence called <quote>Mindfort</quote>. A Mindfort defence greatly reduces the effects of any psychic shock that would normally paralyse or weaken a lesser mortal.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Crown (10 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Crowns who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to mask the goodly aura which radiates naturally from their minds and bodies. Additionally, Grand Crowns can deliberately alter these auras to give a false impression of themselves to creatures who are sensitive to such psychic auras.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Prince (11 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Princes who possess this Discipline are able to create a mental sanctuary in which to keep safe their minds <!-- jdougan: [IMHO - keep their minds safe] -->from psychic assault. Creation of this sanctuary does not require thought or concentration; it occurs instantly whenever a Kai Sun Prince is subjected to psychic attack. The defensive strength of this sanctuary further increases when a Sun Prince attains the rank of Kai Supreme Master.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="grnexus">
       <meta><title>Grand Nexus</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Grand Masters are able to withstand contact with harmful elements, such as flames and acids, for upwards of an hour in duration. This ability increases as a Grand Master advances in rank.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Sun Knight (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Knights who possess Mastery of this Distipline are able to feign death. By placing themselves into a state of suspended animation, outwardly they are able to achieve all semblance of being truly dead. However, whilst in this state the only sense that a Sun Knight retains is the ability to hear.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Thane (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Thanes who possess mastery of this Discipline can pass freely through the Shadow Gates. These phenomena are special portals which enable one to access other dimensions and planes of existence outside of Magnamund. Kai Grand Thanes are able to detect the location of Shadow Gates and pass through them without suffering any physical ill effects. The range of their detection increases as a Kai Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Crown (10 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Crowns who possess this Discipline are able to speak a Kai Power Word<ch.emdash/>a holy utterance which will cause physical and psychic damage to any single creature within a radius of thirty feet. The degree of damage so caused, and the resultant drain upon a Grand Crown<ch.apos/>s reserves of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>, are dependent upon individual circumstances. The power and range of this skill increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="gnosis">
       <meta><title>Telegnosis (Advanced Divination)</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>This skill may warn a Kai Master of imminent or unseen danger or enable him to detect an invisible or hidden enemy. It may also reveal the true purpose or intent of a stranger or strange object encountered in your adventure. Divination may enable you to communicate telepathically with another person and to sense if a creature possesses psychic abilities.</p>
        <p>If you choose this skill, write <quote>Divination</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Sun Knight (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Knights who possess this Discipline are able to communicate telepathically over great distances. Initially the range of this ability is approximately 100 miles, but this distance increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Lord (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Sun Lords who possess this Discipline are able to alter their body-weight in order to walk successfully upon different kinds of surface, e.g., water, mud, lava and quicksand. Time duration and degree of surface difficulty increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Thane (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd><p><em>Grand Thanes who possess this Discipline are able to detect the exact location of precious gems, and valuable metals such as gold, platinum and silver. These minerals and metals may occur naturally in the ground or they could be part of a hidden treasure hoard. The range of this ability is limited at first, but increases steadily as a Kai Grand Master rises in rank.</em></p></dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>
      
      <section class="mainmatter" id="magi">
       <meta><title>Magi-magic</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Under the tutelage of Lord Rimoah, you have been able to master the rudimentary skills of battle magic, as taught to the Vakeros<ch.emdash/>the native warriors of Dessi. As you advance in rank, so will your knowledge and mastery of Old Kingdom magic increase.</p>
       <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Kai Grand Guardian (5 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd>
            <p><em>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Kai Grand Guardian are able to use the following battle-spells of the Elder Magi:</em></p>
            <ul>
             <li><em>Splinter<ch.emdash/>This causes breakable items such as bottles, jugs, mirrors, windows, etc., to shatter to pieces. The range of this spell increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></li>
             <li><em>Flameshaft<ch.emdash/>This causes the tip of any arrow, or arrow-like missile, to burn fiercely with a magical flame which cannot readily be extinguished by normal means.</em></li>
            </ul>
           </dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Lord (7 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd>
            <p><em>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Sun Lord are able to use the following battle-spells of the Elder Magi:</em></p>
            <ul>
             <li><em>Penetrate<ch.emdash/>This increases the penetrative energy of any arrow, or arrow-like missile, launched by a Sun Lord.</em></li>
             <li><em>Energy Grasp<ch.emdash/>This spell enables a Sun Lord to discharge a powerful electrical force into anything he or she touches. It is similar in effect to the Brotherhood spell <quote>Lightning Hand</quote>, but differs in that it is easier to control and channel the resulting energy. It also requires the actual touching of an object or an enemy to effect the spell.</em></li>
            </ul>
           </dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Thane (9 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd>
            <p><em>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Grand Thane are able to use the following Old Kingdom Battle-spells:</em></p>
            <ul>
             <li><em>Power Glyph<ch.emdash/>By inscribing this ancient glyph (a secret magical symbol) upon a door, an archway, or even upon the lid of a closed box, a Kai Grand Thane is able to protect items or portals from being opened. Any creature attempting to open a portal protected in such a way will release the power of the glyph and suffer its deadly effects.</em></li>
             <li><em>Hold Enemy<ch.emdash/>Using this spell, a Kai Grand Thane is able to immobilize a single hostile creature anywhere within twenty feet of themselves. The duration of the spell is dependent upon the size and strength of the targetted creature. The range and duration of effect of this spell increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></li>
            </ul>
           </dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="kai-alchemy">
       <meta><title>Kai-alchemy</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>Under the tutelage of Guildmaster Banedon, you have mastered the elementary spells of left-handed magic, as practised by the Brotherhood of the Crystal Star. As you advance in rank, so will your knowledge and mastery of left-handed magic increase, enabling you to craft new Kai weapons and artefacts.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>Improvements: (see <a idref="gmimprv">Improved Grand Master Disciplines</a> and <a idref="gmlevels">Levels of Grand Mastership</a>)</em></p>
         <dl class="paragraphed">
          <dt><em>Sun Knight (6 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd>
            <p><em>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Sun Knight are able to use the following Brotherhood spells:</em></p>
            <ul>
             <li><em>Halt Missile<ch.emdash/>This causes any projected or hurled missile (i.e. arrows, axes, crossbow bolts, etc.) which may pose an immediate threat to the life of a Sun Knight, to cease its flight and remain stationary in mid-air. The effect of the spell lasts for 2<ch.endash/>3 seconds, allowing the Sun Knight sufficient time to move away from its line of flight. Initially only one missile can be affected by this spell, but the number lncreases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></li>
             <li><em>Strength<ch.emdash/>By casting this spell, a Sun Knight is able to greatly increase his or her physical strength for a short duration. It can be used to lift or move heavy objects, or to effect a temporary increase in <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> scores whilst fighting an enemy in unarmed combat.</em></li>
            </ul>
           </dd>
          <dt><em>Sun Thane (8 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd>
            <p><em>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Sun Thane we able to use the following Brotherhood spells:</em></p>
            <ul>
             <li><em>Slow Fall<ch.emdash/>By casting this spell, Kai Sun Thanes are able to slow their rate of free-falling to three feet per second, thereby avoiding damage upon landing while the spell is in effect. The duration of the spell is limited at first, but it steadily increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></li>
             <li><em>Breathe Water<ch.emdash/>Using this spell, a Kai Sun Thane is able to breathe underwater for ten minutes. The duration of effect increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</em></li>
            </ul>
           </dd>
          <dt><em>Grand Crown (10 Disciplines)</em></dt>
           <dd>
            <p><em>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Grand Crown are able to use the following Brotherhood spells:</em></p>
            <ul>
             <li><em>Teleport<ch.emdash/>By casting this spell, Kai Grand Crowns can transport themselves physically to any place which they can see with their own eyes. The spell will carry the caster, his equipment and clothing to his chosen sighted destination. It cannot be used on any other living creature and it will not transport any other living creature along with the caster. Use of this spell will cost the caster between 1 and 5 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points every time it is used. This cost reduces as a Kai Grand Master increases in rank.</em></li>
             <li><em>See Illusion<ch.emdash/>Using this spell, a Kai Grand Crown is able to detect an illusion and know immediately its true identity or purpose.</em></li>
            </ul>
           </dd>
         </dl>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <p>If you successfully complete the mission as set in this, the first of the Lone Wolf Grand Master series, you may add a further Grand Master Discipline of your choice to your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> in <bookref series="lw" book="14tcok">Book 14</bookref>.</p>

      <p>For every Grand Master Discipline you possess, in excess of the original four disciplines you begin with, you may add 1 point to your basic <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> score and 2 points to your basic <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points score. These bonus points, together with your extra Grand Master Discipline, your original four Grand Master Disciplines, and any Special Items that you have found and been able to keep during your adventures, may then be carried over and used in the next Grand Master adventure.</p>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="gmeqpmnt">
     <meta>
      <title>[Grand Master] Equipment</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="gmdisc" />
      <link class="next" idref="gmcmbt" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>The way in which you obtain your equipment before the adventure varies greatly from book to book. What follows is a fairly common scenario intended to give you a feel for what to expect, but it may be very different from a particular book you read. Please carefully read the Equipment section of the book you are playing to find out its particular details.</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>Before leaving on your journey, you are given a map of the area, and a pouch of gold. To find out how much gold is in the pouch, pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>. Add 10 to the number you have picked. The total equals the number of <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> inside the pouch, and you should now enter this number in the <quote><a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></quote> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. If you have successfully completed previous Lone Wolf adventures, you may add this sum to the total sum of Crowns you already possess. You can carry a maximum of only fifty Crowns, but additional Crowns can be left in <a idref="topics-safekeeping">safekeeping</a> at your Kai monastery.</p>
      <p>You are offered a choice of equipment to aid you on your perilous mission. You can take three items from the list below, again adding to these, if necessary, any you may already possess. However, remember that you can carry a maximum of two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> and ten <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a>.</p>
      <blockquote>
       <p><em>(see the <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a> for details about a particular item)</em></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>List the three items that you choose on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>, under the heading given in brackets, and make a note of any effect they may have on your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points or <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="gmhwcry">
       <meta><title>How to Carry Equipment</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>Now that you have your equipment, the following list shows you how it is carried. You do not need to make notes, but you should refer back to this list in the course of your adventure.</p>
        <blockquote>
         <p><em>(see the <a idref="topics">Topical Guide</a> for details about a particular item)</em></p>
        </blockquote>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="gmmhcry">
       <meta><title>How Much Can You Carry?</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a></dt>
          <dd><p>The maximum number of <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> that you may carry is two.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a></dt>
          <dd><p>These must be stored in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. Because space is limited, you may keep a maximum of only ten articles, including Meals, in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a> at any one time.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a></dt>
          <dd>
           <p><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> are not carried in the <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. When you discover a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, you will be told how to carry it.</p>
           <p>The maximum number of <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> that can be carried on any adventure is twelve. Surplus <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> may be left for safekeeping at your Kai monastery.</p>
          </dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></dt>
          <dd><p>These are always carried in the <a idref="topics-beltpouch">Belt Pouch</a>. It will hold a maximum of fifty Crowns.</p></dd>
         <dt>Food</dt>
          <dd><p>Food is carried in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. Each Meal counts as one item.</p></dd>
        </dl>
        <p>Any item that may be of use and can be picked up on your adventure and entered on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> is given initial capitals (e.g. Gold Dagger, Magic Pendant) in the text. Unless you are told it is a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, carry it in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="gmhowuz">
       <meta><title>How to Use Your Equipment</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a></dt>
          <dd><p><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> aid you in combat. If you have the Grand Master Discipline of Grand Weaponmastery and a correct <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, it adds 5 points to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. If you find a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> during the adventure, you may pick it up and use it. (Remember that you can only carry two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> at once.)</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> and <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrows</a></dt>
          <dd>
           <p>During your adventure there will be opportunities to use a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> and <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrow</a>. If you equip yourself with this <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, and you possess at least one <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrow</a>, you may use it when the text of a particular section allows you to do so. The <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> is a useful <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, for it enables you to hit an enemy at a distance. However, a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> cannot be used in hand-to-hand combat, therefore it is strongly recommended that you also equip yourself with a close combat <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>, like a <a idref="topics-sword">Sword</a> or <a idref="topics-mace">Mace</a>.</p>
           <p>In order to use a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> you must possess a <a idref="topics-quiver">Quiver</a> and at least one <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrow</a>. Each time the <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> is used, erase an <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrow</a> from your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. A <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> cannot, of course, be used if you exhaust your supply of <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrows</a>, but the opportunity may arise during your adventure for you to replenish your stock of <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrows</a>.</p>
           <p>If you have the Grand Master Discipline of <a idref="gwpnmtry">Grand Weaponmastery</a> with a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>, you may add 3 to any number that you choose from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>, when using the <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>.</p>
          </dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a></dt>
          <dd><p>During your travels you will discover various useful items which you may wish to keep. (Remember you can only carry a maximum of ten items in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a> at anytime.) You may exchange or discard them at any point when you are not involved in combat.</p></dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a></dt>
          <dd>
           <p><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> are not carried in the <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. When you discover a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, you will be told how to carry it. If you have successfully completed previous Lone Wolf books, you may already possess <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a>.</p>
           <p>The maximum number of <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> that a Kai Master can carry during an adventure is twelve. Surplus <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> may be left in safekeeping at your Kai monastery.</p>
          </dd>
         <dt><a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></dt>
          <dd><p>The currency of Anari is the Lune, but <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> are readily accepted at an exchange rate of four Lune for every 1 <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crown</a>.</p></dd>
         <dt>Food</dt>
          <dd>
           <p>You will need to eat regularly during your adventure. If you do not have any food when you are instructed to eat a Meal, you will lose 3 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. If you have chosen the Grand Master Discipline of <a idref="ghntmstr">Grand Huntmastery</a> as one of your skills, you will not need to tick off a Meal when instructed to eat.</p>
           <blockquote>
            <p><em><a idref="hntmstry">Huntmastery</a> may also be useful as noted in <a idref="gmdisc">Magnakai Disciplines</a>.</em></p>
           </blockquote>
          </dd>
         <dt>Potion of <a idref="topics-laumspur">Laumspur</a></dt>
          <dd><p>This is a healing potion that can restore 4 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to your total when swallowed after combat. There is enough for one dose only. If you discover any other potion during the adventure, you will be informed of its effect. All potions are <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a>.</p></dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="gmcmbt">
     <meta>
      <title>[Grand Master] Rules for Combat</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="gmeqpmnt" />
      <link class="next" idref="gmlevels" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>There will be occasions during your adventure when you have to fight an enemy. The enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points are given in the text. Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s aim in the combat is to kill the enemy by reducing his <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to zero while losing as few <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points as possible himself.</p>
      <p>At the start of a combat, enter Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s and the enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points in the appropriate boxes on the Combat Record section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. The sequence for combat is as follows:</p>
      <ol class="paragraphed"> 
       <li><p>Add any extra points gained through your Grand Master Disciplines and Special Items to your current <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> total.</p></li>
       <li>
        <p>Subtract the <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of your enemy from this total. The result is your Combat Ratio. Enter it on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
        <p>Example</p>
        <p>Lone Wolf (<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> 28) is attacked by a pack of Doomwolves (<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> 30). He is taken by surprise and is not given the opportunity of evading their attack. Lone Wolf has the Grand Master Discipline of Kai-surge to which the Doomwolves are not immune, so Lone Wolf adds 8 points to his <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>, giving him a total <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of 36.</p>
        <p>He subtracts the Doomwolf pack<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> from his own, giving a Combat Ratio of +6. (36-30 = +6). +6 is noted on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> as the Combat Ratio.</p>
       </li>
       <li><p><a id="kai-stage3">When you have your Combat Ratio</a>, pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>.</p></li>
       <li>
        <p>Turn to the Combat Results Table on the inside back cover of this book. Along the top of the chart are shown the Combat Ratio numbers. Find the number that is the same as your Combat Ratio and cross-reference it with the random number that you have picked (the random numbers appear on the side of the chart). You now have the number of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost by both Lone Wolf and his enemy in this round of combat. (E represents points lost by the enemy; LW represents points lost by Lone Wolf.)</p>
        <p>Example</p>
        <p>The Combat Ratio between Lone Wolf and the Doomwolf Pack has been established as +6. If the number picked from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> is a 2, then the result of the first round of combat is:</p>
        <ul>
         <li>Lone Wolf loses 3 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points (plus an additional 1 point for using Kai-surge).</li>
         <li>Doomwolf Pack loses 7 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points.</li>
        </ul>
       </li>

       <li><p>On the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>, mark the changes in <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to the participants in the combat.</p></li>

       <li><p>Unless otherwise instructed, or unless you have an option to evade, the next round of combat now starts.</p></li>

       <li><p>Repeat the sequence from <a idref="kai-stage3">Stage 3.</a></p></li>
      </ol>

      <p>This process of combat continues until <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points of either the enemy or Lone Wolf are reduced to zero, at which point the one with the zero score is declared dead. If Lone Wolf is dead, the adventure is over. If the enemy is dead, Lone Wolf proceeds but with his <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points reduced.</p>
      <p>A summary of Combat Rules appears on the page after the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>.</p>

      <section class="frontmatter" id="kevasion">
       <meta><title>Evasion of Combat</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>During your adventure you may be given the chance to evade combat. If you have already engaged in a round of combat and decide to evade, calculate the combat for that round in the usual manner. All points lost by the enemy as a result of that round are ignored, and you make your escape. Only Lone Wolf may lose <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points during that round (but then that is the risk of running away!). You may evade only if the text of the particular section allows you to do so.</p>
       </data>
      </section>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="gmlevels">
     <meta>
      <title>Levels of Grand Mastership</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="gmcmbt" />
      <link class="next" idref="gmimprv" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>The following table is a guide to the rank and titles you can achieve at each stage of your journey along the road of Kai Grand Mastership. As you successfully complete each adventure in the Lone Wolf Grand Master series, you will gain an additional Grand Master Discipline and progress towards the pinnacle of Kai perfection<ch.emdash/>to become a Kai Supreme Master.</p>
      <ol>
       <li>Kai Grand Master Senior</li> 
       <li>Kai Grand Master Superior</li>
       <li>Kai Grand Sentinel</li>
       <li>Kai Grand Defender<ch.emdash/><em>You begin the Lone Wolf Grand Master adventures at this level of Mastery</em></li>
       <li>Kai Grand Guardian</li>
       <li>Sun Knight</li>
       <li>Sun Lord</li>
       <li>Sun Thane</li>
       <li>Grand Thane</li>
       <li>Grand Crown</li>
       <li>Sun Prince</li>
       <li>Kai Supreme Master</li>
      </ol>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="gmimprv">
     <meta>
      <title>Improved [Grand Master] Disciplines</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="gmlevels" />
      <link class="next" idref="norulz" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>As you rise through the higher levels of Kai Grand Mastery, you will find that your Disciplines will steadily improve. For example, If you possess the Discipline of Grand Nexus when you reach the Grand Master rank of Grand Thane, you will be able to pass freely through Shadow Gates and explore the nether realms of Aon and the Daziarn Plane.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="guardian">
       <meta><title>Kai Grand Guardian</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>If you are a Grand Master who has reached the rank of Kai Grand Guardian (5 Disciplines), you will now benefit from improvements to the following Grand Master Disciplines:</p>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Animal Mastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Grand Guardians with this discipline are able to  summon a limited number of forest animals to their location. The creatures so summoned will become loyal and willing allies, willing to do the Kai Grand Guardian<ch.apos/>s bidding. This ability can only be used in an outdoor setting.</p></dd>
         <dt>Assimilance</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Grand Guardians who possess this skill are able to create a cloud of fog-like vapour within 15 yards of their location. This fog will obscure both normal and infra-vision. The duration of the fog increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Huntmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Grand Guardians with this skill enjoy increased mobility when travelling across all types of terrain, whether on foot or on horseback. This improved ability is very useful when used to outdistance a pursuing enemy.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-surge</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Grand Guardians who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to attack up to three enemies in psychic combat simultaneously.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-screen</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Grand Guardians who possess this Discipline are able to exercise a defensive psychic skill known as Mindblend. This cloaking ability enables them to both protect and hide their minds from being detected by a hostile psychic probe.</p></dd>
         <dt>Magi-Magic</dt>
          <dd>
           <p>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Kai Grand Guardian are able to use the following battle-spells of the Elder Magi:</p>
           <ul>
            <li>Splinter<ch.emdash/>This causes breakable items such as bottles, jugs, mirrors, windows, etc[.], to shatter to pieces. The range of this spell increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</li>
            <li>Flameshaft<ch.emdash/>This causes the tip of any arrow, or arrow-like missile, to burn fiercely with a magical flame which cannot readily be extinguished by normal means.</li>
           </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="sunkght">
       <meta><title>Sun Knight</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>If you are a Grand Master who has reached the rank of Sun Knight (6 Disciplines), you will now benefit from improvements to the following Grand Master Disciplines:</p>
        <dl class="paragraphed">  
         <dt>Grand Weaponmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Knights with this discipline are able to wield <a idref="topics-twohandedweapons">two-handed weapons</a> (e.g. Broadsword, Quarterstaff, Spear, etc.) with full effect, using only one hand.</p></dd>
         <dt>Deliverance</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Knights who possess this skill are able to repair serious wounds sustained by creatures other than themselves. By the laying of hands upon the affected creature<ch.apos/>s body, a Sun Knight can cause an open wound (or other serious injury) to mend itself. The speed at which this healing takes place increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Pathsmanship</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Sun Knights with this skill are able to repel at will all normal-sized insects within a radius of three yards. The range and numbers of insects so affected increases considerably as a Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Nexus</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Knights who possess Mastery of this Distipline are able to feign death. By placing themselves into a state of suspended animation, outwardly they are able to achieve all semblance of being truly dead. However, whilst in this state the only sense that a Sun Knight retains is the ability to hear.</p></dd>
         <dt>Telegnosis</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Knights who possess this Discipline are able to communicate telepathically over great distances. Initially the range of this ability is approximately 100 miles, but this distance increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-alchemy</dt>
          <dd>
           <p>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Sun Knight are able to use the following Brotherhood spells:</p>
           <ul>
            <li>Halt Missile<ch.emdash/>This causes any projected or hurled missile (i.e. arrows, axes, crossbow bolts, etc.) which may  pose an immediate threat to the life of a Sun Knight, to cease its flight and remain stationary in mid-air. The effect of the spell lasts for 2<ch.endash/>3 seconds, allowing the Sun Knight sufficient time to move away from its line of flight. Initially only one missile can be affected by  this spell, but the number lncreases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</li>
            <li>Strength<ch.emdash/>By casting this spell, a Sun Knight is able to greatly increase his or her physical strength for a short duration. It can be used to lift or move heavy objects, or to effect a temporary increase in <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> scores whilst fighting an enemy in unarmed combat.</li>
           </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="sunlord">
       <meta><title>Sun Lord</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>If you are a Grand Master who has reached the rank of Sun Lord (7 Disciplines), you will now benefit from improvements to the following Grand Master Disciplines:</p>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Grand Weaponmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Lords with this Discipline are able to cause the metal edge of any non-magical weapon to ignite and burn fiercely. When a weapon thus affected is used in combat, it inflicts an additional 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point loss upon an enemy in every successful round of combat. This ability cannot be used with a wholly wooden weapon such as a quarterstaff.</p></dd>
         <dt>Assimilance</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Lords who possess this skill are able to cause the outline of their bodies to become blurred and indistinct. By so doing, they can greatly increase their chances of avoiding magical and/or non-magical missiles directed at them.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Huntmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Sun Lords with this skill are able to see, with acute accuracy, light in the infrared spectrum, ie. they can see complex patterns generated by heat in near or total darkness. They can also see light in the ultraviolet spectrum.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-surge</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Lords who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to launch a Kai-Blast<ch.emdash/>a pulse ofintense psychic energy which is capable of affecting both psychically active and inactive enemies. This form of psychic attack is very effective, more so than a usual Kai-surge, Psi-surge or Mindblast. It can cause an enemy to lose between 2 and 18 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points in one attack. However, use of a Kai-Blast will reduce a Sun Lord<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points total by 4. It cannot be used in conjunction with any other form of psychic attack.</p></dd>
         <dt>Telegnosis</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Lords who possess this Discipline are able to alter their body-weight in order to walk successfully upon different kinds of surface, eg: water, mud, lava and quicksand. Time duration and degree of surface difficulty increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Magi-magic</dt>
          <dd>
           <p>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Sun Lord are able to use the following battle-spells of the Elder Magi:</p>
           <ul>
            <li>Penetrate<ch.emdash/>This increases the penetrative energy of any arrow, or arrow-like missile, launched by a Sun Lord.</li>
            <li>Energy Grasp<ch.emdash/>This spell enables a Sun Lord to discharge a powerful electrical force into anything he or she touches. It is similar in effect to the Brotherhood spell <quote>Lightning Hand</quote>, but differs in that it is easier to control and channel the resulting energy. It also requires the actual touching of an object or an enemy to effect the spell.</li>
           </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="sunthane">
       <meta><title>Sun Thane</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>If you are a Grand Master who has reached the rank of Sun Thane (8 Disciplines), you will now benefit from improvements to the following Grand Master Disciplines:</p>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Animal Mastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Thanes with this Discipline are able to command an animal to fall asleep at will. Some hostile animals may be able to resist this command, but most will be affected by it in some way. The duration of effect and the number of animals which can be affected at one time will increase as a Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Deliverance</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Thanes who possess this skill are able to conduct a Kai Exorcism. This ritual will banish any evil supernatural force that has taken possession of any goodly creature or object.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Huntmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Sun Thanes with this skill are able to protect themselves from the effects of being struck by natural electrical discharges, ie. <!-- JDOUGAN: I think that we want e.g. and not i.e. --> [i.e.] lightning.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Pathsmanship</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Thanes who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to alter the temperature of water by touch. By using this skill they are able to transform water into ice and vice versa. The volume of water affected, and  the duration of effect, both increase as a Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-screen</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Thanes who possess this Discipline are able to erect a special psychic defence called <quote>Mindfort</quote>. A Mindfort defence greatly reduces the effects of any psychic shock that would normally paralyse or weaken a lesser mortal.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-alchemy</dt>
          <dd>
           <p>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Sun Thane we able to use the following Brotherhood spells:</p>
           <ul>
            <li>Slow Fall<ch.emdash/>By casting this spell, Kai Sun Thanes are able to slow their rate of free-falling to three feet per second, thereby avoiding damage upon landing while the spell is in effect. The duration of the spell is limited at first, but it steadily increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</li>
            <li>Breathe Water<ch.emdash/>Using this spell, a Kai Sun Thane is able to breathe underwater for ten minutes. The duration of effect increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</li>
           </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="grthane">
       <meta><title>Grand Thane</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>If you are a Kai Grand Master who has reached the rank of Grand Thane (9 Disciplines), you will now benefit from improvements to the following Grand Master Disciplines:</p>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Deliverance</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Thanes with this Discipline are able to call upon the God Kai for divine assistance should a situation warrant it. Kai cannot intervene to save a Grand Thane from physical danger, but he can give signs which may help a Grand Thane chose the best course of action. A Grand Thane can call upon the God Kai for assistance no more than once every month. The frequency of divine audiences will increase as a Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Assimilance</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Thanes who possess this skill are able to protect themselves from detection by creatures using infra-vision (the ability to see the heat radiating from a person or thing), or ultra-vision (the ability to detect objects or movement in the ultra-violet spectrum of light).</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-surge</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Thanes with this skill are able to focus their mind-power upon inanimate breakable objects, eg, bottles, windows, all ceramics, urns, jugs etc, and cause them to explode violently. Any person or creature in close proximity to such an explosion risks injury from flying shrapnel.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Nexus</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Thanes who possess mastery of this Discipline can pass freely through the Shadow Gates. These phenomena are special portals which enable one to access other dimensions and planes of existence outside of Magnamund. Kai Grand Thanes are able to detect the location of Shadow Gates and pass through them without suffering any physical ill effects. The range of their detection increases as a Kai Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Telegnosis</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Thanes who possess this Discipline are able to detect the exact location of precious gems, and valuable metals such as gold, platinum and silver. These minerals and metals may occur naturally in the ground or they could be part of a hidden treasure hoard. The range of this ability is limited at first, but increases steadily as a Kai Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Magi-magic</dt>
          <dd>
           <p>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Grand Thane are able to use the following Old Kingdom Battle-spells:</p>
           <ul>
            <li>Power Glyph<ch.emdash/>By inscribing this ancient glyph (a secret magical symbol) upon a door, an archway, or even upon the lid of a closed box, a Kai Grand Thane is able to protect items or portals from being opened. Any creature attempting to open a portal protected in such a way will release the power of the glyph and suffer its deadly effects.</li>
            <li>Hold Enemy<ch.emdash/>Using this spell, a Kai Grand Thane is able to immobilize a single hostile creature anywhere within twenty feet of themselves. The duration of the spell is dependent upon the size and strength of the targetted creature. The range and duration of effect of this spell increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</li>
           </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="grcrown">
       <meta><title>Grand Crown</title></meta>
      <data>
        <p>If you are a Grand Master who has reached the rank of Grand Crown (10 Disciplines), you will now benefit from improvements to the following Grand Master Disciplines:</p>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Grand Weaponmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Grand Crowns with this discipline are consummate masters of unarmed combat. When fighting bare-handed ie, without any weapons, they may add 3 points to their <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</p></dd>
         <dt>Animal Mastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Crowns with this ability are able to plant in the mind of any animal the image of their most-feared predator or adversary. Under the influence of this illusion the animal will believe, with all of its senses, that it is being confronted by such a creature instead of a Kai Grand Crown.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Pathsmanship</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Crowns with this skill are able to create a clear passageway through dense undergrowth, forest, or jungle. Once having passed through this passageway, the plant material will revert to its normal state. This skill can also be employed by a Kai Grand Crown against magical foliage, or to counter any plant material ranged against him by an enemy.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-screen</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Crowns who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to mask the goodly aura which radiates naturally from their minds and bodies. Additionally, Grand Crowns can deliberately alter these auras to give a false impression of themselves to creatures who are sensitive to such psychic auras.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Nexus</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Crowns who possess this Discipline are able to speak a Kai Power Word<ch.emdash/>a holy utterance which will cause physical and psychic damage to any single creature within a radius of thirty feet. The degree of damage so caused, and the resultant drain upon a Grand Crown<ch.apos/>s reserves of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>, are dependent upon individual circumstances. The power and range of this skill increases as a Grand Master rises in rank.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-alchemy</dt>
          <dd>
           <p>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Grand Crown are able to use the following Brotherhood spells:</p>
           <ul>
            <li>Teleport<ch.emdash/>By casting this spell, Kai Grand Crowns can transport themselves physically to any place which they can see with their own eyes. The spell will carry the caster, his equipment and clothing to his chosen sighted destination. It cannot be used on any other living creature and it will not transport any other living creature along with the caster. Use of this spell will cost the caster between 1 and 5 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points every time it is used. This cost reduces as a Kai Grand Master increases in rank.</li>
            <li>See Illusion<ch.emdash/>Using this spell, a Kai Grand Crown is able to detect an illusion and know immediately its true identity or purpose.</li>
           </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="sunprinc">
       <meta><title>Sun Prince</title></meta>
       <data>
        <p>If you are a Grand Master who has reached the rank of Sun Prince (11 Disciplines), you will now benefit from improvements to the following Grand Master Disciplines:</p>
        <dl class="paragraphed">
         <dt>Animal Mastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Sun Princes with this Discipline are able to alter their appearance, including clothing and equipment, to take on the guise of any animal that they may come into contact with. This physical change will only be witnessed by the animal in question.</p></dd>
         <dt>Deliverance</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Princes with this ability are able to cause the regeneration of lost body parts, ie, [i.e.] hands, feet, arms, legs, bones and internal organs.  This improved Discipline can be used to repair a Sun Prince<ch.apos/>s own body, or that of another person or creature. The time required to effect regeneration depends on the size and relative importance of the body part affected.</p></dd>
         <dt>Assimilance</dt>
          <dd><p>Kai Sun Princes who possess this Discipline are able to create an illusory double of themselves and project this image up to a range of thirty feet. The Sun Prince must remain in visual contact with his/her image in order to maintain the illusion. Physical, magical, and psychic attacks upon the illusory image will cause no injury. The range of this ability increases substantially when a Sun Prince attains the rank of Kai Supreme Master.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-surge</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Princes who possess mastery of this Discipline are able to focus their psychic power into a Kai-Ray: a laser-like beam of mental energy capable of penetrating the strongest of psychic defences. This ability can be used once during a combat to reduce an enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score by 15 points. However, use of this Kai-Ray will also reduce a Sun Prince<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score by 4  points. It cannot be used if a Sun Prince<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score is 10 or less and it cannot be used in conjunction with any other form of psychic attack.</p></dd>
         <dt>Kai-screen</dt>
          <dd><p>Sun Princes who possess this Discipline are able to create a mental sanctuary in which to keep safe their minds <!-- JDOUGAN: [IMHO - keep their minds safe] -->from psychic assault. Creation of this sanctuary does not require thought or concentration; it occurs instantly whenever a Kai Sun Prince is subjected to psychic attack. The defensive strength of this sanctuary further increases when a Sun Prince attains the rank of Kai Supreme Master.</p></dd>
         <dt>Grand Huntmastery</dt>
          <dd><p>Grand Masters who have reached the rank of Sun Prince are able to control their direction and rate of movement when subjected to strong currents of air or water, or when venturing through non-material planes of existence, eg, [e.g.] Shadow Gates.</p></dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>
     </data>
    </section>
   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="mainmatter" id="norulz">
   <meta>
    <title>The [New Order] Game Rules</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="gmimprv" />
    <link class="next" idref="wrldrulz" />
   </meta>
   <data>

    <p>This portion of the booklet is yet to be completed.</p>

   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="mainmatter" id="wrldrulz">
   <meta>
    <title>The [World of Lone Wolf] Game Rules</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="norulz" />
    <link class="next" idref="powers" />
   </meta>

   <data>
    <p>To keep a record of your adventure, use the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
    <p>Before you set off on your adventure, you must discover how well your Shianti masters have prepared you for your quest by determining your fighting prowess<ch.emdash/><a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a><ch.emdash/>your state of mind<ch.emdash/><a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a><ch.emdash/>and your physical stamina<ch.emdash/><a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>. To do this take a pencil and, with eyes closed, point with the blunt end of it on to the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>. If you pick 0 it counts as zero.</p>
    <p>The first number that you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> in this way represents your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. Add 10 to the number you picked and write the total in the <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>. (e.g., if your pencil fell on the number 4 in the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> you would write in a <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of 14.) When you fight, your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> will be pitted against that of your enemy. A high score in this section is therefore very desirable.</p>
    <p>The second number that you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> represents your <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a>. Add 20 to this number and write the total in the <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> (e.g., if your pencil fell on the number 6 in the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> you would have a <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> of 26). If you decide to use a spell or utilize the power of your <a idref="topics-wizardsstaff">Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</a>, then you will lose <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points. If at any time your <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> falls to zero, you may not use any of your spells or your <a idref="topics-wizardsstaff">Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</a>. Lost <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points can be regained during the course of the adventure, and it is possible for your <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points to rise above the total with which you start your adventure.</p>
    <p>The third number that you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> represents your powers of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>. Add 20 to this number and write the total in the <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> (e.g., if your pencil fell on the number 6 on the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> you would have 26 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points). If you are wounded in combat, you will lose <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points. If at any time your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points fall to zero, you are dead and the adventure is over. Lost <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points can be regained during the course of the adventure but can never rise above the number with which you start your adventure.</p>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="powers">
     <meta>
      <title>Magical Powers</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="wrldrulz" />
      <link class="next" idref="weqpmnt" />
     </meta>

     <data>

      <p>When you start your adventure, your education in the ways of wizardry is incomplete. You have mastered only <em>five</em> of the seven magical powers that the Shianti call the <typ class="ital">lesser magicks</typ>. The choice of which five powers these are, is up to you. All of the lesser magicks will be of use to you at some point on your quest, so choose them with care. Your survival may depend on the correct use of a magical power at the right time.</p>
      <p>The seven magical powers available to you are listed below. When you have chosen your five powers, enter them in the Magical Powers section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="sorcery">
       <meta><title>Sorcery</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>This power allows a wizard to transform his thoughts or desires into magical energy. By concentration of the will it is possible to create magical shields of force to bar doors or move objects. Sorcery drains more <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points than any other Magical Power, and is most effective when your <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points are high.</p>
        <p>If you choose this power, write <quote>Sorcery</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="enchant">
       <meta><title>Enchantment</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>The power of Enchantment enables a wizard to charm or beguile other creatures, and create illusions in the minds of others. He will be able to extract information from others, place thoughts and compulsions into another<ch.apos/>s mind or cause them to believe that imaginary events are actually taking place. Some magical or highly intelligent beings may be immune to the powers of Enchantment</p>
        <p>If you choose this power, write <quote>Enchantment</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="elementl">
       <meta><title>Elementalism</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>The Power of elemental magic allows a wizard some control over the natural elements of Air, Fire, Earth and Water. By entering a trance and chanting incantations, you may summon aid from the spirits of the Elemental Plane. Elementals have very little understanding of man, and for this reason a wizard can never be sure of the nature of the aid the Elementals may send.</p>
        <p>If you choose this power, write <quote>Elementalism</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="alchemy">
       <meta><title>Alchemy</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>A wizard who possesses the power of Alchemy is able, through the mixing of various substances, to create magical potions. Given the correct ingredients, a potion may restore lost energy (i.e., <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points, <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a>), or temporarily improve various abilities (e.g., <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>). The use of alchemy may also allow a wizard to alter the nature of substances (e.g., change lead into gold), but the necessary ingredients and the correct equipment (e.g., a pestle and mortar) must be at hand. The use of the power of Alchemy drains no <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a>.</p>
        <p>If you choose this power write <quote>Alchemy</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="prophecy">
       <meta><title>Prophecy</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>The power of prophecy allows a wizard to foretell the future through meditation. A meditative state will allow a wizard to make the correct decision when facing conflicting choices or difficult actions; to discover the whereabouts of a person he has once met, or an object he has once seen. It may also allow him to determine the true nature of a stranger or a strange object. Magical beings or objects are sometimes hidden from the power of prophecy.</p>
        <p>If you choose this power, write <quote>Prophecy</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="psycmncy">
       <meta><title>Psychomancy</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>This power bestows upon a wizard the ability to deduce facts about events by touching objects connected to them. Through deep concentration, a wizard may lay his hands upon any inanimate object and visualize scenes that have affected it. Visions brought about through the use of Psychomancy are often cryptic, taking the form of a riddle or puzzle. Some magic items are resistant to the use of Psychomancy and may, sometimes, impart misleading information.</p>
        <p>If you choose this power, write <quote>Psychomancy</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="evcation">
       <meta><title>Evocation</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>Mastery of this power permits contact with the spirit realm. A wizard wishing to speak with the dead, or to call up a form from the spirit world, must draw a magic pentacle and enter a trance, when the use of the correct spell-chant will reach out to the Spiritual Plane. Standing within the protection of a magic pentacle, a wizard may consider himself to be relatively safe from harm. If he wishes to speak with a corpse, especially one whose former life was good and righteous, then a wizard can expect help and advice. However, contact with those whose former lives were evil or selfish can be a perilous, and often fatal, experience. Evil spirits are reluctant to return to the realm of the dead and may try to trick a wizard into freeing them into the world of the living. All spirits, good and evil, will require some service of the wizard in return for their aid. Any failure to perform this task, however difficult may result in the wizard losing his life.</p>
        <p>If you choose this power, write <quote>Evocation</quote> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="staff">
       <meta><title>Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>Your Staff is your most valuable possession. It looks and feels like an ordinary quarterstaff, yet it is stronger than any known metal. This is your main combat weapon, for you are untrained in the use of any other form of armed combat. It contains a potent force that is unleashed at will by the power of your mind, and causes a beam of destructive power to hurtle from its tip. Every time you unleash this power you must deduct 1 <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> point.</p>
        <p>In the event that your enemy survives such an attack or should you fall victim to a surprise attack, you will be forced to engage in close combat and must attempt to strike your enemy with the Staff. If your attack is successful, a bolt of energy will be released from the Staff that is capable of inflicting great physical harm. If you wish to increase the amount of damage that you inflict in this way, you must use more <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points and multiply the number of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost by the enemy, accordingly. For example, if you chose to expend 3 <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points on your attack, all enemy <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point losses would be multiplied by three.</p>
        <p>If you enter combat without your Staff, deduct 6 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> If you have no weapon at all, you must deduct 8 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="weqpmnt">
     <meta>
      <title>Equipment</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="powers" />
      <link class="next" idref="wrldcmbt" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>You wear the grey robe and hooded cloak of a Shianti Wizard. Your only weapon is your <a idref="topics-wizardsstaff">Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</a> (note this on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> under <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>). You wear a <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a> containing 4 Meals (note under Meals on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>), and you have been given a map of the Shadakine Empire (note under <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>) which you place inside your robe.</p>
      <p>If you have chosen Alchemy as one of your Magical Powers, then you will have a leather pouch for herbs and potions hanging from your belt. The <a idref="topics-herbpouch">Herb Pouch</a> contains the following:</p>

      <ul>
       <li>2 empty Vials for carrying potions</li>
       <li>1 Vial containing Saltpetre</li>
       <li>1 Vial containing Sulphur</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Mark these 4 items in your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
      <p>Your <a idref="topics-herbpouch">Herb Pouch</a> will carry a maximum of eight items.</p>

      <p>On your last day on the Isle of Lorn, your Shianti Masters offer you the following gifts to aid you in your quest. According to Shianti custom, you may choose one of them. They are:</p>

      <ul>
       <li>Jewelled Dagger (<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>) This adds 1 point to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> when used in combat.</li>
       <li>Magic Talisman (<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>) This adds 2 points to your <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> total.</li>
       <li>Vial of Laumspur (<a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Item</a>) This restores 4 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to your total when swallowed after combat. There is enough for one dose.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>When you have made your choice, mark the item on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> under the headings given in brackets, and make a note of any effect it may have on your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>, <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> or <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> totals.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="whowcary">
       <meta><title>How to Carry Equipment</title></meta>

       <data>
        <p>Now that you have your equipment, the following list shows you how it is carried. You do not need to make notes, but you should refer back to this list in the course of your adventure.</p>

        <ul>
         <li><a idref="topics-wizardsstaff">Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</a><ch.emdash/>Carried in the hand.</li>
         <li><a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a><ch.emdash/>slung over the shoulder.</li>
         <li>Meals<ch.emdash/>carried in the <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>.</li>
         <li>Jewelled Dagger<ch.emdash/>tucked into your belt.</li>
         <li>Magic Talisman<ch.emdash/>worn on a chain around your neck</li>
         <li>Vial of Laumspur<ch.emdash/>carried in the <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>.</li>
        </ul>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="whowmuch">
       <meta><title>How Much Can You Carry?</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl>
         <dt><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a></dt>
          <dd>The maximum number of weapons that you may carry is <em>two</em>. Your <a idref="topics-wizardsstaff">Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</a> counts as one weapon.</dd>

         <dt><a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a></dt>
          <dd>These must be stored in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. Because space is limited, you may only keep a maximum of eight articles, including Meals, in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a> at any one time.</dd>

         <dt><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a></dt>
          <dd><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> are not carried in the <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>, When you discover a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, you will be told how to carry it.</dd>

         <dt><a idref="topics-nobles">Nobles</a> (Shadakine <a idref="topics-currency">currency</a>)</dt>
	   <!-- WOLM: Is this correct? Compare to 02TFC -->
          <dd>These are carried in your Belt Pouch.</dd>

         <dt>Food</dt>
          <dd>Food is carried in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>. Each Meal counts as one item.</dd>
        </dl>

        <p>Any item that may be of use and can be picked up on your adventure and entered on your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> is given capital letters in the text. Unless you are told it is a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, carry it in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>.</p>
       </data>
      </section>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="whowuse">
       <meta><title>How to Use Your Equipment</title></meta>

       <data>
        <dl>
         <dt><a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a></dt>
          <dd>Your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> depends on your <a idref="topics-wizardsstaff">Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</a>. If you do not possess your Staff when you enter combat you must deduct 6 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. If you enter a combat without a weapon, deduct 8 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and fight with your bare hands. If you find a weapon during the adventure, you may pick it up and use it. (Remember that you can only carry <em>two</em> weapons at once.)</dd>

         <dt><a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a></dt>
          <dd>During your travels you will discover various useful items which you may wish to keep. (Remember that you can only carry a maximum of eight items in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a> at any one time.) You may exchange or discard them at any point when you are not involved in combat.</dd>

         <dt><a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a></dt>
          <dd>Each <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> has a particular purpose or effect. You may be told this when the item is discovered, or it may be revealed to you as the adventure progresses.</dd>

         <dt><a idref="topics-currency">Currency</a></dt>
	   <!-- WOLM: Is this correct? Compare to 02TFC -->
          <dd>The <a idref="topics-currency">currency</a> of the Shadakine Empire is the <a idref="topics-nobles">Noble</a>, which is a small jade stone. The system of money is alien to the Shianti, and for this reason you begin your adventure with no money. Whenever you kill an enemy, you may take any <a idref="topics-nobles">Nobles</a> belonging to him and keep them in your Belt Pouch.</dd>

         <dt>Food</dt>
          <dd>You will need to eat regularly during your adventure. If you do not have any food when you are instructed to eat a Meal, you will lose 3 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points.</dd>
        </dl>
       </data>
      </section>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="mainmatter-separate" id="wrldcmbt">
     <meta>
      <title>Rules for Combat</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="weqpmnt" />
      <link class="next" idref="fwrulz" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <p>There will be occasions during your adventure when you have to fight an enemy. The enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points are given in the text. Grey Star<ch.apos/>s aim during the combat is to kill the enemy by reducing his <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to zero while at the same time losing as few <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points as possible himself.</p>
      <p>At the start of a combat, enter Grey Star<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points and the enemy<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points in the appropriate boxes on the Combat Record section of your <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p>
      <p>The sequence for combat is as follows:</p>
      <ol class="paragraphed">
       <li>
	<p>Calculate your current <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> total, based on the weapon you are using. (Remember, if you enter combat without your Staff, you must deduct 6 points from your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. If you have no weapon at all, you must deduct 8 points.)</p></li>
       <li>
        <p>Subtract the <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of your enemy from this total. The result is your Combat Ratio. Enter it on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>.</p></li>
       <li>
        <p><a id="wrld-stage3">If you are using your</a> <a idref="topics-wizardsstaff">Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</a>, decide how many <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points you wish to use. (Remember, you must expend at least 1 point.) Enter this number on your Combat Record in the box marked <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a>.</p>
        <p>Example</p>
	<p>Grey Star (<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> 15, <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> 23) is ambushed by a Deathgaunt (<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> 20). He is not given the opportunity to evade combat, but he can use his <a idref="topics-wizardsstaff">Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</a> against the creature as it swoops down on him. He subtracts the Deathgaunt<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> from his own, giving a Combat Ratio of <ch.minus/>5. (15 <ch.minus/> 20 = <ch.minus/>5). <ch.minus/>5 is noted on the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> as the Combat Ratio. Grey Star decides to use 2 <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points, which is noted on the <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> box of the Combat Record.</p></li>

       <li><p>When you have decided upon the number of <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points you wish to use, and have determined your Combat Ratio, pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>.</p></li>
       <li>
        <p>Turn to the <a idref="topics-combatresultstable">Combat Results Table</a> on the inside back cover of the book. Along the top of the chart are shown the Combat Ratio numbers. Find the number that is the same as your Combat Ratio and cross-reference it with the random number that you have picked. (The random numbers appear on the side of the chart.) You now have the number of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost by Grey Star. To calculate the number lost by the enemy, multiply this by the number of <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points that Grey Star elected to use. Now you have the final number of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost by both Grey Star and his enemy in this round of combat. (E represents points lost by the enemy; GS represents points lost by Grey Star.)</p>
	 <p>Example</p>
	 <p>The Combat Ratio between Grey Star and the Deathgaunt has been established as <ch.minus/>5, and Grey Star<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points used as 2. If the number taken from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> is a 6, then the result of the first round of combat is:</p>
        <ul>
         <li>Grey Star loses 4 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points.</li>
         <li>Deathgaunt loses 5 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points, multiplied by 2 <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points, giving a total of 10 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost in all.</li>
        </ul>
       </li>
       <li><p>On the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a>, mark the changes in <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to the participants in the combat, and Grey Star<ch.apos/>s amended <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points total.</p></li>
       <li><p>Unless otherwise instructed, or unless you have an option to evade, the next round of combat now starts.</p></li>
       <li><p>Repeat the sequence from <a idref="wrld-stage3">Stage 3</a>.</p></li>
      </ol>

      <p>This process of combat continues until the <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points of either the enemy or4 Grey Star are reduced to zero, at which point the one with the zero score is declared dead. If Grey Star is dead, the adventure is over. If the enemy is dead, Grey Star proceeds but with his <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> points reduced.</p>
      <p>A summary of Combat Rules appears in the back of this book.</p>

      <section class="mainmatter" id="wevasion">
       <meta>
        <title>Evasion of Combat</title>
       </meta>

       <data>
        <p>During your adventure you may be given the chance to evade combat If you have already engaged in a round of combat and decide to evade, calculate the combat for that round in the usual manner. All points lost by the enemy as a result of that round are ignored, and you make your escape. Only Grey Star may lose <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points during that round, but then that is the risk of running away! You may only evade if the text of the particular section allows you to do so.</p>
	</data>
      </section>
     </data>
    </section>
   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="mainmatter" id="fwrulz">
   <meta>
    <title>The [Freeway Warrior] Game Rules</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="wrldrulz" />
    <link class="next" idref="topics" />
   </meta>
   <data>

    <p>This portion of the booklet is yet to be completed.</p>

   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="glossary" id="topics">
   <meta>
    <title>Topical Guide</title>
    <link class="prev" idref="fwrulz" />
    <link class="next" idref="topicsa" />
   </meta>
   <data>

    <p>The Topical Guide attempts to provide answers, or at least insight, into some of the inconsistencies and blind spots in the rules. It is organized alphabetically by topic. If you are looking for guidance on a particular subject, this is intended to be a quick reference.</p>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsa">
     <meta>
      <title>A</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topics" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsb" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a></dt>
        <dd><p>The <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> is a set of tables which contain all information about your character such as items carried, skills possessed, etc. The <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> can take many forms. You may use a specialized program like StatsKeeper to help you keep track of character statistics. You may use a spreadsheet document. You may print out the <a idref="topics-actionchart">Action Chart</a> that appears in the Internet Editions of the books and fill in the blanks. As you become familiar with the rules, you may want to create your own by hand on paper. The method you choose doesn<ch.apos/>t matter as long as you<ch.apos/>re comfortable with it.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-adgana">Adgana</a></dt>
        <dd>
         <p>(<a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Item</a>) The leaves of the Adgana plant are a potent narcotic popular among the warriors of Magnamund. When dried, crushed, and eaten, they provide a potent enhancement to <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> for the duration of a fight, but at a high potential cost.</p>
         <p>Use of Adgana will grant a bonus of +6 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> for the duration of a fight when first used (i.e. all combats listed in a single numbered section). Immediately upon completing the combat, you must pick a number from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>. If that number is either a 0 or a 1, you have become addicted to Adgana, and must reduce your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score permanently by 4 points.</p>
         <p>Regardless of whether addiction is suffered on the first use or not, future doses of Adgana will provide a bonus of only +3 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>. Addiction must still be checked for at the end of a combat, but now occurs on a pick of 0, 1, 2, or 3 from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>.</p>
        </dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-alether">Alether</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Item</a>) This plant is common throughout much of Magnamund. Its orange berries are renowned for their ability to improve combat prowess either when eaten whole or when the juice of the crushed berries is drunk. Alether potions or berries typically provide a bonus of +2 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> for the duration of a single fight, but the amount of the bonus is always specified when you find the item. It is uncertain whether or not Alether<ch.apos/>s effects should last for a single enemy or for all enemies in one numbered section.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-armour">Armour</a></dt>
        <dd><p>There is an interesting blind spot in the rules regarding armour which increases your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> (e.g. <a idref="topics-chainmailwaistcoat">Chainmail Waistcoats</a> and <a idref="topics-paddedleatherwaistcoat">Padded Leather Waistcoats</a>). For example, if you are wearing a piece of armour that gives you a 4 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point bonus and your current <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point score is less than or equal to 4, what happens if you lose or discard the armour? Your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score has fallen to zero or below, so strictly speaking, you should be dead. This doesn<ch.apos/>t mesh well with reality, so use your best judgement.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-axe">Axe</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand)</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-arrow">Arrow</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> carried in a <a idref="topics-quiver">Quiver</a>) This item is carried in a <a idref="topics-quiver">Quiver</a> and so doesn<ch.apos/>t take up any more space as a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> or <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> than the <a idref="topics-quiver">Quiver</a> required to carry it. You must possess an Arrow in order to use a <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsb">
     <meta>
      <title>B</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsa" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsc" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-backpack">Backpack</a></dt>
        <dd><p>Your Backpack is used to carry various items. The maximum number of items that can be carried in your Backpack in the Kai and Magnakai series is eight. If you lose your Backpack, you cannot keep any Backpack Items until you find a Backpack in which to keep them. If you have lost your Backpack in an adventure and haven<ch.apos/>t yet found one before beginning the next adventure, you will be given a new one when you choose your equipment.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-beltpouch">Belt Pouch</a></dt>
        <dd><p>Your Belt Pouch stores 50 <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a> or an equivalent amount of another <a idref="topics-currency">currency</a>.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-bow">Bow</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand) You must have at least one <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrow</a> (usually carried in a <a idref="topics-quiver">Quiver</a>) to use a Bow<ch.emdash/>more if the text requires it. You cannot use a Bow in combat, but will be told in the text when you have an opportunity to use it. If you enter combat armed only with a Bow, it is the same as if you were unarmed.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-broadsword">Broadsword</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand) This <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> requires the use of <a idref="topics-twohandedweapons">two hands</a> in combat.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsc">
     <meta>
      <title>C</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsb" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsd" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-chainmailwaistcoat">Chainmail Waistcoat</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> worn on the body) The Chainmail Waistcoat <a idref="topics-armour">armour</a> adds 4 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to your total. It may be used in conjunction with a <a idref="topics-paddedleatherwaistcoat">Padded Leather Waistcoat</a> for a cumulative 6 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point bonus. [cite LWCN]</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a></dt>
        <dd><p>The Combat Ratio is not a true ratio in the mathematical sense. It is the difference between your character<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT RATIO</typ></a> and that of his opponent<ch.apos/>s. For example, if your character<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> is 21 and his opponent<ch.apos/>s is 22, the Combat Ratio is <ch.minus/>1 (21<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>20<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/>1). <a idref="topics-negativenumbers">Negative</a> Combat Ratios are valid.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-combatresultstable">Combat Results Table</a></dt>
        <dd>
         <p>The Combat Results Table is used to determine your character<ch.apos/>s <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points</a> loss and that of his opponent during a single round of combat. You cross-reference the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> with the number chosen from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>. (see <a idref="appb">Appendix B: Example Combat Results Table</a>) For example, if the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> is <a idref="topics-negativenumbers"><ch.minus/>4</a> and the random number is 7, you would find the column that has <a idref="topics-negativenumbers"><ch.minus/>4</a> at the top (note that most columns have two or more <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratios</a>) and the row that 7 on the side. Where that row and that column intersect, the opponents<ch.apos/> <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> point</a> loss is found. (see the example)</p>
         <illustration class="inline">
          <meta>
           <creator>Jonathan Blake</creator>
          </meta>
          <instance src="crtnegex.gif" width="250" height="306" class="html" mime-type="image/gif" />
         </illustration>
        </dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-combatskill">Combat Skill</a></dt>
        <dd><p>This is a measurement of your overall fighting prowess which can be effected by many things such as equipment carried, how surprised you are by an attack, your skills, etc. When in combat, your <typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ> is compared to your enemy<ch.apos/>s<ch.emdash/>the higher your <typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ> score the better.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-cs">CS</a></dt>
        <dd><p>Abbreviation for <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a></p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-currency">Currency</a></dt>
        <dd><p>There are various forms of currency in use throughout Magnamund. The most commonly used in Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s adventures is the <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crown</a>. Other currencies include the <a idref="topics-lune">Lune</a> and the <a idref="topics-kika">Kika</a>. All forms of currency are stored in the <a idref="topics-beltpouch">Belt Pouch</a>.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsd">
     <meta>
      <title>D</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsc" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicse" />
     </meta>

     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-dagger">Dagger</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand)</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-daggerofvashna">Dagger of Vashna</a></dt>
        <dd><p>This cursed blade is a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> carried tucked into your belt. Although a potent <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> which may be useful on Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s adventures, it doesn<ch.apos/>t carry a bonus to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> or <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> outside of the Darklands.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicse">
     <meta>
      <title>E</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsd" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsf" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-endurance">Endurance</a></dt>
        <dd><p>This is a measurement of your overall health and stamina. If your <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> score ever falls to zero <a idref="topics-negativenumbers">or below</a>, your character is dead.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-ep">EP</a></dt>
        <dd><p>Abbreviation for <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points</a></p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsf">
     <meta>
      <title>F</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicse" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsg" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-fireseed">Fireseeds</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> carried in your pocket) Small, explosive items that burn fiercely when thrown against a hard surface. The total of all the Fireseeds you are carrying always takes up the space of exactly one <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, no matter how many you carry. (see <a idref="lwcn1987summer">Lone Wolf Club Newsletter: Summer Special 1987</a>)</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsg">
     <meta>
      <title>G</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsf" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsh" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a></dt>
        <dd><p>Gold Crowns are a common form of <a idref="topics-currency">Currency</a> used in Magnamund which you carry in your <a idref="topics-beltpouch">Belt Pouch</a>.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsh">
     <meta>
      <title>H</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsg" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsi" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-healing">Healing</a></dt>
        <dd>
         <p>Healing provides the ability to cure minor diseases, heal injuries and wounds, and provide a steady restoration of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> when not involved in combat. There is some uncertainty as to what kind of <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> losses can be restored by this Discipline and its enhancements. The Kai series described Healing as effective against <quote><a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost in combat.</quote> This implies that losses due to missed Meals and other non-combat losses are not curable using Healing. The description of Curing in the Magnakai series does not contain this restriction. The descriptions of Curing in the Grand Master and New Order series do contain this restriction however. Curing is described in these series as being effective against <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points lost as a result of combat.</p>
         <p>Strict adherence to the rules would dictate that only <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> lost in combat can be restored using Healing and its improved derivatives: Curing and Deliverance. Common sense says that wounds similar to those sustained in combat can also be healed, but <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> lost due to hunger, fatigue, etc. cannot.</p>
        </dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-herbpouch">Herb Pouch</a></dt>
        <dd><p>Carried by those skilled in the Wizard<ch.apos/>s power of Alchemy, it is used to carry the raw materials necessary to use this power. Contrary to what is stated in <cite>Grey Star the Wizard</cite>, the Herb Pouch can carry eight items. (see <a idref="lwcn1986summer">Lone Wolf Club Newsletter: Summer Special 1986</a>)</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsi">
     <meta>
      <title>I</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsh" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsj" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsj">
     <meta>
      <title>J</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsi" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsk" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsk">
     <meta>
      <title>K</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsj" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsl" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-kika">Kika</a></dt>
        <dd><p>The Kika is the form of <a idref="topics-currency">currency</a> used by the Darklords<ch.apos/> minions. This small iron coin is worth one-tenth of a <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crown</a> and ten of them take up as much space in your <a idref="topics-beltpouch">Belt Pouch</a> as a single <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crown</a>.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsl">
     <meta>
      <title>L</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsk" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsm" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-lantern">Lantern</a></dt>
        <dd><p>This item can be used as a source of light similar to a <a idref="topics-torch">Torch</a> and <a idref="topics-tinderbox">Tinderbox</a> except this is the only item that you need.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-laumspur">Laumspur</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Item</a>) This prolific herb is well-known for the curative properties possessed by its red flowers. While they can occasionally be eaten whole, they are more typically crushed and extracted to form a red-coloured potion. Laumspur potions typically restore 4 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points per dose, but the amount is always specified when you find the item. Laumspur also has curative powers over some diseases.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-lorecircles">Lore-circles</a></dt>
        <dd><p>The Lore-circles of the Magnakai represent groups of Disciplines that, when possessed together, have a synergistic effect. Every time you complete a Lore-circle by acquiring the appropriate Disciplines, you add the appropriate <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> and <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point bonuses immediately and permanently to your basic scores. Lore-circles that you have completed may give you other advantages throughout your adventure, as indicated in the text. These advantages are always related to the Disciplines that make up the Lore-circle. For example, if you have the Lore-circle of Solaris, you may have an advantage in a situation that requires excellent awareness. Note that the Discipline of Huntmastery counts towards two different Lore-circles.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-lune">Lune</a></dt>
        <dd><p>A <a idref="topics-currency">currency</a> used in Magnamund. The silver coin is equivalent in weight and value to one quarter of a <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crown</a>. Four Lune therefore take up the same space as one <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crown</a> in your <a idref="topics-beltpouch">Belt Pouch</a>.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsm">
     <meta>
      <title>M</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsl" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsn" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-mace">Mace</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand)</p></dd>
       <dt>Money</dt>
        <dd><p>(See <a idref="topics-currency">Currency</a>)</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsn">
     <meta>
      <title>N</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsm" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicso" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-negativenumbers">Negative Numbers</a></dt>
        <dd>
         <p>Negative numbers are used throughout the books. They are the numbers below zero. For example, if we have 1 and subtract 1 from it, we have 0. If we subtract 1 again, we have the next number below zero: <ch.minus/>1 (we call this negative 1). The minus sign before the one tells us that it is a negative number. If we subtract 1 yet again, we have <ch.minus/>2, and so on.</p>
         <p>If we count from <ch.minus/>5 to 5, it looks like this: <ch.minus/>5, <ch.minus/>4, <ch.minus/>3, <ch.minus/>2, <ch.minus/>1, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. If we subtract 5 from 3, we get <ch.minus/>2. To see that this is true, start at 3 and count back 5 numbers.</p>
         <p>To add a negative number to a normal (positive) number, we can think of it like subtraction. For example, if we add 3 and <ch.minus/>2 we get 1. 3<ch.thinspace/>+<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/>2 is the same as 3<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>2, which is 1.</p>
         <p>As a practical example of how negative numbers are used, during combat the opponent<ch.apos/>s score is subtracted from Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s to find the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a>. If, for example,  Lone Wolf has a <typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ> of 16 and his opponent has one of 18, the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> is <ch.minus/>2 (16<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>18<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/>2).</p>
        </dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-nobles">Nobles</a></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicso">
     <meta>
      <title>O</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsn" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsp" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsp">
     <meta>
      <title>P</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicso" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsq" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-paddedleatherwaistcoat">Padded Leather Waistcoat</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> worn on the body) The Padded Leather Waistcoat <a idref="topics-armour">armour</a> adds 2 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points as long as it is worn. It may be worn with a <a idref="topics-chainmailwaistcoat">Chainmail Waistcoat</a> which would add the two <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point bonuses together. [cite LWCN]</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-potionoflaumspur">Potion of Laumspur</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(see <a idref="topics-laumspur">Laumspur</a>)</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsq">
     <meta>
      <title>Q</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsp" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsr" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-quarterstaff">Quarterstaff</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand) This <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> requires the use of <a idref="topics-twohandedweapons">two hands</a> in combat.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-quiver">Quiver</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> worn slung over your shoulder) You must possess this <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> in order to carry <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrows</a>. A Quiver will hold a maximum of six <a idref="topics-arrow">Arrows</a>. Although strange, the rules never state that you cannot wear more than one Quiver.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsr">
     <meta>
      <title>R</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsq" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicss" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a></dt>
        <dd><p>The Random Number Table is a ten-by-ten grid of random numbers that was printed in the back of the original series (see <a idref="appa">Appendix A: Example Random Number Table</a>). It was intended to allow you to play the books with minimal equipment. However, blindly stabbing a pencil at a page can be clumsy and not very random. You may also choose to use any method that gives you a random number between 0 and 9 (e.g. ten-sided die or computer random number generator).</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-rope">Rope</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Item</a>) Some Ropes are larger than others and require two spaces in your <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicss">
     <meta>
      <title>S</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsr" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicst" />
     </meta>
     <data>   
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-safekeeping">Safekeeping</a></dt>
        <dd><p>You may store any item you chose in safekeeping at the monastery beginning with Book 5 <cite>Shadow on the Sand</cite>. (see <a idref="lwcn7">Lone Wolf Club Newsletter No. 7</a>) There is no limit to the number of items you may store at the monastery, but be sure to note which items you keep there and what kind of item it is (i.e. <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack</a>, <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>, etc.). Items in safekeeping may be reclaimed at the beginning of a book during the equipment selection process. You cannot access these items during the adventure.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-shield">Shield</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> normally worn slung over the shoulder but carried in the hand during combat) The Shield gives you a 2 point <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> bonus. Optionally, may not be used with <a idref="topics-twohandedweapons">two-handed weapons</a>.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-shortsword">Short Sword</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand)</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-silverbowofduadon">Silver Bow of Duadon</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>) This is a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> not a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> (see ???). It adds +3 to every number you pick from the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a> when using this <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a> to make a shot.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-sommerswerd">Sommerswerd</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>) This legendary <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> forged by a god-like race and given to the Sommlending is a powerful bane against evil. It grants a +8 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> bonus when used in combat. Any Discipline bonus due to Weaponskill, Weaponmastery, or Grand Weaponmastery with <a idref="topics-sword">Swords</a>, <a idref="topics-shortsword">Short Swords</a>, or <a idref="topics-broadsword">Broadswords</a> is applicable when using the Sommerswerd. The Sommerswerd also absorbs hostile magic used against its bearer, and doubles all damage done to an undead opponent. It enhances the Disciplines of Sixth Sense, Divination, and Telegnosis (see Sections <bookref series="lw" book="02fotw" section="sect97">97</bookref> and <bookref series="lw" book="02fotw" section="sect242">242</bookref> of <cite><bookref series="lw" book="02fotw">Fire on the Water</bookref></cite>).</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-spear">Spear</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand) This <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> requires the use of <a idref="topics-twohandedweapons">two hands</a> in combat.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a></dt>
        <dd><p>Special Items are any items which are not <a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Items</a>, <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> or <a idref="topics-currency">currency</a> (e.g. <a idref="topics-goldcrown">Gold Crowns</a>). In Books 1<ch.endash/>7 of the Lone Wolf series, there is no stated maximum on how many Special Items you may carry. From Book 8 onwards, the maximum number you may carry is twelve. You may, if you wish, follow this rule prior to Book 8.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-sword">Sword</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand)</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicst">
     <meta>
      <title>T</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicss" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsu" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-tarama">Tarama</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>) The seeds of this plant are highly sought after by those trained in the magical arts. Swallowing a single seed prior to the working of a spell will allow it to be cast without loss of <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a>. These benefits do not apply to the use of <a idref="topics-willpower"><typ class="attribute">WILLPOWER</typ></a> to charge a Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff in combat although they do help when making long distance attacks.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-tinderbox">Tinderbox</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Item</a>) You must possess this item to light a <a idref="topics-torch">Torch</a>.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-torch">Torch</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-backpack">Backpack Item</a>) You must possess a <a idref="topics-tinderbox">Tinderbox</a> in order to light a Torch.</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-twohandedweapons">Two-handed Weapons</a></dt>
        <dd><p>An off-handed reference in <cite><bookref series="lw" book="10tdot">The Dungeons of Torgar</bookref></cite>: <bookref series="lw" book="10tdot" section="sect304">Section 304</bookref> lists <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> which can be used in combat with one hand. This topic is dealt with more directly in the Grand Master series (e.g. <cite><bookref series="lw" book="13tplor">The Plague Lords of Ruel</bookref></cite>: <bookref series="lw" book="13tplor" section="sect295">Section 295</bookref>). Those not on the list <a idref="topics-broadsword">Broadsword</a>, <a idref="topics-quarterstaff">Quarterstaff</a> and <a idref="topics-spear">Spear</a> require the use of two hands during combat. Optionally, you may decide that this means that you cannot also use a <a idref="topics-shield">Shield</a> at the same time as these two-handed <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a>.</p></dd>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsu">
     <meta>
      <title>U</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicst" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsv" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsv">
     <meta>
      <title>V</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsu" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsw" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsw">
     <meta>
      <title>W</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsv" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsx" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt><a id="topics-warhammer">Warhammer</a></dt>
        <dd><p>(<a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> carried in the hand)</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-weapons">Weapons</a></dt>
        <dd><p>You carry Weapons in your hands, therefore you may only carry two. The Weapons in which the Kai Lords specialize are the <a idref="topics-dagger">Dagger</a>, <a idref="topics-spear">Spear</a>, <a idref="topics-mace">Mace</a>, <a idref="topics-shortsword">Short Sword</a>, <a idref="topics-warhammer">Warhammer</a>, <a idref="topics-sword">Sword</a>, <a idref="topics-axe">Axe</a>, <a idref="topics-quarterstaff">Quarterstaff</a>, <a idref="topics-broadsword">Broadsword</a> and <a idref="topics-bow">Bow</a>. (see <a idref="topics-weaponlikespecialitems">Weapon-like Special Items</a>)</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-weaponlikespecialitems">Weapon-like Special Items</a></dt>
        <dd><p>This is a class of <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Items</a> that may be used as a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a>. They aren<ch.apos/>t counted toward your maximum of two <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapons</a> carried but rather count as a <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a>. A weapon-like <a idref="topics-specialitems">Special Item</a> is used as a <a idref="topics-weapons">Weapon</a> of its same type (e.g. the <a idref="topics-daggerofvashna">Dagger of Vashna</a> is used like a <a idref="topics-dagger">Dagger</a>).</p></dd>
       <dt><a id="topics-willpower">Willpower</a></dt>
       <dt><a id="topics-wizardsstaff">Wizard<ch.apos/>s Staff</a></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsx">
     <meta>
      <title>X</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsw" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsy" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsy">
     <meta>
      <title>Y</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsx" />
      <link class="next" idref="topicsz" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>
    <section class="glossary-separate" id="topicsz">
     <meta>
      <title>Z</title>
      <link class="prev" idref="topicsy" />
     </meta>
     <data>
      <dl class="paragraphed">
       <dt></dt>
      </dl>
     </data>
    </section>

   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="backmatter" id="appa">
   <meta><title>Appendix A: Example Random Number Table</title></meta>

   <data>
    <illustration class="inline">
     <meta>
      <creator>Jonathan Blake</creator>
     </meta>
     <instance src="random.gif" width="332" height="432" class="html" />
     <instance src="random.tex" width="380" height="500" class="tex" />
    </illustration>
   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="backmatter" id="appb">
   <meta><title>Appendix B: Example Combat Results Table</title></meta>

   <data>
    <illustration class="inline">
     <meta>
      <creator>Jonathan Blake</creator>
     </meta>
     <instance src="crtneg.gif" width="386" height="472" class="html" />
     <instance src="crtneg.tex" width="380" height="500" class="tex" />
    </illustration>

    <illustration class="inline">
     <meta>
      <creator>Jonathan Blake</creator>
     </meta>
     <instance src="crtpos.gif" width="386" height="472" class="html" />
     <instance src="crtpos.tex" width="380" height="500" class="tex" />
    </illustration>
   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="backmatter" id="appc">
   <meta><title>Appendix C: Example Combat</title></meta>

   <data>
    <p>The following is an example of a simple combat to show how it works in general and to supplement the example given in the Rules for Combat section of the books. This example is taken from <cite><bookref series="lw" book="01fftd">Flight from the Dark</bookref></cite>: <bookref series="lw" book="01fftd" section="sect229">Section 229</bookref>.</p>
    <p>Lone Wolf has a base <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> score of 15. He has an <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score of 23. He has the Discipline of Mindblast which adds 2 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points to his base score (as long as his enemy isn<ch.apos/>t immune to Mindblast). He has mastered the Discipline of Weaponskill with the <a idref="topics-quarterstaff">Quarterstaff</a>. He is carrying an <a idref="topics-axe">Axe</a> and a <a idref="topics-mace">Mace</a>.</p>
    <p>He is in combat with a Kraan who isn<ch.apos/>t immune to Mindblast, so he adds 2 <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points to his score (15<ch.thinspace/>+<ch.thinspace/>2<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>17). He isn<ch.apos/>t carrying a <a idref="topics-quarterstaff">Quarterstaff</a> (the <a idref="topics-weapons">weapon</a> in which he has Weaponskill so he doesn<ch.apos/>t benefit his Weaponskill mastery. He must reduce his <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> by 1 due to dust mentioned in the book (17<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>1<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>16).</p>
    <p>Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s opponent<ch.emdash/>a Kraan<ch.emdash/>has a <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> of 16 so the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> is 0 (16<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>16<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>0). The Kraan has an <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> of 25.</p>
    <p>Combat begins by picking a random number which is traditionally done using the <a idref="topics-randomnumbertable">Random Number Table</a>, but there a other ways available. The first random number picked is 6. Looking that up on the <a idref="topics-combatresultstable">Combat Results Table</a> by finding the <a idref="topics-combatratio">Combat Ratio</a> (0) at the top and cross-referencing it with the random number (6) along the side. In this case, we find that Lone Wolf has lost 2 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points and the Kraan has lost 8. Now Lone Wolf has 21 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points (23<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>2<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>21) and the Kraan has 17 (25<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>8<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>17). Lone Wolf and his opponent continue with these new, reduced <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point scores.</p>
    <p>Combat continues by picking another random number: 5. During this round, Lone Wolf loses another 2 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points while the Kraan loses 7. Lone Wolf now has an <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score of 19 (21<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>2<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>19) and the Kraan has 10 (17<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>7<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>10). The situation looks good for Lone Wolf.</p>
    <p>The random number picked for the next round is 1<ch.emdash/>not a great round for Lone Wolf. He loses 4 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points while the Kraan loses only 3. Lone Wolf is left with 15 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points (19<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>4<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>15) and the Kraan has 7 (10<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>3<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>7).</p>
    <p>Another random number is picked: 7. This time Lone Wolf loses 2 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points leaving him with 13 (15<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>2<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/>13) and the Kraan loses 9 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points leaving him with <ch.minus/>2 (7<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/><ch.thinspace/>9<ch.thinspace/>=<ch.thinspace/><ch.minus/>2). Since the Kraan has an <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> score that is <a idref="topics-negativenumbers">less than or equal to 0</a>, it is dead and Lone Wolf wins the combat and can continue his quest. If Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s score had been reduced to <a idref="topics-negativenumbers">0 or below</a>, his quest would now be over.</p>
   </data>
  </section>

  <section class="backmatter" id="appd">
   <meta><title>Appendix D: Lone Wolf Club Newsletter Excerpts</title></meta>

   <data>
    <dl class="paragraphed">
     <dt><a id="lwcn1986summer">Summer Special 1986</a></dt>
      <dd>
       <p>[Q:] On page 26 of Grey Star Book 2, it says you <quote>carry a maximum of eight items in your Herb Pouch</quote><ch.emdash/>should it be six?</p>
       <p>[A:] Actually, the rule which first appeared in Grey Star Book 1 regarding the herb Pouch was incorrect. It should be able to hold up to eight itmes hence the changed rule in later books.</p>
      </dd>
     <dt>Newsletter No. 6</dt>
      <dd>
       <p>[Q:] In the sewers beneath Tekaro, I lost my weapon to the grasp of a certain killer organism<ch.emdash/>that weapon was the Sommerswerd!<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] Strictly speaking, the Sommerswerd is a Special Item<ch.emdash/>not a weapon. When facing the organism (Ref. 4) you should erase a weapon from your Action Chart. If you do not possess a weapon, only then do you lose the Sommerswerd.</p>
      </dd>
     <dt><a id="lwcn7">Newsletter No. 7</a></dt>
      <dd>
       <p>[Q:] Is the <quote>Dagger of Vashna</quote> Taken from the Bandit Leader Barraka at the Maakengorge, usable as a weapon?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] Yes, if you possess this Special Item you may use it as an ordinary dagger in combat. Kai Masters may find it interesting to note for future use that the Dagger of Vashna could prove to be a valuable piece of equipment to take with them on the quest for the Lorestone of Tahou in Lone Wolf Book 9<ch.emdash/><quote>The Cauldron of Fear</quote><ch.ellips/>you have been warned!</p>
       <p>[Q:] Can you keep Backpack Items in [safekeeping] at the Kai Monastery?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] Yes if you wish to leave any surviving Backpack tems in [safekeeping] at the end of an adventure, you can do so. When beginning the next quest, you are given a selection of new equipment which you may then supplement with any of the items you previously held. Many readers have written to point out that they now have a huge selection of Special Items discovered during the course of their adventures and that carrying all these goodies seems a little unrealistic. In response to theis valid point, a new rule comes into effect in Lone Wolf 8, limiting the number of Special Items you can carry. The new limit is 12 Special Items; all others you may have must be left in safe keeping. A tip to all Kai Masters<ch.emdash/>don<ch.apos/>t take you full quota of 12 items with you when youbegin the adventure; leave enough room for any you may find en route otherwise you will have to sacrifice some in favour of others. The recommended number to start with is eight. Also, purely for the sake of accuracy, the term <quote>safe keeping at the Kai Monastery</quote> in fact means leaving some items with the Elder Magi in Elzian, which features as Lone Wolf<ch.apos/>s base of operations during the Magnakai Quest.</p>
      </dd>
     <dt><a id="lwcn1987newyears">1987 New Year<ch.apos/>s Special</a></dt>
      <dd>
       <p>[Q:]Is there a ranking system for Shianti Wizards, like there is for Kai Lords and Masters?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] No, unlike the ranking system that marks the rise of Kai Lords, the Shianti do not have set levels of advancement.</p>
       <p>[Q:] On reaching the rank of Primate and having mastered Weaponmastery, would this enable you to be skilled in four weapons and increase the points added to your <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> to +4 when entering combat with a wepon you have mastered?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] For every adventure you complete in the Magnakai series, assuming you have the mastery of Weaponmastery, you gain proficiency in the use of one new weapon. The bonus to your [<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>] rating for use of this weapon is combat always remains at +3.</p>
       <p>[Q:] Are you allowed to drop a weapon, or must you wait until the end of the book?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] You can drop ([i.e.] discard) a weapon at any time during your adventure, you need not wait until the end of the book. If you find a weapon during the adventure (it will be marked in the text with a capital letter, like a Backpack Item) you may pick it up and use it. You can only carry two weapons at any time.</p>
      </dd>
     <dt><a id="lwcn8">Newsletter No. 8</a></dt>
      <dd>
       <p>[Q:] If Lone Wolf has Weaponskill <ch.ampersand/> Weaponmastery with the same weapon, does this give him +3 or +5 extra <a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a> points in battle? Also, if he has Healing as well as Curing, does this give him +2 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points back for every section through which he passes without combat?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] The correct weapon bonus is +3, on higher than the basic Kai Discipline bonus for having Weaponskill. Kai Mastery of Curing gives the same +1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point back (for every section though which you pass without combat) as does the basic Kai Discipline of Healing. The mastery advantage comes with the ability to cure disease, blindness and combat wounds, as well as being able to identify the properties of herbs, roots, and potions. Additional advantages are gained at higher rank as the Magnakai [Discipline] improves.</p>
      </dd>
     <dt><a id="lwcn1987summer">Summer Special 1987</a></dt>
      <dd>
       <p>[Q:] In Lone Wolf Book 8, ref. no. 169, you <quote>lose a grip of your weapon</quote>. Can you retrieve it or must it be erased from you Action Chart?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] If you win the combat against the Vordak you are able to retrieve the weapon and keep it noted on your Action Chart.</p>
       <p>[Q:] When you complete a Lone Wolf adventure, do you renew your <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points to their original total for the next adventure?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] All lost [<a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>] points are regained at the end of an adventure. If you have completed any new Lore-circles by finishing an adventure successfully, the bonuses you gain to your [<a idref="topics-combatskill"><typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ></a>] and [<a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>] are added to this basic score prior to the next adventure.</p>
       <p>[Q:] In the basic series (Books 1-5) I possessed the Kai Discipline of Healing and was able to restore 1 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> point for every section I passed through in which I was not involved in combat. Now that I am a Kai Master with the Magnakai Discipline of Curing I can no longer benefit from my basic healing skills<ch.ellips/> or can I?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] If you have completed all five of the Basic series books you can add +1 [<a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a>] as per the rules of Healing. This advantage will benefit all those Kai Masters who have completed the basic series books prior to tackling the Magnakai Series.</p>
       <p>[Q:] When I was captured in Book 9, All my weapons were taken from me. Can I retrieve them at the end of the book?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] Yes. The South Gate Guard would definately allow the <quote>Saviour of Tahou</quote> to have his weapons back!</p>
       <p>[Q:] In some books you can choose Fireseeds at the start. It says 3 Fireseeds<ch.emdash/>if you take all three does this mean you have taken 3 [separate] items from the 5 you are allowed to pick?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] The Fireseeds are Special Items which count only as 1 item no matter how many of them you possess. However, when you use them be sure to note how many you have left. Also, for the purpose of determining your maximum number of Special Items (12), all Fireseeds count as 1 item.</p>
      </dd>
     <dt><a id="lwcn10">Newsletter No. 10</a></dt>
      <dd>
       <p>[Q:] If, in a Magnakai adventure, we are instructed to eat a Meal (or lose 3 <a idref="topics-endurance"><typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ></a> points) and we do not have the Magnakai skill of Huntmastery, can we still use the basic skill of Hunting (assuming we<ch.apos/>re not in a desert or wilderness), [e.g.] Book 8; ref. 129?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] Basically, yes you can. All [Kai Masters] who have completed one or more of the Lone Wolf <quote>basic</quote> books (1<ch.endash/>5) can benefit from their experience in this way. This will give them a real advantage over those who have tried only one or more of the Magnakai series books (6<ch.endash/>12).</p>
      </dd>
     <dt><a id="lwcn12">Newsletter No. 12</a></dt>
      <dd>
       <p>[Q:] If you find a new Backpack in one of the adventures, can you use it to hold an additional 8 items as well as those you already have?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] Realistically, you can only wear one [Backpack] at a time, and carry a maximum of eight [Backpack] items ([Special Items] not included). Carrying two [Backpacks], and 16 [Backpack Items], would make close combat very difficult indeed, even for a Kai Master. (<em>Note: This aspect of the Lone Wolf rules influenced the progressive [encumbrance] rule of the Freeway Warrior series</em>)</p>
      </dd>
     <dt><a id="lwcn28">Newsletter No. 28</a></dt>
      <dd>
       <p>[Q:] Can you clarify what happens to the +1EP bonus when you progress from Kai Master to Grand Master?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] The [+1EP] bonus gained when passing through combatless sections does still apply, but only if you have played and survived the Magnakai series books. Joe Dever intended this as a <quote>hidden loyalty bonus</quote> for readers who had played the earlier books, which is why it was ommitted from the Grand Master rules.</p>
       <p>[Q:] If a person keeps the +4CS Weaponmastery ability from one series to the next, does that mean that when he gets Grand Weaponmastery he has +9CS with the weapons he has proficiency in?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] The +4CS Weaponmastery bonus is not added to Grand Weaponmastery<ch.emdash/>it simply rises by 1 to +5.</p>
       <p>[Q:] Is the Dagger of Vashna taken from the bandit leader Barraka at the Maakengorge useable as a Weapon?<ch.ellips/></p>
       <p>[A:] Yes, if you possess this Special Item you may use it as an ordinary [Dagger] in combat. It could also prove especially usefull during the quest for the Lorestone of Tahou (Lone Wolf 9).</p>
      </dd>
    </dl>
   </data>
  </section>

  &inclusion.project.aon.license;

 </data>
</section>

</gamebook>