<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE gamebook SYSTEM "gamebook.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % xhtml.characters SYSTEM "htmlchar.mod">
 <!ENTITY % latex.characters SYSTEM "ltexchar.mod">
 %xhtml.characters;

 <!ENTITY % general.links SYSTEM "genlink.mod">
 %general.links;
 <!ENTITY % xhtml.links   SYSTEM "htmllink.mod">
 %xhtml.links;
]>

<gamebook xml:lang="en-UK" version="0.10">

<meta>
 <title>[Insert Title]</title>
</meta>

<section id="toc">
 <meta />
 <data />
</section>

<section id="title">
 <meta>
  <title>Title Page</title>
  <link class="next" idref="dedicate" />
 </meta>

 <data>

  <!-- Frontmatter -->

<!--

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Table of Contents</title>

<h2>Table of Contents</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="timeline.htm">Magnamund Then and Now</a>
 <ul>
 <li><a href="timeline.htm">The Ages of Magnamund</a></li>
 <li><a href="realmsno.htm">The Realms of Northern Magnamund</a></li>
 <li><a href="realmsso.htm">The Realms of Southern Magnamund</a></li>
 </ul>
<li><a href="nations.htm">The Nations of Magnamund</a>
 <ul>
 <li><a href="nations.htm">The Races of Magnamund</a></li>
 <li><a href="vaderish.htm">The Vaderish/Aluvian Nations</a></li>
 <li><a href="nael.htm">The Nael/Nael-Aluvian Nations</a></li>
 <li><a href="lastland.htm">The Lastlander/Old Kingdom Nations</a></li>
 <li><a href="mythensh.htm">The Mythenish/Tianese Nations</a></li>
 <li><a href="vassa.htm">The Vassa Nations</a></li>
 <li><a href="drakkar.htm">The Drakkarim/Agarashi Nations</a></li>
 <li><a href="primtive.htm">The Primitive/Drodarin Nations</a></li>
 </ul>
</li>
<li><a href="drklords.htm">The Darklords</a>
 <ul>
 <li><a href="drklords.htm">The Creatures of Helgedad</a></li>
 <li><a href="darkhist.htm">The History of the Darklords</a></li>
 <li><a href="darkpwr.htm">The Fighting Power of the Darklords</a></li>
 </ul>
</li>
<li><a href="kai.htm">The Kai Lords</a></li>
<li><a href="ragadorn.htm">Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</a>
 <ul>
 <li><a href="ragadorn.htm">Introduction &amp; Setting-up</a></li>
 <li><a href="ragrulz.htm">Rules (Part I)</a></li>
 <li><a href="ragrulz2.htm">Rules (Part <span class="caps">II</span>)</a></li>
 <li><a href="ragrulz3.htm">Rules (Part <span class="caps">III</span>)</a></li>
 <li><a href="ragsmmry.htm">Rules Summary</a></li>
 <li><a href="ragchrt.htm">Ragadorn Tavern Game Characters</a></li>
 </ul>
</li>
<li><a href="sommrlnd.htm">Sommerlund</a></li>
 <ul>
 <li><a href="sommrlnd.htm">The Royal Estates, Fryelund and Baronial Provinces</a></li>
 <li><a href="sommsaga.htm">The Saga of Sommerlund</a></li>
 <li><a href="faldon.htm">Lorin Faldon - Young Archer</a></li>
 <li><a href="rolny.htm">Aran Rolny - Young Scribe</a></li>
 <li><a href="taynor.htm">Jac Taynor - Farmer's Son</a></li>
 <li><a href="sommwarr.htm">The Warriors of Sommerlund</a></li>
 </ul>
</li>
<li><a href="giaks.htm">Giaks</a>
 <ul>
 <li><a href="giaks.htm">The Giak Army</a></li>
 <li><a href="giaklang.htm">The Giak Language</a></li>
 <li><a href="giakword.htm">Giak Word List</a></li>
 <li><a href="giakspek.htm">Zegor Jok Dak Eg</a></li>
 </ul>
</li>
<li><a href="modling.htm">Modelling Magnamund</a>
 <ul>
 <li><a href="modling.htm">The Kai Monastery</a></li>
 <li><a href="skyrider.htm">The Skyrider</a></li>
 <li><a href="fntsyflt.htm">Fantasy Fleets</a></li>
 </ul>
</li>
<li><a href="dod.htm">Dawn of the Darklords</a>

[numbered sections]

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The History of the Darklords</title>

<h2>The Darklords</h2>

<h3>The History of the Darklords</h3>

<p>Once there were twenty Darklords, each unique and very powerful and each with a 'court' of followers drawn from the ranks of the Nadziranim and Xaghash. The most powerful lord was Vashna. He masterminded the War of Desecration that bent the Drakkarim nations to his cause. In the year <span class="caps">MS</span> 3192, he was proclaimed Archlord of the Darklands. He then ordered the construction of eight gigantic fortress-cities.</p>

<p>In <span class="caps">MS</span> 3262, Vashna began the construction of Helgedad, the mightiest Darklord city. Perched upon an island of granite at the centre of a huge volcanic chasm, it claimed the lives of one million Giak slaves during the many years it took to build its walls, towers and turrets of black steel. A bridge of twisted steel now spans the fiery chasm joining Helgedad to the desolate plain of the Naogizaga where craters of molten rock belch forth a black gas that keeps the city forever in shadow.</p>

<p>Beneath the towers and the streets of iron, are many dungeons that descend through solid rock towards the blazing chasm floor. Here lie the breeding pits of a host of Vashna's evil creations. Vordaks, Doomwolves and Kraan emerged from these terrible halls to swell the Darklord armies, securing victory after victory in the incessant wars of expansion. But victory turned sour when a new breed of warriors appeared from the Northern Void. For the very first time, Vashna tasted defeat at the hands of mortal men called Sommlending; his armies were ejected from the Lastlands and held at bay along the Durncrag Ranqe. The Sommlending, under their leader King Kian, established the land of Sommerlund within this captured territory and defied all attempts to recapture it. Vashna was enraged.</p>

<p>He vowed to destroy Sommerlund and its king, and set about the creation of a new evil to unleash upon his enemies. His efforts spawned the Helghast, undead beings of great power who could adopt the form of humans at will. They were used to great effect during the Helghast Wars (<span class="caps">MS</span> 3520-50), but the strength and resolve of the Sommlending finally overcame them. The magicians of Toran identified them, and using the Sommerswerd, a sword of great magical power wielded by their king, drove them out of the land. This sword then brought about the destruction of Vashna himself, at the Great Battle of Maakengorge, where, upon the edge of the chasm of doom, King Ulnar I slew and in turn was slain by the evil Darklord.</p>

<p>After Vashna's death, chaos errupted in Helgedad as the Darklords struggled between themselves, to win supreme control. In order to increase their personal strength, many Darklords undertook a quest to discover the lost Doomstones of Agarash the Damned, for with these gems of power they could dominate Helgedad and force their peers to proclaim them Arch-lord of the Darklands. The Doomstone quest was eventually completed and one Darklord emerged to claim the throne. His name was Zagarna, and he, like his former master Vashna, pledged himself to the complete destruction of Sommerlund. He exercised his new-found power by launching an attack on the monastery of the Kai. But the invasion was defeated by the superiority of the Sommlending archers. Frustrated but undeterred, Zagarna focused his attentions upon other human nations. He planted agents throughout the royal courts of the Stornlands and used them to maintain a state of conflict. Elsewhere, his Nadziranim were engaged in a quest for magical items and tomes of wisdom that were lost following the decimation of the Elder Magi in the Great Plague of 2514 <span class="caps">MS</span>.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Fighting Power of the Darklords</title>

<h2>The Darklords</h2>

<h3>The Fighting Power of the Darklords</h3>

<p>Darklord Zagarna, who had emerged supreme after the completion of the Doomstone quest, soon turned his attention to creating an arsenal of terrible weapons. With them, he aided the Vassagonian and Shadakine empires and shared in the spoils of their conquests. He forged staves of power and harnessed blue lightning within their twisted black steel shafts. Explosive crystals, great swords of iron and flame, daggers with magical blades, and poisoned spikes that always found their mark were among the many cruel arms fashioned by Zagarna in preparation for the fulfilment of his one overwhelming desire - the invasion and conquest of Sommerlund. In <span class="caps">MS</span> 4950, he ordered the construction of fortresses in the Durncrag Range; they were to serve as marshalling posts for his Giak armies and as bases for agents and spies operating within Sommerlund. Carefully, he built up his armies, taking great pains to hide their numbers and movements from the prying eyes of Sommlending Border Rangers.</p>

<p>It was early in the year <span class="caps">MS</span> 5050 that fate presented the ideal opportunity for Zagarna's invasion, when a Sommlending magician named Vonotar betrayed his country in return for Nadziranim magic and weapons. His treachery brought about the near total destruction of the Kai lords, but it did not secure victory for Darklord Zagarna, who was destined to perish during the siege of Holmgard.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Dawn of the Darklords</title>

<h2>Dawn Of The Darklords</h2>
<h3>A Solo Role-Playing Adventure Game</h3>

<h3>The Story So Far...</h3>

<p>You are Banedon, a young journeyman to the Magicians Guild of Toran in Sommerlund. In the last two weeks disturbing events have rocked the stability of your guild. A brother magician named Vonotar denounced the Guild and murdered one of the Elders. He disappeared after the crime and your Guildmaster fears that he has fled to Helgedad to aid the Darklords.</p>

<p>It is now dawn of the day before the feast of Fehmarn. You have been summoned to the Guildmaster's chamber and entrusted with an envelope that must be taken to the Monastery of the Kai. It contains an urgent message for the Kai Grand Master, and your mission is to deliver it by hand at all costs. The Guildmaster warns you to be on your guard at all times, for he fears that enemy agents are already at work within the land. 'Travel swiftly, my son,' he says, as you turn to leave his chamber, 'and may the luck of the Gods go with you.'</p>

<h3>The Game Rules</h3>

<p>To keep a record of your adventure, use the <a href="action.htm">Action Chart</a> below. Before you start you must determine your fighting prowess (Combat Skill) and physical stamina (Endurance). To do this take a pencil and, with your eyes closed, point with the blunt end of it onto the <a href="random.htm">Random Number Table</a> on the last page of this book. If you pick 0 it counts as zero.</p>

<p>The first number that you pick in this way represents your Combat Skill. Add 10 to this number and write the total in the Combat Skill section of your <a href="action.htm">Action Chart</a>.</p>

<p>The second number that you pick from the <a href="random.htm">Random Number Table</a> represents your powers of Endurance. Add 20 to this number and write the total in the Endurance section of your <a href="action.htm">Action Chart</a>.</p>

<p>If you are wounded in combat, or if you use any of your spells, you will lose Endurance points. If at any time your Endurance points fall to zero, you are dead and the adventure is over.</p>

<h4>Magical Powers</h4>

<p>You have mastered only five of the ten spells that the Magicians Guild call the 'Brotherhood Spells'.</p>

<p>When you have chosen your five spells, enter them in the 'Spells' section of your <a href="action.htm">Action Chart</a>.</p>

<dl>
<dt>Lightning Hand</dt>
<dd>This spell enables you to cast a bolt of lightning, simply by pointing a finger and concentrating upon the spell. Every time this spell is used you must deduct 3 from your Endurance points total.</dd>
<dt>Mind Charm</dt>
<dd>Casting this spell upon a person (or creature) will cause that person to regard you as a trusted friend. It will not allow you to control the person, but anything you do or say will be looked on as friendly.</dd>
<dt>Invisible Shield</dt>
<dd>When this spell is cast, an invisible barrier will form as protection from missiles and enemies. However, it will not protect you from magical attacks, and every time it is used you must deduct 2 Endurance points from your score.</dd>
<dt>Net</dt>
<dd>This spell enables you to cast a web-like net of magical rope at a chosen target. It can be used to ensnare an enemy, or to enable you to climb high walls or obstacles with ease.</dd>
<dt>Vigour</dt>
<dd>Casting this spell will increase your Combat Skill by 3 points for the duration of one combat, at the cost of 3 Endurance points. It cannot be used if your Endurance points total is below 10.</dd>
<dt>Counterspell</dt>
<dd>This spell may be used to protect yourself, or another person or object of your choice, from a magical attack. Use of this spell costs 2 Endurance points.</dd>
<dt>Levitation</dt>
<dd>This spell may be cast upon yourself, or upon another person or object, to cancel the effects of gravity, and thereby make the affected object rise into the air. The spell lasts no more than a few minutes and its usage costs 2 Endurance points.</dd>
<dt>Sense Evil</dt>
<dd>When this spell is cast it will enable you to detect the presence of evil in any creature or object close by. However, perils such as traps or naturally poisonous animals will not be detected through the use of this spell.</dd>
<dt>Mend</dt>
<dd>This spell can be used to repair damaged items or to restore lost Endurance points. In order for the spell to work, you must be standing in fresh running water, such as a river or stream, when the spell is cast. Using this spell upon yourself will restore 5 Endurance points.</dd>
<dt>Silence</dt>
<dd>Casting this spell will muffle the sound of any movement that you make.</dd>
</dl>

<h4>Equipment</h4>

<p>You wear a Crystal Star Pendant (Special Item). Before leaving the Guildhall, you are given an envelope that contains the Guildmaster's message to the Kai (Special Item), and a pouch of gold. To find out how much gold is in the pouch, pick a number from the <a href="random.htm">Random Number Table</a>. Now add 10 to this number. The total equals the number of Gold Crowns inside the pouch, and you may now enter this number in the Gold Crowns section of your <a href="action.htm">Action Chart</a>. The message is carried inside your robe, and you are given a backpack in which to carry any four of the following items:</p>

<ul>
<li>Blanket (Backpack Item)</li>
<li>Healing Potion (Backpack Item) This potion restores 2 points to your total when swallowed after combat. There is enough for one dose.</li>
<li>Rope (Backpack Item)</li>
<li>Torch (Backpack Item)</li>
<li>2 Meals (Backpack Items) Each Meal takes up one space in your Backpack.</li>
<li>Tinderbox (Backpack Item)</li>
<li>Bottle Of Wine (Backpack Item)</li>
</ul>

<p>You also possess a Short Sword (Weapon) which you carry in a scabbard.</p>

<h5>Using Your Equipment</h5>

<dl>
<dt>Weapons</dt>
<dd>If you enter a combat with no weapons, deduct 4 points from your Combat Skill and fight with your bare hands. If you find a weapon during the adventure, you may pick it up and use it. The maximum number of weapons that you may carry is two.</dd>
<dt>Backpack Items</dt>
<dd>You may discover various useful items which you may wish to keep. You may exchange or discard them at any point when you are not involved in combat. Your Backpack can carry a maximum of eight articles (including Meals).</dd>
<dt>Special Items</dt>
<dd>When you discover a Special Item, you will be told how to carry it.</dd>
<dt>Gold Crowns</dt>
<dd>These are carried in your pouch (maximum 50 Crowns).</dd>
<dt>Food</dt>
<dd>Each Meal counts as one backpack item. If you do not have any food when you are instructed to eat, you will lose 3 Endurance points.</dd>
</dl>

<h4>Rules For Combat</h4>

<p>There will be occasions during your adventure when you have to fight an enemy. The enemy's Combat Skill and Endurance points are given in the text. Your aim during the combat is to kill the enemy by reducing his Endurance points to zero while at the same time losing as few Endurance points as possible yourself.</p>

<p>At the start of a combat, enter your Endurance points and the enemy's Endurance points in the appropriate boxes on the Combat Record section of the <a href="action.htm">Action Chart</a>.</p>

<p>The sequence for combat is as follows:</p>

<ol>
<li>Add any extra points gained through the use of Special Items or spells to your current Combat Skill total.</li>
<li>Subtract the Combat Skill of your enemy from this total. The result is your Combat Ratio. Enter it on the <a href="action.htm">Action Chart</a>.</li>
<li>When you have your Combat Ratio, pick a number from the <a href="random.htm">Random Number Table</a>.</li>
<li>Turn to the Combat Results Table on page 96. Along the top of the chart are shown the Combat Ratio numbers. Find the number that is the same as your Combat Ratio and cross-reference it with the random number you have picked (the random numbers appear on the side of the chart). You now have the number of Endurance points lost by both Banedon and his adversary in this round of combat.</li>
<li>On the <a href="action.htm">Action Chart</a>, mark the changes in Endurance points to both participants in the combat.</li>
<li>Unless otherwise instructed, or unless you have an option to evade, the next round of combat now starts.</li>
<li>Repeat the sequence from Stage 3.</li>
</ol>

<p>This process of combat continues until the Endurance points of either the enemy or Banedon are reduced to zero, at which point the one with a zero score is declared dead. If Banedon is dead, the adventure is over. If the enemy is dead, Banedon proceeds but with his Endurance points reduced.</p>

<h5>Evasion of Combat</h5>

<p>You may only evade if the text allows you to.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Drakkarim/Agarashi Nations</title>

<h2>The Nations of Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Drakkarim/Agarashi Nations</h3>

<h4>The Danarg</h4>
<p>Ruler: Unknown 
<br />Capital: No major settlements 
<br />Population: 50,000 + 
<br />Resources: Undeveloped 
<br />Currency: None 
<p>This vast tract of forest swamp lies in the crater of an ancient volcano, and is fed by the many rivers and streams that flow down from the encircling hills and mountains. Ferocious monsters, the legacy of the Agarashi empire, control the swamp and occasionally raid the freelands of Talestria. It is said that the lost temple of the Elder Magi still stands at the heart of the Danarg, but as yet these rumours have not been confirmed.</p>

<h4>Ghatan</h4>
<p>Ruler: Darklord Dakushna of Kagorst 
<br />Capital: Torgar 
<br />Population: 25,000 + 
<br />Resources: Sulphur, slave labour 
<br />Currency: Kika (10 Kika = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>The hills of Ghatan have harboured creatures of evil since the dark days of the Agarashi empire. Nothing grows in the sulphurous soil, except for the twisted trees that border upon the source of the Hellswamp. In <span class="caps">MS</span> 2801, Ghatan was overrun by the Drakkarim who, in the midst of this desolation, constructed the city of Torgar for the grim purpose of imprisoning and torturing their enemies. In <span class="caps">MS</span> 3150, when the Drakkarim allied themselves to the Darklords, Torgar came under Darklord control.</p>

<h4>Ixia - The Land of the Dead</h4>
<p>Ruler: Lord Ixiataaga 
<br />Capital: Xaagon 
<br />Population: Number unknown 
<br />Resources: Rare minerals 
<br />Currency: No system of currency 
<p>The peninsula of Ixia is an icy, desolate wasteland, lit by the lightning flashes of electrical storms that rage constantly above its bleak mountain peaks. Lord Ixiataaga, Masterlord of the Dead, has reigned over this terrible place for more than ten thousand years. The city of Xaagon is the seat of his power, its undead inhabitants, condemned to an eternity in his service. It is some measure of his power that even the Darklords of Helgedad fear to trespass in his realm.</p>

<h4>Hardlands - The Tadatizaga</h4>
<p>Ruler: The Shog'aash of Lake Ghargon 
<br />Capital: Unknown 
<br />Population: 260,000 
<br />Resources: Black iron ore, minerals 
<br />Currency: None 
<p>For centuries the hellish landscape of the Tadatizaga has repelled all but the hardiest of creatures. The sky is dark and the blizzard-swept hills and poisonous vegetation encourage the monstrous inhabitants to remain in their lairs underground. In the midnight depths of the black, cold waters of Lake Ghargon lives the Shog'aash, an evil sea dragon of immense size. It swims supreme having devoured all potential rivals long ago. Occasionally it ventures onto land to terrorize the inhabitants of Gournen, a Darklord city built upon the edge of Lake Ghargon.</p>

<h4>The Dark Realm of Skaror</h4>
<p>Ruler: Darklord Kraagenskul of Helgedad 
<br />Capital: Cragmantel 
<br />Population: 38,000 
<br />Resources: Slave labour, timber, iron ore, copper 
<br />Currency: Kika (10 Kika = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Helotry of Nyraz</h4>
<p>Ruler: High Warlord Magnaarn of Darke 
<br />Capital: Darke 
<br />Population: 55,000 + 
<br />Resources: Shipbuilding, timber, slaves, agriculture 
<br />Currency: Kika (10 Kika = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Helotry of Nyvoz</h4>
<p>Ruler: Darklord Dakushna of Kagorst 
<br />Capital: Kagorst 
<br />Population: 75,000 
<br />Resources: Timber, slave labour 
<br />Currency: Kika (10 Kika = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Darklordship of Zaldir</h4>
<p>Ruler: Darklord Gnaag of Mozgoar 
<br />Capital: Shpydar 
<br />Population: 26,000 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, timber, copper, slave labour 
<br />Currency: Kika (10 Kika = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>Swamp of Maakenmire</h4>
<p>Ruler: Unknown 
<br />Capital: V'ka 
<br />Population: Unknown 
<br />Resources: Undeveloped 
<br />Currency: No system of currency</p>

<h4>The Infernal Hellswamp</h4>
<p>Ruler: Swamplord Vag'kroag 
<br />Capital: Unknown 
<br />Population: Unknown 
<br />Resources: Rare herbs, rare minerals 
<br />Currency: None</p>

<h4>The Bandit Domain of the Hammerlands</h4>
<p>Ruler: Baron Shinzar 
<br />Capital: Blackshroud 
<br />Population: 62,000 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, rare minerals, gems, mercenaries 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown) Kika (10 Kika = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Helotry of Ogia</h4>
<p>Ruler: Warchief Zegron 
<br />Capital: Xanar 
<br />Population: 42,000 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, silver, bronin, mercenaries, slaves 
<br />Currency: Kika (10 Kika = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Doomlands of Naaros</h4>
<p>Ruler: Unknown 
<br />Capital: Naaros (destroyed) 
<br />Population: Unknown 
<br />Resources: Mostly destroyed 
<br />Currency: None</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Darklords</title>

<h2>The Darklords</h2>

<p>During the Golden Age of the Shianti, Naar, the King of the Darkness, set about creating new and powerful servants to champion his cause and to reconquer the empire that was lost with the destruction of Naaros. Drawing upon the awesome power of his domain, he fashioned a race of supernatural creatures who were to become his generals in a war to end all wars. These terrible creatures were the Darklords of Helgedad.</p>

<h3>The Creatures of Helgedad</h3>

<h4>Helghast</h4>
<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Darklord Vashna originally bred the Helghast for the wars against the Sommlending. They are powerful, undead creatures who can adopt human form at will. This, coupled with their invulnerability to normal weapons, makes them ideally suited to missions of spying and assassination. They have greatly furthered the Darklord cause by the subversion of countries in Northern and Southern Magnamund.</p>

<h4>Vordak</h4>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Vordaks were the first undead to be summoned and controlled during Vashna's early experiments in the laboratories of Helgedad. Their skeletal bodies were formed around crystals of power called 'Vordak gems', and when they are destroyed they revert back to this crystal state. They possess strong psychic powers and often act as lieutenants in Darklord armies to control Drakkarim regiments.</p>

<h4>Zlanbeast/Kraan</h4>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Bred in the pits of Heigedad, the Zlanbeast, and their smaller sub-species the Kraan, were created as flying mounts for Darklord and Nadziranim commanders. Fed on the meat of Szalls and swamp Giaks, these creatures are strong and fierce, and enable the Darklords to travel with great speed. Vashna mustered a vast number to invade Sommerlund, and it was their air assault that destroyed the monastery of the Kai.</p>

<h4>Crypt Spawn</h4>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>These winged, brain-like creatures can be summoned by all Darklords from the plane of existence occupied by their master, Naar. They are as hideous as they are powerful, and are often used to guard Darklord chambers, tombs and treasures. Darklords can use a flood of Crypt Spawn to attack and overwhelm an enemy, or set a plague of them upon a land to despoil livestock and crops and create mayhem.</p>

<h4>Doomwolves</h4>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Larger and fiercer than the mountain wolves of Northern Magnamund, the Doomwolves were first bred in Helgedad to serve as mounts for Giak officers. They were hardy and quick to multiply in the wolf pens of the Black City, and were soon commonplace in every Darkland fortress. Large units of Doomwolves are employed to carry Giak lancers into battle, and as mounts for scouts and messengers.</p>

<h4>Xaghash</h4>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Although among the weakest of the lesser-Darklords, Xaghash are powerful creatures. They are always involved in complex schemes and court intrigues in attempts to ascend their evil hierarchy. To maintain their physical strength, they must devour warm-blooded creatures (preferably humans), and many of the attacks launched from the Darklands are raids to gather 'food' for these loathsome beings.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Lorin Faldon - Yound Archer</title>
<meta name="robots" content="noindex,nofollow">
<link rel="stylesheet" href="aon.css" type="text/css">
</head>

<body bgcolor="#ffffcc" text="black" link="#990000" alink="#990000" vlink="#990000">
<div class="title"><img src="title.gif" width="29" height="201" alt="The Magnamund Companion"></div>

<div class="body">


<h2>Sommerlund</h2>

<h3>Lorin Faldon - Young Archer</h3>

<p>I can remember my first bow, it was given to me by my father on my fifth birthday. He taught me to draw my bow using all my strength, not just my arms. 'Lay your body to the bow, Lorin,' he used to say, as I struggled to hit the stooks in our cornfield. I'd have no trouble hitting them now.</p>

<p>Our lands lie close to the Durncrag Range and at night you can sometimes hear Giaks calling one another in the hills. They are horrible creatures. Once they raided our village and killed our livestock; a cottage was burned down and Vinas the blacksmith was blinded in one eye. We lived in fear of them until the King built the watchtower at Shadow Pass, and Knight Hobar made the villagers train with bows so that they could defend themselves if the Giaks ever returned., I trained every day until I could split a plank at four hundred paces, and I learned to fledge my own arrows with goose feathers.</p>

<p>On my Oathday of Fehmarn, I was sent into service in the household of Knight Hobar. I was taught how to fight with a sword and a mace, but all I really wanted was to use a bow. Eventually, I got my chance. It was midsummer and a tournament was being held at Thornfalcon market. Knight Hobar granted us permission to attend but ordered: 'All boys must conduct themselves in a manner as befits Sommlending warriors.'</p>

<p>We wore our best white tunics and coats of mail, and held our heads high as we marched into the tournament stands. We had barely taken our seats when my eye fell upon a distant corner of the field. There, beyond the jousters and the tents, was an archery range. The targets were bales of twigs, stacked and cut to look like Giaks, with stunted arms and bow legs. A contest was set to commence. As my brothers shouted and cheered the joust, I sat in silence with my thoughts focused upon that distant range. The temptation was too great; I had to slip away and enter the archery contest myself. I wriggled beneath my seat and jumped down below the stand where I hid my surcoat and mail in a barrel. My shirt was quite plain and with my sleeves rolled up I easily passed for a stable lad or trades boy.</p>

<p>The judges chuckled when I paid my crown, and one even offered to help draw back my bowstring for fear I was too weak to manage it alone. I was given three arrows, and as I entered the field the crowd began to laugh and point their fingers at me. 'Who'll bet on the boy?' cried the umpire. 'Not I,' came the gamblers' unanimous reply. The first three rounds saw an end to the hopes of all but three archers: a cobbler, a woodsman and myself. Again the umpire called for bets, but none would wager gold on me. As my winning arrow hit the mark, the gamblers stopped laughing.</p>

<p>The news quickly spread and so caught up was I in the excitement of my victory that I didn't recognize the face of the man who handed me first prize until I had returned to my brothers at the tournament. He was my lord - Knight Hobar. My heart sank like a stone. To remove one's tunic and mail in a public place is considered dishonourable; I would be punished severely, of that I had no doubt. As I marched hesitantly into the castle keep, the gatehouse guard handed me a parchment. It was a summons to Knight Hobar's chambers. My legs started to shake and oh how I wished for the ground to open and swallow me up! Trembling all over, I knocked upon my master's door and entered.</p>

<p>'Lorin Faldon,' he boomed, 'you were ordered to conduct yourself as befits a warrior of the realm.'</p>

<p>I gritted my teeth and clenched my sweating palms as I awaited his wrath. But to my shocked surprise, he began to laugh.</p>

<p>'Calm yourself, boy,' he said, grinning broadly. 'You're a credit to your village and this household. Never have I seen such natural bowmanship in all my days.'</p>

<p>I could scarcely believe my ears.</p>

<p>'I have need of skilful archers,' he continued, 'especially those who would dare face a taunting crowd and the wrath of their master to prove their worth.'</p>

<p>That night my lord invited me to dine at his table, and the following day he ordered that I join the garrison of the watchtower at Shadow Pass, where my bow skill would be put to good use in the defence of my home and village. Now I am the youngest archer in the army of the King!</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Fantasy Fleets</title>

<h2>Modelling Magnamund</h2>

<h3>Fantasy Fleets</h3>

<p>The battle between Admiral Calfen's Durenese fleet and Vonotar's death-hulks is the climax of Fire on the Water. Overleaf, you can see part of the action being refought with models. Building fantasy ships is not that difficult - those overleaf were built mainly from card and strip balsa wood.</p>

<p>For a death-hulk or Durenese warship, you will need:</p>

<ol>
<li>Some mounting card. (Try artists' suppliers for large sheets or picture framers for cheap offcuts.)</li>
<li>Balsa strip for ships' rails and mouldings on the stern and forecastles. Use balsa block about 2 cms square for the ram on Vonotar's flagship.</li>
<li>Several pieces of dowel about 1/2 or 3/4 cm in diameter for masts and spars.</li>
<li>Cartridge or good quality typing paper for sails and, if you want to make several ships, to make a prototype for the various pieces.</li>
<li>Impact adhesive, e.g. Uhu.</li>
<li>Ready-made accessories. Anchors, pulleys, etc from model shops. Metal washers make good portholes, and figures like the bolt throwers come from Citadel Miniatures.</li>
<li>Modelling enamels for painting the ships.</li>
</ol>

<h4>Constructing a Basic Hull</h4>

<p>Using Fig 1 as a guide, draw out the ship's sections using a ruler and set square. These can be cut out and used as a pattern to produce as many identical parts as you need. Use a craft knife to cut the ship sections out of the card, and bend the ship's sides to correspond to the curve of the deck. Then glue the parts together as shown in Fig 2. This basic bull can then be decorated to become either a death hulk or warship. Add a section of dowel midway between the stern and forecastles to create a mast. Fix it in position under the deck with self-hardening modelling clay. Leave to set. Durenese ships should have intact mouldings on their stern and forecastles and smart card deckhouses with an overall bright paint finish. Their bulls are painted dark brown, drybrushed with a little pale khaki; the decks, masts and yards are painted light tan. Death hulks will have suffered damage during their time beneath the waves but don't overdo it. Small, jagged holes can be cut into the sides of the stern and forecastles to look like shattered planking and deckhouses can be made from irregular balsa planks. They should be painted black with dirty, greeny-brown decks, masts and spars. Grey or brown dry-brushing will pick out the texture and make the vessel's shape more apparent. Exposed ironwork should be painted rust brown with vertical streaks leading from it to simulate staining. Mould a lump of modelling clay textured with a pin to resemble seaweed, and paint it green. The evil flagship was made bigger to reflect its importance. It also has a derrick, which swivels round the mast and carries a cage of monsters to drop on unwary opponents. All the ships have sails and flags cut from paper, their designs painted with drawing ink or modelling enamels. The creases, where the sails are glued to the yards, are painted in a darker shade of the sail's basic colour.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Giak Language</title>

<h2>Giaks</h2>

<h3>The Giak Language</h3>

<h4>Giak Gramar</h4>

<p>Giak is a well-developed military language that evolved to meet the needs of inter-racial communication. The language is full of concepts relating to warfare, military construction and hunting: the three main Giak occupations. It is a harsh and guttural language with a limited range of vowel and consonant sounds, but it serves as a common tongue for all the creatures serving the Darklords of Helgedad.</p>

<p>The structure of Giak sentences uses the simple grammar of subject, verb and object, in that order. Any words that modify other words will follow them.</p>

<p>For example, the English sentence: 'The enemy of the Giaks escaped the black doomwolf of the Great Forest.' would be organized in Giak as follows:</p>

<table>
<tr><td>'Enemy of Giaks</td><td>escape</td><td>doomwolf black of Forest Great.' 
</td></tr>
<tr><td align="center">(subject)</td><td align="center">(verb)</td><td align="center">(object)</td></tr>
</table>

<p>The simplest form of this sentence is:</p>

<p>'Enemy/escape/doomwolf.'
<br />(Subject/verb/object)</p>

<p>with the following modifiers:</p>

<ol>
<li>The subject 'enemy' is modified by 'Giaks'.</li>
<li>The verb 'escape' is put into the past tense by using the adverb 'rannad'.</li>
<li>The object 'doomwolf' is modified by the adjective 'black' and the prepositional phrase 'of Forest Great'.</li>
</ol>

<p>This is the basic structure of the Giak language. The following pages contain the most commonly used Giak words.</p>

<h4>Numbers</h4>

<table>
<tr><td>1</td><td>Aki</td></tr>
<tr><td>2</td><td>Ig</td></tr>
<tr><td>3</td><td>Ga</td></tr>
<tr><td>4</td><td>Rorag</td></tr>
<tr><td>5</td><td>Ishrak</td></tr>
<tr><td>6</td><td>Narga</td></tr>
<tr><td>7</td><td>Na</td></tr>
<tr><td>8</td><td>Sha</td></tr>
<tr><td>9</td><td>Shak</td></tr>
<tr><td>10</td><td>Ishrakig</td></tr>
<tr><td>11</td><td>Da-aki</td></tr>
<tr><td>12</td><td>Da-ig</td></tr>
<tr><td>13</td><td>Da-ga</td></tr>
<tr><td>14</td><td>Darorag</td></tr>
<tr><td>15</td><td>Daishrak</td></tr>
<tr><td>16</td><td>Da-narga</td></tr>
<tr><td>17</td><td>Da-na</td></tr>
<tr><td>18</td><td>Da-sha</td></tr>
<tr><td>19</td><td>Da-shak</td></tr>
<tr><td>20</td><td>Gogoz</td></tr>
<tr><td>21</td><td>Gogoz-aki</td></tr>
</table>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Giaks</title>

<h2>Giaks</h2>

<p>These ferocious fighters, spawned in the dark dungeons of Helgedad, fear their evil masters more greatly than any mortal enemy. For centuries they have served the Darklords, bringing death and destruction to all who dare resist. It is said that on the field of battle there are but few sounds that match the blood-curdling clamour of the Giak war cry: '<span class="caps">SHEGGA</span>-<span class="caps">ASH</span>-<span class="caps">TAAG</span>!'</p>

<h3>The Giak Army</h3>

<p>During the early years of the Age of the Black Moon, the Darklords bred slaves to form the mainstay of their invading armies and for labour in the construction of fortresses and cities within the conquered lands. These slaves were the Giaks, and quickly they became respected as a formidable fighting force.</p>

<p>Under the command of Darklord Vashna, the Giaks built the notorious stronghold of Helgedad, a place that owes its name to the Giak language (Hel = black/gedad = city). Upon its completion, Vashna began breeding new types of Giak in many dreadful spawning pits deep below his infernal city. The fruits of his ghastly labour were a stronger and more fearless breed that could better withstand the hellish heat and poisonous atmospheres of the Darklands. They were small, squat and grey-skinned, with yellow fangs and eyes that could see clearly in the smoky dungeons of Helgedad. Ruthlessly, this new breed, the Mountain Giaks, persecuted the weaker earlier breeds, ruling over them in a society founded on strength, cruelty and fear.</p>

<p>As the Darklords expanded their empire, and as their need for bigger armies increased, the Giaks were used less frequently as slaves. Their society became wholly military, and a well-developed language evolved to fulfil their need for clear communication. In addition to their language, the Giaks are famed for their instinctive sense of order. Their armies are highly disciplined and well organized, with a strong chain of command. It is said that they fear their officers more greatly than any enemy, and this is borne out in many tales of Giak battles. With a strong leader they are fearless foes, but should their leader prove to be weak, or should he fall at a crucial moment, then Giak nerve is swift to break. The soldiers of Sommerlund were quick to realize this weakness during the siege of the Kai Monastery in <span class="caps">MS</span> 4219. By directing their bows against the attacking Giak officers, they succeeded in routing an army that totally outnumbered their own.</p>

<p>The Darklords were gravely worried by this weakness and sought to find leaders for their Giak armies who were less susceptible to arrows. Their search lasted many centuries, but eventually they discovered the ideal creature to lead their Giaks in battle - the Gourgaz. Gourgaz are huge swamp-dwelling reptilians that inhabit the Maakenmire swamp of Eastern Magnamund. Not only are they intelligent and uncannily battle-wise, they also have a special ability that makes them perfect for the role of Giak army leaders. When a Gourgaz engages in combat, it secretes an oil from scent glands that ridge the underside of its tail. This scent is odourless but when it is inhaled by Giaks, a chemical reaction takes place in their blood, stirring them to frenzy and total fearlessness.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Zegor Jok Dak Eg</title>

<h2>Giaks</h2>

<h3>Zegor Jok Dak Eg (How to Speak Giak)</h3>

<p>Now use your Giak grammar and vocabulary to make sentences in Giak.</p>

<p>For example, take the sentence. 'The merchant asked us to guard the treasure.' and rearrange it as explained on p. 68.</p>

<p>You now have: 'Merchant ask (past tense) to guard treasure us.' The basic Giak sentence would be: 'Merchant ask me'. The subject 'merchant' is not modified, but the verb 'ask' is modified by the phrase '(to) guard the treasure', and by being placed in the past tense by the use of the word 'rannad'. The object of the sentence 'I' is modified by adding the plural suffix, 'a'.</p>

<p>A direct translation of this rearranged sentence into Giak reads: 'Kikago jok rannad eg odak kika oka.' which, when written in Giak script, looks like this: (insert Giak sentence here)</p>

<p>Now that you can see how the Giak language works, why not try your hand at solving these three fun exercises:</p>

<ol>
<li>What does the following Giak phrase mean?
<br />'Zutgorak shok rannad kog zazgog naj odnenga ak.'</li>
<li>Translate the following English sentence into Giak:
<br />'The human wizard is strong. He will destroy our castle.'</li>
<li>What does this Giak sentence say?
<br />(insert Giak sentence here)</li>
</ol>

<p>For the answers please see page 73.</p>

<p>Answers to Giak Language Exercises on page 72:</p>

<ol>
<li>The monster lives in the temple near the red river.</li>
<li>Ziran orgaduk tukor. Dok ruzzar rogag gazad oka.</li>
<li>I fought three dwarf soldiers and I won.</li>
</ol>

<h4>The Official English/Giak Phrase Book</h4>
<p>Approved by H.A.T.E. (Helgedad Adventure Tour Enterprises)</p>

<p>A selection of everyday phrases you may find useful when visiting the city of Helgedad.</p>

<p>English - Your spear is hurting my chest. 
<br />Giak - Zuk okak zutag narg tadzar ok.</p>

<p>English - The view of the slave huts is nice. 
<br />Giak - Zee kor hezaa kuz hoki narg.</p>

<p>English - There is a monster in my bedroom. 
<br />Giak - Zutgorak narg kog shardar-ligaheza ok.</p>

<p>English - When is the tour of the Lake of Blood? 
<br />Giak - Tak-eg on narg Nengud-kor-Adez ta.</p>

<p>English - Your Doomwolf has eaten my shoes/friend/horse. 
<br />Giak - Akamaz okak raz rannad hagora/lug/nozod ok.</p>

<p>English - Please unchain me from this wall. 
<br />Giak - Ok naog-shuk jok zordak kor.</p>

<p>English - How much is a poisoned dagger? 
<br />Giak - Kez dak narg ogsha zejar rannad ta.</p>

<p>English - What is that incredible smell? 
<br />Giak - Teg narg zinoz gudjag ta.</p>

<p>English - Waiter, there's an undead in my soup. 
<br />Giak - Zutaagon kog nenigooga - kuz.</p>

<p>English - Do you have a map of the Burning Swamp? 
<br />Giak - Edaz jokog okak Nodog-Azagada kor ta.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Giak Word List</title>

<h2>Giaks</h2>

<h3>The Giak Word List</h3>

<table>
<tr><td>And (conj)</td><td>Ash</td></tr>
<tr><td>Army/War party (n)</td><td>Orgar/Dorgar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Ask/Demand (v)</td><td>Jok</td></tr>
<tr><td>At (prep)</td><td>Iak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Attack (n)</td><td>Dargag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Attack (v)</td><td>Darg</td></tr>
<tr><td>Bed (n)</td><td>Shardar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Big/Great (adj)</td><td>Gudjag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Black (adj)</td><td>Hel</td></tr>
<tr><td>Blood (n)</td><td>Adez</td></tr>
<tr><td>Blue (adj)</td><td>Gug</td></tr>
<tr><td>Boot/Shoe (n)</td><td>Hagor</td></tr>
<tr><td>Break (v)</td><td>Jez</td></tr>
<tr><td>Brown (adj)</td><td>Klag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Burn (v)</td><td>Azgad</td></tr>
<tr><td>But (conj)</td><td>Ka</td></tr>
<tr><td>Carry (v)</td><td>Kag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Castle/Stronghold (n)</td><td>Gazad</td></tr>
<tr><td>Chain (n)</td><td>Shuk</td></tr>
<tr><td>Champion (n)</td><td>Kookar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Charge (v)</td><td>Shaag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Chest (n)</td><td>Tadzar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Church/Temple (n)</td><td>Zazgog</td></tr>
<tr><td>City/Town (n)</td><td>Gedad</td></tr>
<tr><td>Climb (v)</td><td>Ezar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Close/shut (v)</td><td>Zen</td></tr>
<tr><td>Cold (adj)</td><td>Gour</td></tr>
<tr><td>Come (v)</td><td>Dez</td></tr>
<tr><td>Cut (v)</td><td>Shez</td></tr>
<tr><td>Dagger/Knife (n)</td><td>Ogsha</td></tr>
<tr><td>Danger (n)</td><td>Jatnar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Dark (adj)</td><td>Nad</td></tr>
<tr><td>Deep (adj)</td><td>Lenag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Defend (v)</td><td>Akag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Desert/Wasteland (n)</td><td>Adar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Destroy (v)</td><td>Ruzzar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Die (n)</td><td>Gaj</td></tr>
<tr><td>Dog (n)</td><td>Sheg</td></tr>
<tr><td>Doomwolf (n)</td><td>Akamaz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Drink (v)</td><td>Gag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Drink (n)</td><td>Gajog</td></tr>
<tr><td>Dwarf (n)</td><td>Shegtar</td></tr>
<tr><td>East (n)</td><td>Dej</td></tr>
<tr><td>Eat (v)</td><td>Raz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Eighty (adj)</td><td>Shazoz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Enemy (n)</td><td>Gaz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Escape (v)</td><td>Ozon</td></tr>
<tr><td>Fall (v)</td><td>Ekor</td></tr>
<tr><td>Far (adj/adv)</td><td>Ish</td></tr>
<tr><td>Fast (adj/adv)</td><td>Tagog</td></tr>
<tr><td>Fear (v)</td><td>Tuz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Fifty (adj)</td><td>Izraz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Fight (v)</td><td>Nak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Fire (n)</td><td>Kaggaz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Food (n)</td><td>Googa</td></tr>
<tr><td>For (prep)</td><td>Tor</td></tr>
<tr><td>Forty (adj)</td><td>Roraz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Free (adj)</td><td>Loga</td></tr>
<tr><td>Friend (n)</td><td>Lug</td></tr>
<tr><td>Get/fetch (v)</td><td>Ek</td></tr>
<tr><td>Giak (n)</td><td>Zegor</td></tr>
<tr><td>Go (v)</td><td>Der</td></tr>
<tr><td>Green (adj)</td><td>Shug</td></tr>
<tr><td>Guard (v)</td><td>Odak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Guard (n)</td><td>Odakar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Hammer (n)</td><td>Moggador</td></tr>
<tr><td>Hard (adj/adv)</td><td>Tadat</td></tr>
<tr><td>Hate (v)</td><td>Nig</td></tr>
<tr><td>He (n)</td><td>Dok</td></tr>
<tr><td>Head (n)</td><td>Nogjat</td></tr>
<tr><td>Hide (v)</td><td>Zek</td></tr>
<tr><td>Hold (v)</td><td>Jokog</td></tr>
<tr><td>Horse (n)</td><td>Nozod</td></tr>
<tr><td>Hot (adj)</td><td>Razi</td></tr>
<tr><td>House/Hut (n)</td><td>Heza</td></tr>
<tr><td>How (adv/conj)</td><td>Dak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Human (n)</td><td>Orgadak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Hunt (n)</td><td>Kon</td></tr>
<tr><td>Hunt (v)</td><td>Shegga</td></tr>
<tr><td>Hunter (n)</td><td>Konkor</td></tr>
<tr><td>I/me (n)</td><td>Ok</td></tr>
<tr><td>If (conj)</td><td>Dar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Ill/Disease/Sickness (v)/(n)</td><td>Ezog</td></tr>
<tr><td>In (prep)</td><td>Kog</td></tr>
<tr><td>Is/am/to be (v)</td><td>Narg</td></tr>
<tr><td>Kill (v)</td><td>Taag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Lake (n)</td><td>Nengud</td></tr>
<tr><td>Lead (v)</td><td>Okgan</td></tr>
<tr><td>Leader/Officer (n)</td><td>Oknar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Left (n)</td><td>Daz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Like/As (prep)</td><td>Tek</td></tr>
<tr><td>Listen/Hear (v)</td><td>Tan</td></tr>
<tr><td>Live (adj)</td><td>Shok</td></tr>
<tr><td>Long (adj)</td><td>Lozon</td></tr>
<tr><td>Make/Build/Erect (v)</td><td>Dag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Many (adj)</td><td>Kez</td></tr>
<tr><td>Map (n)</td><td>Edaz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Merchant (n)</td><td>Kikago</td></tr>
<tr><td>Monster (n)</td><td>Zutgorak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Move (v)</td><td>Daka</td></tr>
<tr><td>Near (adj)</td><td>Naj</td></tr>
<tr><td>New (adj)</td><td>Haag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Night (n)</td><td>Nadul</td></tr>
<tr><td>Ninety (adj)</td><td>Shakoz</td></tr>
<tr><td>No/Negative (adj)</td><td>Naog</td></tr>
<tr><td>North (n)</td><td>Aztar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Obey (v)</td><td>Okja</td></tr>
<tr><td>Of/From (prep)</td><td>Kor</td></tr>
<tr><td>Open (v)</td><td>Tok</td></tr>
<tr><td>Or (conj)</td><td>Nart</td></tr>
<tr><td>Order (v)</td><td>Zaz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Order (n)</td><td>Zazdak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Pain/Hurt (n/v)</td><td>Zutag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Plan (v)</td><td>Tuja</td></tr>
<tr><td>Pleasure/joy (n)</td><td>Hoki</td></tr>
<tr><td>Poison (n)</td><td>Zejar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Red (adj)</td><td>Ak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Rest (v)</td><td>Dat</td></tr>
<tr><td>Retreat (v)</td><td>Ogot</td></tr>
<tr><td>Ride (v)</td><td>Kluz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Right (n)</td><td>Jag</td></tr>
<tr><td>River (n)</td><td>Odnenga</td></tr>
<tr><td>Run (v)</td><td>Dakagog</td></tr>
<tr><td>Safe/Safety (adj/n)</td><td>Tanoz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Scout (v)</td><td>Rek</td></tr>
<tr><td>Scout (n)</td><td>Rekenar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Sea (n)</td><td>Egina</td></tr>
<tr><td>See (v)</td><td>Zee</td></tr>
<tr><td>Seventy (adj)</td><td>Nazgiz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Shoot (v)</td><td>Zaj</td></tr>
<tr><td>Shut/Close (v)</td><td>Kot</td></tr>
<tr><td>Sixty (adj)</td><td>Nizgaz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Slave (n)</td><td>Kuz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Slow (adj)</td><td>Jatnek</td></tr>
<tr><td>Small (adj)</td><td>Liga</td></tr>
<tr><td>Smell (v)</td><td>Zinoz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Soft(adj)</td><td>Zendod</td></tr>
<tr><td>Soldier (n)</td><td>Shad</td></tr>
<tr><td>South (n)</td><td>Zand</td></tr>
<tr><td>Spear (n)</td><td>Zuk</td></tr>
<tr><td>Stand (v)</td><td>Dan</td></tr>
<tr><td>Start/Begin (v)</td><td>Ekar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Stone (n)</td><td>Lajak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Stop/Halt (v)</td><td>Koa</td></tr>
<tr><td>Strong (adj)</td><td>Tukor</td></tr>
<tr><td>Succeed/Win (v)</td><td>Leka</td></tr>
<tr><td>Swamp/Marsh (n)</td><td>Nodog</td></tr>
<tr><td>Sword (n)</td><td>Shezag</td></tr>
<tr><td>Take (v)</td><td>Jeg</td></tr>
<tr><td>Thief (v)</td><td>Nenrak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Thirty (adj)</td><td>Gaggaz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Threaten (v)</td><td>Gan</td></tr>
<tr><td>To (prep)</td><td>Eg</td></tr>
<tr><td>Treasure/Wealth/Money (n)</td><td>Kika</td></tr>
<tr><td>Undead (n/adj)</td><td>Zutaagon</td></tr>
<tr><td>Up (adv/prep)</td><td>Tog</td></tr>
<tr><td>Use (v)</td><td>Oza</td></tr>
<tr><td>Wall (n)</td><td>Zordak</td></tr>
<tr><td>Want (v)</td><td>Aga</td></tr>
<tr><td>War (n)</td><td>Nadgaj</td></tr>
<tr><td>Water (n)</td><td>Nen</td></tr>
<tr><td>West (n)</td><td>Tozaz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Wet (adj)</td><td>Neni</td></tr>
<tr><td>What (adv/n)</td><td>Teg</td></tr>
<tr><td>When (adv/conj)</td><td>On</td></tr>
<tr><td>Where (adv/conj)</td><td>Ega</td></tr>
<tr><td>White (adv)</td><td>Orgad</td></tr>
<tr><td>Who/Whom (n)</td><td>An</td></tr>
<tr><td>Why (adv/conj)</td><td>Ka</td></tr>
<tr><td>With (prep)</td><td>Ar</td></tr>
<tr><td>Wizard/Sorcerer (n)</td><td>Ziran</td></tr>
<tr><td>Wood (n)</td><td>Kona</td></tr>
<tr><td>Wrong/Bad (adj)</td><td>Zut</td></tr>
<tr><td>Yellow (adj)</td><td>Staz</td></tr>
<tr><td>Yes/Positive (adv)</td><td>Gee</td></tr>
<tr><td>You (n)</td><td>Okak</td></tr>
</table>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Kai Lords</title>

<h2>The Kai Lords</h2>

<p>Of the Sommlending who first appeared from out of the Northern Void, to defeat the Darklords and establish the sun-realm of Sommerlund, there were some who possessed a great strength that lay undeveloped within them. Greater powers of mind and body, and combat skills far beyond the reach of other men were attainable to these special few. These remarkable warriors became known as the Kai Lords of Sommerlund.</p>

<h3>The Rise of the Kai Lords</h3>

<p>The first Kai Lord was a noble warrior, a Baron of Toran, who achieved distinction during the Great Battle of Maakengorge. Aided by the magicians of Dessi, he came to realize the true nature of his powers and the purpose for which they were bestowed. For on their prompting, he searched for and found the Lorestones of Nyxator, and through them unlocked the wisdom and strength that lay dormant within him.</p>

<p>In the year <span class="caps">MS</span> 3810, he built a monastery high in the hills of Western Sommerlund, on lands of the Royal Estate, and established the Order of the Kai. The monastery became a warrior school devoted to the development of the powerful disciplines that lay within all true Kai Lords. He took the name 'Sun Eagle', partly in honour of the sun-realm and partly in recognition of his baronial eagles' crest, and recorded the wisdom of his discoveries in a great tome that became known as the Book of the Magnakai. Guided by the wisdom of this book and the personal instruction of Kai Grand Master, Sun Eagle, the Order of the Kai flourished and grew. Children in the households of Knights of the Realm who were seen to possess dormant kai disciplines, were sent to the monastery to receive special training. They entered a caring but very strict society where their true potential as warrior lords was developed to the highest level. The skills by which they had first come to the attention of their liege-lords were honed to perfection under the watchful eye of the Kai Masters. Besides the Kai Disciplines, they were also taught the virtues of truth, honour and selfless courage.</p>

<p>After one year, they each received a new name. It was given to them by their teachers on the feast day of Fehmarn, and it reflected qualities in their growing personalities. Gradually, as the young novices mastered each of the ten basic Kai Disciplines, they were awarded ranks and titles and given greater responsibilities both inside and away from the monastery. At the rank of Warmarn or Journeyman, a Kai Lord was either sent into the service of the Sommlending Army to accustom himself to the command of troops, or sent abroad to gather information about the lands bordering his realm. Upon complete mastery of all ten basic Kai Disciplines, a Kai Lord became a Kai Master. The pupil was now a teacher whose role it was to train young novices in the way of the Kai.</p>

<p>But a Kai Master's learning was still incomplete, for beyond the ten basic skills there awaited the higher Kai Disciplines. The 'Magnakai' skills were handed down through each generation of Kai Masters by personal instruction and study of the Book of the Magnakai. The skills were divided into groups, each of which was governed by a separate training school called a 'lore-circle'. By mastering all of the Magnakai Disciplines of a lore-circle, the Kai Masters increased their fighting prowess and their physical and mental stamina to a level far higher than any mortal warrior could have otherwise attained.</p>

<h3>The Kai Monastery</h3>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>The Kai Monastery built by Sun-Eagle in <span class="caps">MS</span> 3810. Situated high in the hills of Western Sommerlund, the monastery became a warrior school devoted to the development of the Kai Disciplines. Here potential Kai Lords were trained in all the warrior skills and imbued with the virtues of truth, honour and courage.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Lastlander/Old Kingdom Nations</title>

<h2>The Nations of Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Lastlander/Old Kingdom Nations</h3>

<h4>The Kingdom of Durenor</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Alin <span class="caps">IV</span> 
<br />Capital: Hammerdal 
<br />Population: 96,000 + 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, agriculture, shipbuilding, gold, silver, copper, fish, gems, timber 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

<p>The peninsula of Durenor was the first territory claimed by the Ulnarian peoples when they came to Magnamund in <span class="caps">MS</span> 2829. They encountered little resistance to their expansion; the outlaws and corsairs (mainly fugitives from Vassagonian law) who had settled along the southern coast, fled to Cloeasia and the Lakuri Isles when confronted by the Ulnarian armies. The second migration (<span class="caps">MS</span> 3434) saw the arrival of Durenor's greatest ally, the Sommlending, and the construction of the city of Hammerdal.</p>

<h4>The Magiocracy of Dessi</h4>
<p>Ruler: 'Magi Regnanti' (The Council of Elder Wizards) 
<br />Capital: Elzian 
<br />Population: 4000 + 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, gold, silver, platinum, rare gems, minerals <br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

<p>The Magicians of Dessi are all that remains of the great Elder Magi, the race of beings from whom all magical power stems. Sent to destroy Agarash and to deliver Magnamund out of the age of Eternal Night, the Elder Magi brought about his final downfall during the War of One Thousand Years (3572 <span class="caps">MS</span>). In 2514 <span class="caps">MS</span>, their numbers were decimated in the Great Plague. The surviving magicians sought refuge in the mountains of Dessi and have lived there ever since.</p>

<h4>The Free State of Chaman</h4>
<p>Ruler: Arch-Chief Borghanaphon 
<br />Capital: Gleesh 
<br />Population: 11,000 + 
<br />Resources: Fishery, timber, copper, bronin
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<p>The government and populace of this independent free state are made up almost exclusively of Kloons - an intelligent race of Drodarin descent. They are to be found throughout the Stornlands and have a reputation for being scholarly and industrious creatures. The city of Gleesh is one of the great trading ports of the Tentarias, a fact attributed to the renowned business acumen and wisdom of the country's ruler - Arch-Chief Borghanaphon.</p>

<h4>The Isle of the Sianti - (Isle of Lorn)</h4>
<p>Ruler: High Wizard Acarya 
<br />Capital: Temple of Amida 
<br />Population: 1500 
<br />Resources: Self-supporting - agriculture, fish, timber 
<br />Currency: None</p>

<p>Surrounded by the mage-winds and illusions of the Sea of Dreams, the Isle of Lorn is the last refuge of a race of lesser gods called the Shianti. They were exiled to this small island by command of the Goddess Ishir, and they pledged themselves to remain separate from the peoples and lands of Magnamund, and to take no further part in the destiny of mankind.</p>

<h4>The Plenary of Bautar</h4>
<p>Ruler: Magnalord Fennic 
<br />Capital: Talon 
<br />Population: 8000 +
<br />Resources: Rare herbs, timber, fish, copper, bronin 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

<h4>The Realm of Ruel</h4>
<p>Ruler: Grand Druid Cadak 
<br />Capital: Mogaruith 
<br />Population: 8000
<br />Resources: Rare herbs, timber, fish 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Gynarchy of Telchos</h4>
<p>Ruler: Council of Thirty 
<br />Capital: Telchos 
<br />Population: 30,000 + 
<br />Resources: Silver, platinum, iron ore, gold, agriculture, fish, rare gems
<br />Currency: Telc (1 Telc = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Modelling Magnamund</title>

<h2>Modelling Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Kai Monastery</h3>

<p>It you want to start re-fighting Lone Wolf's adventures in miniature, where better to start than at the Kai Monastery. It was here that the Darklords struck their greatest blow against Sommerlund, when on the Feast of Fehmarn, they launched a surprise attack on the Kai Lords.</p>

<p>On the left, you can see the Darklords launching their final assault. Those Kai with the swiftest reactions have snatched up weapons in a desperate attempt to stop the Giaks and Drakkarim bursting in. In the foreground, a Giak Shaman has loosed a fireball at the defending Kai warriors, killing some and wounding others. Doomwolves are waiting to pour through the gap in the Kai lines.</p>

<p>The model of the monastery was designed with a flat back to allow it to be placed up against the edge of a war-games table. The towers and keep have no back wall, enabling you to see the figures inside. The monastery is about 100 cms long - a fairly large model for an inexperienced modeller but the same techniques can be used to make smaller, less detailed models.</p>

<p>First of all, draw a simple plan of your model showing the layout of the building and its dimensions. Rooms should be relatively large as figure bases take up a lot of room. If you need help deciding what to build, try the junior history section of your local library.</p>

<h4>The Materials</h4>

<p>All the materials you need for making models are cheap and readily available in hobby or <span class="caps">DIY</span> shops or artists' suppliers.</p>

<p>You will need:</p>

<ol>
<li>Some polystyrene ceiling tiles for walls and floors.</li>
<li>Some <span class="caps">PVA</span> glue. (This is for sticking the polystyrene tiles together. Don't use any other type of glue as it may dissolve the plastic.)</li>
<li>A piece of hardboard or chipboard for the model's base. For a small model use hardboard but for a larger model (over 30 cms square) use chipboard as it's less likely to warp.</li>
<li>A sheet of thin plasticard (to simulate stone work).</li>
<li>A tube of ready-mixed household filler, such as Tetrion or Polyfiller.</li>
<li>Some strip balsa wood (for door- and window-frames or mouldings on the building's exterior).</li>
<li>Dressmaking pins (to reinforce the corners and to hold the model together while the glue dries).</li>
<li>Cork bark (for any rocks or boulders on the base of your model). For small amounts try model railway shops; for large amounts try a garden centre or florist.</li>
<li>Ready-made accessories. The doors and windows of the Kai Monastery are white-metal castings. You should be able to buy them at model shops. (Note: Citadel Miniatures have a worldwide mailing service. Their address is: Chewton St, Hilltop, Eastwood, Notts.) In plastic, they are available from model railway shops. You can make your own from balsa or plastic strip but they take a long time and look less finished. Statues can be made by painting figures grey. Use the larger plastic figures for huge statues.</li>
<li>Emulsion paint. If your model is meant to be a stone building, it will look best if painted in shades of grey. You can tint white paint by adding a little poster or powder colour. You can usually buy small quantities of paint at <span class="caps">DIY</span> shops.</li>
</ol>

<h4>Instructions</h4>

<ol>
<li>The base. Cut a piece of hardboard or chipboard to the required size. Allow about 3 cms all around your model. If by any chance you have a jigsaw or keyhole saw, use this to cut the base in an irregular shape. Use sandpaper to remove roughness round the edge.</li>
<li>Walls and floors. Using a ruler and set square and a fine felt tip pen, draw the shapes of the walls and floor on the polystyrene ceiling tiles. Take care to ensure they're accurate. Mark in position the outlines of any doors or windows you require.</li>
<li>Cutting out the pieces. Use a craft knife or scalpel to cut out the pieces of polystyrene. Any straight edges, door and window apertures should be cut by drawing the knife very carefully along the edge of a ruler.</li>
<li>Putting it together. Pin the pieces together to make sure they fit. If everything fits, brush the edges to be joined with <span class="caps">PVA</span> glue and press them together. Push a pin deep into each joint to hold it together. (See Fig 1.) Remember not to glue the fourth wall if your model is to be free-standing. When everything is glued together, allow the model to dry.</li>
<li>Doors and windows. If you are making your own, use balsa wood glued together with an impact adhesive like Uhu. (See Fig 2.) Make them to the same size as the holes in your model. Do not attempt to fit them in place until the glue has set hard.</li>
<li>Stonework. Take your plasticard and with a ruler and craft knife, score its surface in a grid to make a large number of rectangles of different sizes (none should be larger than 1 1/2 cms). Snap them off into individual pieces. Using the <span class="caps">PVA</span> glue, fix the pieces in irregular clusters on the exterior of your building (see Fig 3). Glue the larger pieces on the corners as shown. If you are making a building with a removable side, look closely at Fig 4 before gluing the plasticard pieces onto the building. The corner pieces should only be fixed to the edge of the removable side. This will disguise any join between the loose wall and the main building. Now glue the model to the base, using the <span class="caps">PVA</span> adhesive.</li>
<li>Plastering. Wait until the glue holding the stonework in place has completely dried. Then, using a small spatula or scrap of plasticard fill any gaps round the doors and windows with a little of the ready-mixed filler. Thin down some of the filler with a little water until it's like thin custard and then paint it all over the inside and outside of the building. If your model is built with a removable side, don't brush any plaster where the pieces of plasticard grip the walls as the increased thickness of the dried filler may prevent the loose section fitting properly.</li>
<li>The Base. If you wish to have a rocky base, you should glue your cork bark into position with an impact adhesive such as Uhu. Then spread unthinned filler over the base right up to the walls and round any cork rocks so that they appear to be sunk into the ground. Make sure it sets with a rough texture but while it's still soft, add small objects (twigs, stones, treasure chests, severed heads!) for extra interest. If your building has a removable side take care not to plaster the loose section into place.</li>
<li>Painting. Make sure the plaster has dried. Use only emulsion paint on the polystyrene pieces. If you have a removable wall, remove and paint separately. Paint the interior in the colour of your choice. For the exterior and stone flooring: first paint all the exposed stonework medium grey and let it dry. Then put a little light grey paint on your brush and wipe it firmly with a rag. Now draw the brush lightly over the surface from side to side and up and down. This technique (dry-brushing) picks out the texture of the stonework and makes the building look more three dimensional. Next dry-brush the building with the off-white paint, very lightly, using up and down strokes. This highlights those parts that would catch the sunlight. When the emulsion has dried, paint the doors and windows with modelling enamel in either dark brown or white. Paint the base next using medium green for grass, dry-brushed with yellow (when dry) to pick out the rough textures. Dry-brush cork rocks with off-white.</li>
</ol>

<p>Your building is now complete. If you want to furnish the inside, visit your games shop and look at their range of miniature furniture. Or make your own using balsa wood strip and thin card.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Mythenish/Tianese Nations</title>

<h2>The Nations of Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Mythenish/Tianese Nations</h3>

<h4>The Autocracy of Bhanar</h4>
<p>Ruler: Imperial Autarch Sejanoz 
<br />Capital: Otavai 
<br />Population: 350,000 + 
<br />Resources: Fish, shipbuilding, timber, agriculture, silver, copper, jadin 
<br />Currency: Ren (10 Ren = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>Following the creation of Bhanar during the Great Civil War (<span class="caps">MS</span> 1620), the Imperial Autarch set about the expansion of his empire. In the north, vast tracts of dense timberland were laid bare and the city of Sejanoz built in his honour. Rumour is rife that the Imperial Autarch has entered into a pact with the demonic creatures of Naaros: it is based on the fact that Autarch Sejanoz has not aged a day since the completion of the city, over 3000 years ago.</p>

<h4>The Kingdom of Vaduzhan</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Rhetaka 
<br />Capital: Vaduz 
<br />Population: 120,000 + 
<br />Resources: Fish, timber, shipbuilding, gold, silver, iron ore, copper, spices 
<br />Currency: Ren (10 Ren = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Island Principalities of Nyhtan</h4>
<p>Ruler: Grand Prince Tsumobi 
<br />Capital: Shotia 
<br />Population: 43,000 
<br />Resources: Shipbuilding, fish, silver, copper, spices 
<br />Currency: Ren (10 Ren = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>Chai</h4>
<p>Ruler: Khea-khan of Pensei 
<br />Capital: Pensei 
<br />Population: 89,000 + 
<br />Resources: Fish, timber, gold, silver, iron ore, agriculture, copper, bronin, jadin 
<br />Currency: Ren (10 Ren = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>The natural defences of Chai - mountains, swamps and dense forests - have protected her from aggressive neighbours for over three thousand years. Long ago, during the Age of Eternal Night, the land of Chai was stalked by hideous monsters - the creatures of Agarash the Damned. When he was destroyed, his creatures scattered into the wilderness of Chai. Many are alive to this day, hiding deep in swamp, burrow and cave.</p>

<h4>The Plainlands of Lissan</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Samu (in exile) 
<br />Capital: Rakholi (The Tent City of) 
<br />Population: 220,000 (prior to <span class="caps">MS</span> 5054) 
<br />Resources: Horses, agriculture, copper, silver, iron ore 
<br />Currency: Hen (10 Ren = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Province of Suhn</h4>
<p>Ruler: Mother Magri 
<br />Capital: Port of Suhn 
<br />Population: 25,000 + 
<br />Resources: Fish, spices, rare herbs, rare minerals, shipbuilding
<br />Currency: Noble (1 Noble = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Province of Andui</h4>
<p>Ruler: Mother Chow-loon 
<br />Capital: Andui 
<br />Population: 8000 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, iron ore, copper 
<br />Currency: Noble (1 Noble = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Desolation of Taklakot</h4>
<p>Ruler: The Mad King of Gyanima 
<br />Capital: Gyanima: The Forbidden City 
<br />Population: Unknown 
<br />Resources: Mostly destroyed 
<br />Currency: Kote (10 Kotes = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Freedom Guild of Karnali</h4>
<p>Ruler: Sado of the Long Knife 
<br />Capital: Karnali 
<br />Population: 17,000 
<br />Resources: Rare hides, rare minerals, agriculture, fish 
<br />Currency: Noble (1 Noble = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Principality of Forlu</h4>
<p>Ruler: Mother Lhasa 
<br />Capital: Forlu 
<br />Population: 36,000 + 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, timber, iron ore, jadin 
<br />Currency: Noble (1 Noble = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>Formally ruled by the corrupt household of Mesanna, this principality suffered its ruthless leadership for several centuries. The populace grew weaker and poorer as the Lords of Mesanna hoarded the wealth of the jadin-rich Shuri mountains. They entered into an alliance with the evil forces of the Shadakine Empire, but were betrayed during the War of the Winds. For the Shadakine invaded and took control of the Mesanna palace in Forlu, throwing the former corrupt rulers to the angry citizens.</p>

<h4>The State of Korli</h4>
<p>Ruler: Mother Solani 
<br />Capital: Korli 
<br />Population: 15,000 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, fish, shipbuilding 
<br />Currency: Noble (1 Noble = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>One of the oldest Tianese states, Korli was first established in the year <span class="caps">MS</span> 675 by the ruling household of Lord Margos. It flourished and grew wealthy from its trade with neighbouring provinces, its command of the Kalamar river, and its large merchant fleet. Civil War with the breakaway state of Andui, led by renegade Prince Junai and his Knights of Abbali, weakened her but control of the rich township of Abbali was never lost. Following the War of the Winds in <span class="caps">MS</span> 4663, Korli fell to the invading Shadakine Empire.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Nael/Nael-Aluvian Nations</title>

<h2>The Nations of Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Nael/Nael-Aluvian Nations</h3>

<h4>The Kindom of Klarnos</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Hulz 
<br />Capital: Dragen 
<br />Population: 96,000 
<br />Resources: Gold, iron ore, fish, shipbuilding agriculture, copper <br />Currency: Orla (2 Orla = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<p>Klarnos was the first territory to be settled by the Nael peoples in <span class="caps">MS</span> 1309. They claimed the land by force from the kingdom of Cincoria, and secured for themselves the gold-rich Klann mountains of north. Further Nael expansion led to the Great Plains War with Lunarlia in which they were defeated at the Battle of Kaylar Flat (<span class="caps">MS</span> 1366). Mountains and desert sandstorms have prevented any contact with Telchos, and the continued hostility of Cincoria and Lunarlia has forced Klarnos to rely heavily on sea trade with the Mythenish nations.</p>

<h4>The Grand Principalities of Slovia</h4>
<p>Ruler: Grand Prince Ormond of Suentina 
<br />Capital: Suentina 
<br />Population: 190,000 
<br />Resources: Cloth, textiles, agriculture, iron ore, silver, bronin <br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<p>The fertile plains of Slovia are divided into many principalities which are united, albeit precariously, by the rule of Grand Prince Ormond. War is a constant threat to the Slovians, who face hostile enemies to the north, east and west. A large regular army, comprised in the main of mercenaries and horse knights, keep the land secure and aid her ally, Anari. Recently, it is feared that Darklord subversion has undermined the Grand Prince's court, and civil war seems imminent.</p>

<h4>The Confederated Principalities of Salony</h4>
<p>Ruler: Prince Ewevin of Rhem 
<br />Capital: Rhem 
<br />Population: 42,000 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, timber, shipbuilding, iron ore, mercenaries, rare minerals 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

<p>Descended from both Aluvian and Nael stock, the people of Salony have struggled hard to maintain their independence. Their land-locked principalities have suffered, more than any other Stornland nation, from the countless wars that ravage that region. They emerged victorious from the War of the Lorestone due, in part, to the sinister aid they received from the Cener Druids of Ruel.</p>

<h4>The Kingdom of Siyen</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Oridon <span class="caps">IV</span> 
<br />Capital: Seroa 
<br />Population: 480,000 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, timber, shipbuilding, fish, iron ore, copper, gold, gems, bronin, tin, rare metals 
<br />Currency: Orla (2 Orla = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<p>The kingdom of Siyen was founded by the Nael peoples during their early migration across central Magnamund. Following the Great Plains War, Siyen was cut off from its parent land of Klanos by the Union of Lunarlia. It grew strong from its command over the Tentarius, and from the skilful use of its rich natural resources. King Oridon maintains a large standing army and battle fleet. Of all the neighbouring states, only Rezovia is friendly.</p>

<h4>The Kingdom of Rezovia</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Delhan
<br />Capital: Maula 
<br />Population: 92,000 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, fish, shipbuilding, timber, tin, copper
<br />Currency: Orla (2 Orla = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Palinate of Firalond</h4>
<p>Ruler: Grandar Beylian 
<br />Capital: Firina 
<br />Population: 89,000 + 
<br />Resources: Cloth, textiles, agriculture, iron ore (little) 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Theocracy of Valerion</h4>
<p>Ruler: Fathers of the Truth 
<br />Capital: Kelis 
<br />Population: 66,000 
<br />Resources: Timber, rare metals, rare minerals, agriculture, silver, fish 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Senatocracy of Lourden</h4>
<p>Ruler: The Senate of Arlcor 
<br />Capital: Pforodon 
<br />Population: 106,000 
<br />Resources: Cloth, textiles, agriculture, silver, minerals, iron ore
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Nations of Magnamund</title>

<h2>The Nations of Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Races of Magnamund</h3>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Drakkar Assault-Trooper
<br />c.<span class="caps">MS</span> 5050
<br />Drakkarim Assault-Troopers are used by the Darklords to spearhead Giak attacks. They favour weapons of black steel. This warrior's red helmet plume signifies over 100 'kills'.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Varetian Mercenary
<br />c.<span class="caps">MS</span> 4405
<br />This Aluvian pikeman is typical of many soldiers of fortune who fought in the Stornlands during the War of the Lorestone. He wears the red and white livery of Varetta.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Lencian Crusader
<br />c.<span class="caps">MS</span> 2754
<br />This Vaderish foot knight wears Lencian plate armour. Lightly armoured Drakkarim archers constantly outmanoeuvred these knights in the second crusade.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Ice Barbarian Scout
<br />c.<span class="caps">MS</span> 5000
<br />This fur-clad warrior is equipped with bone armour, skis (formerly the ribs of Kalte mammoths), and a backpack that is specially designed to carry a bow-wielding child.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Sharnazim Warrior
<br />c.<span class="caps">MS</span> 5050
<br />The Vassa guard the Grand Palace and the royal family of Vassagonia. They are famed for their skill with wide-bladed scimitars known as 'bitikali'.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Drodayin Tower-Gunner
<br />c.<span class="caps">MS</span> 4967
<br />Tower-Gunners, armed with axes and primitive handguns, are employed to defend the entrances to the mountain kingdom of Bor.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<p>Imperial Chai Guardsman
<br />c.<span class="caps">MS</span> 5000
<br />This famous Mythenish warrior is wearing a ceremonial 'armour of life'. His gold collar and epaulettes denote his rank of guard-captain, and his weapon is a 'kirusami'.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Primitive/Drodarin Nations</title>

<h2>The Nations of Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Primitive/Drodarin Nations</h3>

<h4>The Kingdom of Starn</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Korl 
<br />Capital: Mount Vost 
<br />Population: 2000 + 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, gold, gems, rare minerals, bronin, silver <br />Currency: Ain (1 Ain = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>The Drodarin giants of Starn have occupied the halls of Mount Vost ever since the Age of the Old Kingdoms. They are an insular race who have shunned all contact with humans since the Great Plague of 2514 <span class="caps">MS</span> devastated their population. A strong bond of friendship exists with the dwarves of Boden, who, in spite of their great physical differences, are also of Drodarin descent.</p>

<h4>The Free State of Caron</h4>
<p>Ruler: Svedchek Moldo 
<br />Capital: Orello 
<br />Population: 6000 + 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, copper, timber, fish, shipbuilding, agriculture, silver 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>This small but resourceful free state is the home of a Drodarin race of blue-skinned creatures called Ogrons. Closely related to the dwarves of Bor and the giants of Starn, they frequently have had cause to call on their aid to repel their sinister neighbours - the Cenerese of Ruel - from their northern territories.</p>

<h4>The Kelderwastes</h4>
<p>Ruler: Count Laj of Sheasu 
<br />Capital: Sheasu 
<br />Population: 2000 + (Sheasu)/30,000 (Mainland) 
<br />Resources: Shipbuilding, fish, agriculture 
<br />Currency: Ren (10 Ren = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>The Isle of Sheasu is the only human settlement in the Kelderwastes, the mainland being a vast jungle populated by lizards and other semi-intelligent reptilians of Agarashi descent, that fled there after the fall of Naaros. Count Laj rules over a small population of exiles from several nations who, for a variety of reasons, choose not to return to the lands of their birth.</p>

<h4>The Kingdom of Bor</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Ryvin 
<br />Capital: Boradon 
<br />Population: 130,000 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, copper, silver, platinum, rare minerals, rare metals, gems, gold 
<br />Currency: Ain (1 Ain = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>The kingdom of Bor is the home of all Drodarin dwarves of Northern Magnamund. The vast hills and chambers at the heart of the Great Bor Range were formed by the labour and skill of these stout and stubborn folk. Their ingenuity (particularly in the field of innovative weapon and armour design) and their tales of bravery and endeavour are famed throughout the whole of Magnamund.</p>

<h4>The Kingdom of Boden</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Lomaer <span class="caps">II</span>
<br />Capital: Anarin 
<br />Population: 120,000 + 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, bronin, gold, silver, rare metals, rare minerals, agriculture, fish 
<br />Currency: Ain (1 Ain = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Burntlands of Lara</h4>
<p>Ruler: Shasarak the Wytch-king 
<br />Capital: None 
<br />Population: 2000 + 
<br />Resources: Sparse agriculture 
<br />Currency: Noble (1 Noble = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Cloud-Realm of the Azanam</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Okosa 
<br />Capital: None 
<br />Population: 12,000 
<br />Resources: Rare herbs, rare minerals, timber, spices 
<br />Currency: None</p>

<h4>The Dark Forest of Fernmost</h4>
<p>Ruler: None 
<br />Capital: None 
<br />Population: Doubtful 
<br />Resources: Rare herbs, rare flora, rare timbers 
<br />Currency: None</p>

<h4>The Icy Wastes of Kalte</h4>
<p>Ruler: Brumalmarc Kzu'tooa 
<br />Capital: Ljuk 
<br />Population: 6000 
<br />Resources: Furs 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown (Ljuk only)</p>

<h4>The Wilderlands of Kaum</h4>
<p>Ruler: Unknown 
<br />Capital: None 
<br />Population: 1000 + 
<br />Resources: Silver, gems, rare metals, rare herbs 
<br />Currency: None</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</title>

<h2>Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</h2>

<h3>Introduction</h3>

<p>The Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl is a multi-player role-playing game where you have the chance to play the part of Ragadorn's famous, or infamous, inhabitants. For maximum enjoyment and excitement players should try to act as though they are the characters dealt them (hence the term 'role-playing'). Whether your character is a native of the city or a visitor, a night to remember awaits you in the Ragadorn Ale-house.</p>

<h3>Preparation</h3>

<p>Before play can begin, you will need to cut out the coloured playing pieces and the Combat Results Table that appear on p. 95. The Character Profiles on pp. 48-9 should be copied out onto separate cards, or alternatively, they can be photocopied, cut out and stuck onto individual cards. (Players may find it convenient to photocopy these rules in advance of play, as reference to them will be impractical once the game is in progress.)</p>

<h3>Game Equipment</h3>

<ul>
<li>Playing Board</li>
<li>3 Torch Counters</li>
<li>10 Character Profile Cards</li>
<li>10 Player Counters</li>
<li>3 Non-Player Counters</li>
<li>3 Bucket Counters</li>
<li>9 Loot Counters</li>
<li>3 Food Counters</li>
<li>9 Chair Counters</li>
<li>1 Broom Counter</li>
<li>6 Bottle Counters</li>
<li>1 Helghast Marker</li>
<li>1 Axe</li>
<li>9 Special Item Counters</li>
<li>10 Gambling Counters</li>
<li>1 Combat Results Table/<a href="random.htm">Random Number Table</a></li>
<li>1 Character Grid</li>
</ul>

<h3>Setting-up</h3>

<ol>
<li>The game is designed for 2 to 10 players, each controlling one or more of the characters.</li>
<li>Characters are allocated to players according to the number of players taking part. Consult the Character Grid for details.</li>
<li>Players take their Character Profile Cards.</li>
<li>The Landlord player mixes the Special Item counters and places one face downwards on each of the Character Profile Cards. (See Heighast rules for special conditions.)</li>
<li>Players may now look at their Special Item counters and adjust their Character Profile Cards depending on the nature of the Special Item received.</li>
<li>Each player draws the coloured Player Counter for their respective character or characters.</li>
</ol>

<p>The Landlord player now prepares the gameboard as follows:</p>

<ol>
<li>Place Chair and Tavern Item counters face upwards on the playing board. Care should be taken to place them in realistic positions on the board e.g. chairs should be set around tables, torches next to walls, etc.</li>
<li>Place the Landlord Player Counter and the 3 Non-Player Counters on the board. At least one of the Serving Girls should be placed behind the bar, and the Croupier should be adjacent to the Gaming Table.</li>
<li>Place the 9 Loot Counters face downwards anywhere on the board. If a Loot Counter occupies the same square as a Non-Player Character counter, the loot is considered to be in the possession of that non-player character. If a Loot Counter is placed on the same square as the Bar, the Gaming Table, a Tavern Item or a piece of furniture (chair or table), then the Loot Counter is considered to be hidden from view (see 'Hidden Counters')</li>
</ol>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</title>

<h2>Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</h2>

<h3>Ragadorn Tavern Game Characters</h3>

<p>Lone Wolf
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 18
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 34 
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 5 
<br />Weapon: Magic Spear 
<br />Gold Crowns: 10</p>
<p>You are Lone Wolf. A scroll found on the body of a dead Giak messenger in the Durncrag mountains points to a Darklord plot to take control of Ragadorn. You arrived in the city last night and were attacked by a Helghast. Fortunately, you fought it off with your Magic Spear. You have now tracked the Helghast to this ale-house and you are sure that it has taken on the appearance of one of the customers.</p>
<p>Your objective: To uncover the Helghast and kill it before it kills you.</p>

<p>Magician 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 13 
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 22 
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 3 
<br />Weapon: Dagger
<br />Gold Crowns: 0</p>
<p>You are a Journeyman from the Magicians Guild of Toran. You reached Ragadorn this morning, but as soon as you stepped inside the city gate you were attacked by a street thief. In the fight the thief fell on his dagger and died. You kept the dagger and the Special Item that was in the thief's pocket. Since then you have heard that the thieves' guild are now on the lookout for you.</p>
<p>Your objective: To acquire 20 Gold Crowns for the coach fare to the safety of Durenor.</p>

<p>Mercenary 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 15 
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 28 
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 4 
<br />Weapon: Sword 
<br />Gold Crowns: 16</p>
<p>You are a Soldier of Fortune from Varetta. Two months ago, your regiment was lured into an ambush and massacred. You were the only one to survive and you have sworn to take revenge on the traitor who betrayed your comrades. He, like yourself, is a mercenary from Varetta, and you have learned that he is in hiding in Ragadorn. You have never seen this man, but you know that he often disguises himself as a Magician or a Ranger.</p>
<p>Your objective: To kill the Magician and the Ranger.</p>

<p>Knight 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 16 
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 26 
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 4 
<br />Weapon: Broadsword 
<br />Gold Crowns: 12 </p>
<p>You are a Knight of the White Mountain, a warrior lord of Durenor. Two days ago your brother was assassinated at his castle in Ryme. You witnessed the crime and have followed the assassin, a female Adventuress, here to Ragadorn. You hope to capture the assassin alive and take her back to Durenor to face trial, but you suspect that she will not give up without a fight.</p>
<p>Your objective: To arrest the Adventuress. You may only attack her if she offers resistance.</p>

<p>Herbwarden 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 12 
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 20 
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 3 
<br />Weapon: Dagger 
<br />Gold Crowns: 8</p>
<p>You are a young Herbwarden from Bautar, sent to Ragadorn to investigate the disappearance of a fellow Herbwarden called Dalimor. You have discovered that your arch-enemies, the Cener Druids, have established a secret temple in Ragadorn, and that Dalimor was murdered there. You must return to Bautar to report your chilling discovery, but you do not have enough money.</p>
<p>Your objective: To acquire 40 Gold Crowns for your return trip to Bautar by whatever means possible.</p>

<p>Druid 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 12 
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 20 
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 3 
<br />Weapon: Quarterstaff 
<br />Gold Crowns: 6</p>
<p>You are a member of an evil sect of Druids called the Ceners. Your brotherhood has set up a secret temple deep in the heart of Ragadorn, but its location has been discovered by your arch-enemies - the Herbwardens of Bautar. You have already killed one of their spies, but now another has been sent to investigate his disappearance. You have tracked him down to this ale-house.</p>
<p>Your objective: To kill the Herbwarden as quickly as possible.</p>

<p>Adventuress 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 15 
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 24 
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 4 
<br />Weapon: Short Sword 
<br />Gold Crowns: 12</p>
<p>You are a skilled fighter and assassin who has just returned from a successful mission in Durenor. Your contact has just been murdered but before his death he hid the payment for your mission, a large diamond (<span class="caps">LOOT</span> counter), somewhere in this ale-house. You fear someone witnessed the assassination you carried out, and that you have been followed all the way from Durenor.</p>
<p>Your objective: To find the large diamond that is hidden somewhere in the ale-house.</p>

<p>Merchant 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 10
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 24
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 3
<br />Weapon: Dagger
<br />Gold Crowns: 20</p>
<p>You are a wealthy Merchant who owns a trading post down by Ragadorn quay. You love gambling and often frequent this ale-house to play the Gaming Table - some nights you are very lucky! You have made many enemies due to your shady business dealings, and you should remain on your guard at all times.</p>
<p>Your objective: To win 50 Gold Crowns at the Gaming Table, or acquire the money by some other means before the night is out.</p>

<p>Ranger 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 15
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 24
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 4 
<br />Weapon: Axe 
<br />Gold Crowns: 10</p>
<p>You have just returned from a long and successful hunting trip to Durenor. On your arrival you sold some furs to the Merchant for 25 Gold Crowns. You later discovered that he had cheated you and that 15 of them were counterfeit. You have come to the ale-house determined to make him give you the money he owes you.</p>
<p>Your objective: Either to persuade the Merchant to hand over 15 Gold Crowns, or to kill him and take the money.</p>

<p>Landlord
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 16
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 26
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 5 
<br />Weapon: Club 
<br />Gold Crowns: 20</p>

<p>Croupier 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 10
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 21
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 4 
<br />Weapon: Dagger 
<br />Gold Crowns: 3</p>

<p>Serving Girl 1
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 8
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 18
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 4 
<br />Weapon:  
<br />Gold Crowns: 1</p>

<p>Serving Girl 2 
<br /><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 8
<br /><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span>: 18
<br /><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 4 
<br />Weapon:  
<br />Gold Crowns: 1</p>

<p>As landlord of the tavern your objective is to collect 40 Gold Crowns from players using the Gambling Table, and to ensure that none of your staff (the non-player characters) get killed.</p>

<h4>Character Grid</h4>

<ul>

<li>2 Players:
 <dl>
 <dt>Player 1</dt>
 <dd>Lone Wolf
 <br />Mercenary
 <br />Druid
 <br />Merchant
 <br />Adventuress</dd>
 <dt>Player 2</dt>
 <dd>Landlord 
 <br />Magician 
 <br />Knight 
 <br />Herbwarden 
 <br />Ranger</dd>
 </dl>
</li>

<li>3 Players: (Take out Knight)
 <dl>
 <dt>Player 1</dt>
 <dd>Druid
 <br />Magician
 <br />Merchant</dd>
 <dt>Player 2</dt>
 <dd>Herbwarden
 <br />Ranger
 <br />Lone Wolf</dd>
 <dt>Player 3</dt>
 <br />Landlord
 <br />Mercenary
 <br />Adventuress</dd>
 </dl>
</li>

<li>4 Players: (Take out Herbwarden & Druid)
 <dl>
 <dt>Player 1</dt>
 <dd>Magician
 <br />Ranger</dd>
 <dt>Player 2</dt>
 <dd>Merchant
 <br />Knight</dd>
 <dt>Player 3</dt>
 <dd>Adventuress
 <br />Lone Wolf</dd>
 <dt>Player 4</dt>
 <dd>Mercenary
 <br />Landlord</dd>
 </dl>
</li>

<li>5 Players:
 <dl>
 <dt>Player 1</dt>
 <dd>Adventuress
 <br />Ranger</dd>
 <dt>Player 2</dt>
 <dd>Knight
 <br />Druid</dd>
 <dt>Player 3</dt>
 <dd>Merchant
 <br />Mercenary</dd>
 <dt>Player 4</dt>
 <dd>Herbwarden
 <br />Lone Wolf</dd>
 <dt>Player 5</dt>
 <dd>Magician
 <br />Landlord</dd>
 </dl>
</li>

<li>6 Players:
 <dl>
 <dt>Player 1</dt>
 <dd>Lone Wolf</dd>
 <dt>Player 2
 <dd>Landlord</dd>
 <dt>Player 3</dt>
 <dd>Magician
 <br />Ranger</dd>
 <dt>Player 4</dt>
 <dd>Merchant
 <br />Knight</dd>
 <dt>Player 5</dt>
 <dd>Adventuress
 <br />Herbwarden</dd>
 <dt>Player 6</dt>
 <dd>Mercenary
 <br />Druid</dd>
 </dl>
</li>

<li>7 Players: (Take out Knight, Herbwarden and Druid)
 <dl>
 <dt>Players take one character each</dt>
 </dl>
</li>

<li>8 Players: (Take out Herbwarden & Druid)
 <dl>
 <dt>Players take one character each</dt>
 </dl>
</li>

<li>9 Players: (Take out Knight)
 <dl>
 <dt>Players take one character each</dt>
 </dl>
</li>

<li>10 Players:
 <dl>
 <dt>Players take one character each</dt>
 </dl>
</li>
</ul>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</title>

<h2>Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</h2>

<h3>Player Objectives</h3>

<p>Each player must attempt to complete the objective given on each Character Profile Card (see also 'Helghast' and 'Winning the Game')</p>

<h3>Startion Positions</h3>

<p>The game begins with the player to the left of the Landlord.</p>

<ol>
<li>Pick a number from the <a href="random.htm">Random Number Table</a>. To do so, place the table face upwards on a flat surface and hold a pencil directly above it. The pencil should be at least 25 cm above the table. Now, let the pencil fall onto the table. The number it falls on is the number that has been picked. If you pick 0 it counts as zero.</li>
<li>If the number chosen is 0-6, the player can place his Character Counter on any square inside the ale-house, with the exception of any table or behind the bar.</li>
<li>If a 7-9 is chosen, the player must position his Character Counter on any one of the four doors.</li>
</ol>

<h3>Game Rounds</h3>

<p>The game is conducted in rounds, each consisting of four quarters - Movement Quarter, Missile Quarter, Combat Quarter, Gaming Quarter. Play in the first round takes place in a clockwise direction, alternating anti-clockwise and clockwise every subsequent round. Actions are completed by each player in turn before moving on to the next Quarter.</p>

<h4>Movement Quarter</h4>

<ol>
<li>The Landlord moves any or all of the Non-Player Character counters.<li>
<li>Each player takes it in turn to move his Character Counter(s), any number of squares up to the maximum allowed on his Character Profile Card.</li>
<li>If one player moves his character onto a square adjacent to another character, he can choose to fight or talk to that character. If so, the character he intends fight or talk to cannot move his Character Counter in that move.</li>
<li>Characters cannot move diagonally or pass through a square occupied by another character.</li>
</ol>

<h4>Missile Quarter</h4>

<ol>
<li>Any character who possesses, or is adjacent to an item that can be thrown, may now choose to throw that item at another character.</li>
<li>Consult the chart that is printed on the playing board to determine if a thrown missile hits its target, and if it does, how many <span class="caps">ENDURANCE POINTS</span> are lost by the target.</li>
<li>Weapons may be thrown if so desired, but are considered lost until retrieved by the throwing character.</li>
<li>Thrown magical weapons do extra damage to their target if a successful hit is scored. Consult the Combat Results Table in the normal way (see Rules for Combat), ignoring any loss of <span class="caps">ENDUPANCE POINTS</span> sustained by the attacker.</li>
<li>Missiles that miss will land one square in front of the target if the random number picked is an even number, and one square behind if the number is odd.</li>
</ol>

<h4>Combat Quarter</h4>

<ol>
<li>Only character counters that are adjacent to each other at the end of the Missile Quarter can engage in combat. If either character is unarmed, his <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span> is reduced by 4.</li>
<li>Characters can only co-operate with other player's characters once they have elected to 'talk' to each other on the gameboard i.e. the two Player Character Counters are moved adjacent to one another. If a player has elected to talk to another player during the Movement Quarter, he cannot enter into combat with him that round, unless the other player has thrown a missile at him during the Missile Quarter.</li>
</ol>

<p>The sequence for combat is as follows:</p>
<ol>
<li>The player who is launching the attack ('the attacker') compares his <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span> to that of the player he is attacking ('the defender').</li>
<li>The defender's <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span> is subtracted from the attacker's <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>. This result is the Combat Ratio.</li>
<li>The attacker picks a number from the <a href="random.htm">Random Number Table</a>.</li>
<li>Turning the <a href="random.htm">Random Number Table</a> over, the attacker finds the number that is the same as the Combat Ratio on the Combat Results Table. He now cross-references it with the Random Number that he picked and finds the number of <span class="caps">ENDURANCE POINTS</span> lost by both the Attacker and the Defender in this Combat Quarter. ('A' represents points lost by the defender, 'B' represents points lost by the attacker.)</li>
<li>Each player marks the changes in <span class="caps">ENDURANCE POINTS</span> on his Character Profile card.</li>
<li>The loser of the Combat Quarter can now choose to continue the combat next game round, or to evade combat.
<br /><br />If he chooses to continue combat, both character counters stay exactly where they are. Neither player can move during the following Movement Quarter or throw a missile during the Missile Quarter. In the next Combat Quarter, the fight continues but with the defender now becoming the attacker, and vice versa.
<br /><br />If the loser chooses to evade combat, he may add 2 to his movement rate in the following Movement Quarter. He must move away from his attacker in that quarter. The attacker can attempt to give chase if he wishes, but the loser must always be allowed to move first.</li>
<li>Any character whose <span class="caps">ENDURANCE POINTS</span> total falls to zero or below is declared dead. The counter remains on the square where the character is killed and becomes an obstruction to movement.</li>
<li>Any weapons, gold or items can be taken from the body by the victor at the end of the Combat Quarter. The defeated player must hand over the dead character's profile card to the winner of the combat.</li>
<li>Characters fighting from a higher vantage point (on a table, chair or the bar) may add 1 point to their <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span> when fighting an opponent on a floor square.</li>
</ol>

<h4>Gaming Quarter</h4>

<ol>
<li>In the Gaming Quarter of each round, any Player Character Counter that is occupying a square adjacent to the Gaming Table, and who is not involved in combat, may elect to gamble.</li>
<li>No gaming can take place if any player's Character Counter is standing on, or if the Croupier is not adjacent to, the Gaming Table.</li>
</ol>

<p>The procedure for gambling is as follows:</p>
<ol>
<li>The Landlord player mixes the Gaming Counters face down.</li>
<li>Each player in turn calls out a number between 0 and 9 and declares how much they wish to stake (minimum bet 2 Gold Crowns, maximum bet 10).</li>
<li>When all the numbers and stakes have been announced, the Landlord player reveals one of the counters at random.</li>
<li>Any player who has called out the same number as that which is revealed wins four times his stake money. If any player has called out a number that is immediately before or after the one revealed, he wins twice his stake money. All other players lose their stake.</li>
<li>Players may enter or leave the Gaming Table during the Movement Quarter.</li>
</ol>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</title>

<h2>Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</h2>

<h3>Helghast</h3>

<p>Helghast are undead shape-changers who serve the Darklords of Helgedad. One of the characters (to the exclusion of Lone Wolf) is really one of these creatures in disguise. To determine which player character is the Helghast, follow the procedure outlined below:</p>

<table border="0">
<tr><th>No. of Players</th><th>Procedure</th></tr>
<tr><td valign="top">2</td><td>The non-Lone Wolf player chooses one of his four characters to be the Heighast.</td></tr>
<tr><td valign="top">3-6</td><td>Special Item counters are dealt to the Lone Wolf player first. One of the remaining counters is substituted with the Heighast counter prior to being dealt out. The player character dealt the Helghast counter becomes that creature.</td></tr>
<tr><td valign="top">7-10</td><td>Lone Wolf and Landlord receive Special Item counters first, then follow same procedure as per 3-6 player game.</td></tr>
</table>

<p>The objective for the Helghast player is to kill Lone Wolf; this objective takes priority over that shown on the character profile card.</p>

<p>The Helghast player can enter combat without revealing his true identity, and all <span class="caps">ENDURANCE POINTS</span> lost in combat are deducted in the usual way. Should the <span class="caps">ENDURANCE POINT</span> total of his 'disguise' fall to zero, the player must reveal his true identity by placing the Helghast counter onto the playing board (on top of his player character counter).</p>

<p>He may then continue to play using the Helghast <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>, <span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span> and <span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span> totals as shown on the playing board.</p>

<p>The Helghast player can choose to reveal his identity at any stage of the game but, in order to keep everyone guessing, it is recommended that he keep his identity a secret for as long as possible.</p>

<p>When the Helghast appears, it can only be killed by a Magical Weapon (Lone Wolf's Magic Spear, the Magic Sword (Special Item) or the Magic Mace (Special Item) are the only weapons that can reduce the Heighast's <span class="caps">ENDURANCE POINTS</span> during combat). All normal weapons are ineffective against it, and all <span class="caps">ENDURANCE POINTS</span> lost by a Helghast in combat with a player character armed with a normal weapon should be ignored.</p>

<h3>Obstructions to Movement</h3>

<ul>
<li>To climb over a table, reduce movement by 2 squares.</li>
<li>To climb on to or off of a table, reduce movement by 1 square.</li>
<li>To pick up an item, reduce movement by 1 square.</li>
<li>To climb over a dead character, reduce movement by 1 square.</li>
<li>To leave the ale-house by a window, reduce movement by 2 squares.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Leaving the Ale-House</h3>

<p>Players may leave the ale-house by any one of the doors or windows shown on the gameboard. They may re-enter by any one of the doors two game rounds later.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</title>

<h2>Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</h2>

<h3>Special Items</h3>

<p>The Laumspur and Alether Special Items can only be used once during the game. When a player chooses to do so, the counter must be shown and then removed from play. The Magic Wand and the Spell Book can only be used twice during the game.</p>

<h3>Hidden Loot Counters</h3>

<p>Players must remain in a square adjacent to a hidden Loot counter for one game round before they can lay claim to it in the Movement Quarter of the following round. Players cannot search for hidden Loot counters if they are involved in combat.</p>

<h3>Winning the Game</h3>

<h4>2-6 Players</h4>

<p>A complete game lasts for 16 game rounds. At the end of the Gaming Quarter of the 16th round, calculate each player's score as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>For every character's objective achieved +6 points</li>
<li>For every character that survives the game +3 points</li>
<li>For every Special Item you possess +1 point</li>
<li>For every character you have lost -2 points</li>
</ul>

<p>The player with the highest score is declared the winner.</p>

<h4>7-10 Players</h4>

<p>The first player to achieve his objective and leave the ale-house by the double doors is declared the winner.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</title>

<h2>Ragadorn Ale-house Brawl</h2>

<h3>Game Round Summary</h3>

<h4>Movement Quarter:</h4>
<ol>
<li>Landlord moves <span class="caps">NPC</span>'S.</li>
<li>Players move (first round clockwise, then alternating anticlockwise/clockwise).</li>
<li>Characters adjacent can elect to fight or talk.</li>
</ol>

<h4>Missile Quarter:</h4>
<ol>
<li>Items that can be thrown by characters are identified.</li>
<li>Hits/damage are calculated on Missile Chart.</li>
</ol>

<h4>Combat Quarter:</h4>
<ol>
<li>Attacker's <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span> compared to Defender's <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span> to find Combat Ratio.</li>
<li>Attacker picks Random Number.</li>
<li>Endurance points lost by attacker and defender found on the Combat Results Table.</li>
<li>Alter Player Character profile cards.</li>
<li>Loser of combat chooses to continue combat next round, or evade.</li>
</ol>

<h4>Gaming Quarter:</h4>
<p>See 'Gaming Table' for details.</p>

<h3>Missile Chart</h3>

<table border="1" cellspacing="0">
<tr><th rowspan="2">Missile</th><th colspan="4">Target Distance</th><th rowspan="2"><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span> loss</th></tr>
<tr><th>1</th><th>2/4</th><th>5/7</th><th>8+</th></tr>
<tr><th>Dagger</th><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>6</td><td>8</td><td>3</td></tr>
<tr><th>Axe/Other Thrown Weapons</th><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>4</td></tr>
<tr><th>Chair</th><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>M</td><td>M</td><td>2</td></tr>
<tr><th>Bottle</th><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>2</td></tr>
<tr><th>Torch</th><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>3</td></tr>
<tr><th>Food</th><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>9</td><td>M</td><td>1</td></tr>
<tr><th>Bucket</th><td>3</td><td>5</td><td>9</td><td>M</td><td>2</td></tr>
<tr><th>Broom</th><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>M</td><td>M</td><td>1</td></tr>
</table>

<ol>
<li>Determine how far target is from thrower.</li>
<li>Cross-reference missile with target distance on the above chart.</li>
<li>Pick a number from the <a href="random.htm">Random Number Table</a>.</li>
<li>If random number is the same or higher than the chart number, the missile hits the target.</li>
<li>Target loses the number of <span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span> points shown in the <span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span> loss column.</li>
</ol>

<h3>Obstructions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Climb onto/off table -1 square</li>
<li>Climb over body -1 square</li>
<li>Pick up item -1 square</li>
<li>Leave via window -2 squares</li>
</ul>

<h3>Special Items</h3>

<ol>
<li><b>Magic Sword</b> - +4 to <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span></li>
<li><b>Ring of Speed</b> - + 2 to <span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span></li>
<li><b>Elixir of Life</b> - +8 to <span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span> (once only)</li>
<li><b>Magic Mace</b> - +2 to <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span></li>
<li><b>Spell Book</b> - Put any player to sleep for two game turns (twice only)</li>
<li><b>Magic Wand</b> - Stop any player moving for two game turns (twice only)</li>
<li><b>Magic Talisman</b> - + 4 to <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span> when attacked by another player</li>
<li><b>Golden Shield</b> - + 2 to <span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span> when attacked by another player</li>
<li><b>Medallion of Stealth</b> - +2 to <span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span></li>
</ol>

<h3>Helghast Profile</h3>

<ul>
<li><span class="caps">COMBAT SKILL</span>: 20</li>
<li><span class="caps">ENDURANCE</span> points: 30</li>
<li>Gold Crowns: -</li>
<li>Weapon: Sword</li>
<li><span class="caps">MOVEMENT</span>: 5</li>
<li>Objective: Kill Lone Wolf</li>
</ul>

<h3>Gaming Table</h3>

<ol>
<li>Landlord mixes Gambling Counters face down.</li>
<li>Players in turn call out their number and stake money.</li>
<li>Landlord turns over one Gambling Counter at random.</li>
<li>Identical number pays 4 x stake money, Number before or after pays 2 x stake money, All other numbers lose stake.</li>
</ol>

<ul>
<li>Minimum bet - 2 Gold Crowns</li>
<li>Maximum bet - 10 Gold Crowns</li>
</ul>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Realms of Northern Magnamund</title>

<h2>Magnamund Then and Now</h2>

<h3>The Realms of Northern Magnamund</h3>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<h4>The Birth of Magnamund</h4>

<p>In the silent darkness before the creation of Magnamund, a titanic struggle raged between the formless, shapeless Lords of Good and Evil. Ageless and unceasing was their conflict until the Peace of Ishir heralded an uneasy truce between the powers of life and death. Goddess Ishir, High Priestess of the Moon, sealed a promise with Naar, the King of the Darkness, by which their endless war might cease. A great vessel was shaped from the truth of her pledge into which Naar infused the essence of his terrible power. Their creation became Aon, the 'Great Balance', and from this seed grew a universe filled with light and dark, life and death, hope and despair. The Lords of Good and Evil looked down upon Aon in wonder, and so greatly did they desire to enter and control their creation that the Peace of Ishir was ended and their struggle was born anew.</p>

<p>The many jewels of Aon shone brightly in the darkness and swiftly were they claimed by the gods. As one world fell to Evil, another was saved by Good, until just one, the brightest jewel of all, remained unclaimed and unconquered. The great powers marshalled their forces in preparation for the final momentous battle that would decide the fate of Aon, for control over the last world would tip the balance in favour of the victor and banish the defeated to the void from whence they came. And so it was that Magnamund, the last free world of Aon, became a battleground of the gods - the keystone of power in the war between Good and Evil.</p>

<p>The forces of the noble God Kai, Lord of the Sun, were the first to enter the primeval world of Magnamund, and in doing so they became mortal creatures. They chose to dwell in the depths of the oceans where they took the shape of sea dragons of massive size and power. Kai spoke to Nyxator, a dragon of immense wisdom, and warned him of the birth of evil among his brethren.</p>

<p>So Nyxator led the true dragons onto the land and created the realm of Cynx, to avoid the evil spawn of Naar that were hatching in the depths of the sea. In his wisdom, Nyxator created the Lorestones in order to preserve the power bestowed upon him by the great God Kai. The dragons of Naar emerged from the sea and waged war on Cynx, destroying it with a rain of fire that lasted many centuries. Nyxator escaped and rallied his brothers to fight again, but they were defeated and Nyxator was forced to take refuge at the molten core of Magnamund. The sea dragons burned and savaged the land, laying all to waste in an orgy of triumphant destruction. But in doing so they sealed their doom for they were now mortal creatures.</p>

<p>Following their extinction, the King of the Darkness sought to destroy Nyxator by other means. He caused the land to seethe and boil - to erupt, twist, and tear. For two thousand years Magnamund was tortured, but it refused to yield its hidden refugee. In desperation Naar sent forth his most powerful servant - Agarash the Damned. In 6700 <span class="caps">MS</span>, he arose and conquered Southern Magnamund, creating the Doomstones in mockery of the Lorestones of Nyxator. In the depths of his fortress of Naaros, he used them to breed a legion of dreadful forms - the Agarashi - the Creatures of Darkness. They were let loose upon the land and nowhere was safe from their insatiable hunger. The power of Agarash grew unchecked; he forged great weapons of power and raised the dead to do his bidding. He hunted and slew the aged Nyxator in a fiery duel at the core of the earth, and captured the Lorestones. For the gods Ishir and Kai, it was the nadir of their struggle, but in their desperation they conceived a new power to save their cause - the power of magic.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Realms of Southern Magnamund</title>

<h2>Magnamund Then and Now</h2>

<h3>The Realms of Southern Magnamund</h3>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[Illustration]</tt></p>

<h4>Man, Magic and the Moonstone</h4>

<p>In the year 4570 <span class="caps">MS</span>, the gods Ishir and Kai sent forth the magical Elder Magi to challenge the mighty Agarash, servant of Darkness. They undertook a daring assault upon his fortress at Naaros and seized the stolen Lorestones of Nyxator whilst he slept, entranced by their spells. Enraged to a terrible fury, Agarash unleashed his Creatures of Darkness in a great war with the Elder Magi that lasted over one thousand years. But the magicians used their skill to turn his creatures against themselves and, in so doing, brought about the downfall of his great empire.</p>

<p>With the ruin of the Agarashi Empire, the pendulum of fate swung in a favourable arc towards the powers of Good. The Age of the Old Kingdoms welcomed the arrival of new civilizations and new hope for a world scarred by war, but it also saw the emergence of a sinister force. The Cenerese, a race of treacherous Druids, appeared in Central Magnamund shortly before the Great Plague swept slowly and systematically across the world, leaving the Elder Magi and Drodarin peoples decimated in its wake. Their power spread until the arrival of the Herbalish, a holy order devoted to the healing arts, defeated them in a long and bitter war.</p>

<p>In the year 1600 <span class="caps">MS</span>, an accident took place that was to alter the balance and course of history. A race of lesser gods called the Shianti appeared through a 'Shadow Gate' - a door between the material world of Magnarnund and the astral world of Daziarn. As centuries passed, they grew ambitious and sought to increase their knowledge of their new home and discover the secrets of the Daziarn. Their culture spread to the north and east where they were known by several names (Majhan, Suukon, Ancients). Their quest for knowledge was successful and culminated in the creation of the Moonstone, a gem of power formed in the astral Daziarn, that became the focus of their wisdom, their magic and their very existence. It saw the dawn of their Golden Age, an era that brought health and plenty to all creatures of Magnamund. Many humans arrived during this age; the Mythenish and Tianese in the south, the Vassa in the east, the Vaderish, Nael and Aluvians in the west, and the Ice Barbarians and Ulnarians in the north. But the presence of the Shianti, and especially their Moonstone, on Magnamund, disturbed the balance of the conflict between the Lords of Good and Evil.</p>

<p>Ishir appeared to the Shianti and persuaded them to relinquish their Moonstone and exile themselves to the remote Isle of Lorn. The Moonstone was returned to the Daziarn and the Shianti abandoned their cities and began their great exodus. In the years prior to their exile, a new and evil force had arrived in the west, a barbaric horde of warriors called Drakkarim. Their name struck terror in the hearts of men, but they were merely a prelude to a far greater nightmare. Naar, the King of the Darkness, had laboured unceasingly to create new champions of evil, and now his task was complete. In the year <span class="caps">MS</span> 3072, the Darklords appeared and began a terrible war of desecration. The Drakkarim nations, in fear and awe of Darklord power, allied themselves to this new force and constructed huge city-fortresses to dominate the lands that they helped to conquer. Never, since the rise of Agarash the Damned, had Magnamund faced such overwhelming evil. Ishir and Kai, woefully ill-prepared for the speed with which Naar's champions were conquering Magnamund, sent forth a race of men called Sommlending and armed them with wisdom and a great power called the Sommerswerd: the sword of the sun. Their defiant bravery is all that now stands in the path of Darklord domination.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Aran Rolny - Young Scribe</title>

<h2>Sommerlund</h2>

<h3>Aran Rolny - Young Scribe</h3>

<p>My name is Aran Rolny, and I count myself the luckiest boy in all Sommerlund. When I was young, my father sent me to the household of Baron Calder of Anskaven, to learn to read and write and wield a sword. Well, I must confess that I was the clumsiest boy in the castle, and I now remember with dread the days spent in the keep practising with sword and shield. The other boys would always tease me when it was my turn to fight. 'Stumbletoes Rolny,' they used to shout, 'you'll never be a knight!' No matter how hard I tried I always managed to drop my sword, or trip over my shield, or both. Then one day, the most humbling of my life, I knocked myself unconscious with the hilt of my sword. When I awoke, the castle keep was echoing to the laughter of my classmates. They rolled around on the dusty ground, tears streaming down their faces as they laughed themselves hoarse at my misfortune. It was awful. The news reached the Baron and he ordered that I be excused my sword duties for fear I would injure myself further. He set me to work in the castle library, where I was placed under the supervision of the Chief Scribe. I learnt to scrape and polish parchment, to cut a quill and prepare the ink for my master. I was his best student and the only boy allowed to write upon his parchments. I loved to sit in his high-backed chair, with its high arms and footstool, with the sunlight streaming down upon a polished parchment laid out before my ink and pen.</p>

<p>It was early winter when my master told me the most joyous news. My work had come to the attention of Baron Medar of Tyso, the Chancellor of the Realm. So impressed was he by the neatness of my script, that he had requested I be sent into his service at the Chancery of the Privy Seal and, to my delight, my master agreed. A special messenger arrived at the castle to collect me, and in his charge he had a chest of solid oak. My heart skipped a beat as I opened the lid, for it contained the wardrobe of a Chancery scribe: a robe of blue silk, breeches of velvet and the finest pair of buckled brown shoes that I had ever seen. The robe was trimmed with lamb's fur and upon the sleeve was the embroidered seal of Baron Medar and my name in golden thread below it.</p>

<p>That evening in the Great Hall, after food and prayers, the Baron himself announced to the assembled household the news of my appointment. The voices that once teased and cajoled me were now filled with praise for my achievement. It was the happiest, proudest moment of my life.</p>

<p>A year has passed since I left Anskaven castle and my world has changed in many ways. My days are now filled with the drafting of royal letters, the issue of summons and papers of state. I have my own horse, a small staff of messengers and the friendship of the King's court. Yet I often recall the day I stumbled with my sword and reflect upon it, not with shame, but with a smile.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Skyrider</title>

<h2>Modelling Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Skyrider</h3>

<p>This is the flying ship, Skyrider, which provides the setting for a fierce aerial battle between Lone Wolf and a pack of Drakkarim mounted on Kraan in Shadow on the Sand. Standing on the prow is Banedon, the vessel's captain, Journeymaster to the Guild of the Crystal Star. The crew, dwarves from the mountain kingdom of Bor, are below. Just as Skyrider was once a conventional water-borne craft so the model opposite started life as a model ship in kit form. Only the hull and deck were actually used in the model overleaf; everything else was built from scraps of card, balsa wood and other bits. Overleaf is a diagram of the Skyrider and instructions for building it. If you can't find exactly the same materials, don't worry. Use what you do have to create a unique flying ship.</p>

<p>The diagram below shows a profile of the Skyrider with some notes explaining what each part of the vessel is made from. The most important part is the hull. If you feel that buying a brand new kit just for the hull is extravagant, you could make your own from card. A modified version of a death-hulk's hull with deeper sides and a flat bottom would look very good.</p>

<p>If you are using a hull from a plastic kit, you should glue it together using polystyrene cement. Everything else on the model can be glued into place using a contact adhesive, but small metal items are best cemented together with Superglue. (<span class="caps">NB</span> Be careful not to get glue on your fingers.) Once the hull is complete, you can build cabins and deckhouses from card and glue them one on top of each other. Alternatively, cabins and cockpits can be raised up on staging and the space underneath used for deck storage. The model in the photograph has a central cabin built straight onto the deck with a bridge above it, a forward observation cockpit and a small house-shaped cabin at the rear all built up on staging made from balsa strip.</p>

<p>The Skyrider's mast was part of another old ship kit but could be made from the thin dowel available in model shops, as were the ribs stiffening the bat-like sails. The outriggers are built from balsa strip. Ready-made accessories from model shops have been used for deck cargo, treasure chests, shields, rolled-up tarpaulins, crates and sacks. Try model railways shops for useful boxes and bags, or you can make your own from balsa wood and modelling clay. Standing in the cockpit at the prow, Banedon is one of Citadel Miniature's Lone Wolf figures. Unless you want a static display, don't glue the figures down - characters in role-playing games move around a lot. The Skyrider's rigging is made from thin wire. You can use fuse wire but florist's wire is best. On completion, the ship was painted with modelling enamels.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Sommerlund</title>

<h2>Sommerlund</h2>

<h3>The Royal Estates, Fryelund and Baronial Provinces</h3>

<p>Of all the lands of Northern Magnamund, one only has defied the awesome might of the Darklands. Sommerlund - 'the land of the sun' - is now poised to fight a war which will decide the fate of the whole continent. The resolve of her people and the bravery of her warriors is seen as a shining example, a beacon of hope to all who fear the terror that follows Darklord domination. Only through Sommerlund's continued vigilance and stolid determination to survive will the future of the Lastlands be secured.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<h4>The Royal Estates of King Ulnar V</h4>
<p>The Royal Estates encompass the capital of Holmgard, and much of the richly forested vale of Central Sommerlund. Stewardship of the estate rests with the Marshal of the Realm, Crown Prince Pelathar, the King's only son. In addition, all highways, bridges and forests fall within this royal fiefdom.

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<h4>The Baronial Confederation of Toran</h4>
<p>Although it is recognized as a baronial province, Toran is a confederation of guilds that dominate the social, political and economic life of the city. All positions of high rank are held by guildsmen, the most influential under the control of the magician's guild - the Brotherhood of the Crystal Star.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<h4>The Baronial Province of Ruanon</h4>
<p>Located far to the south, Ruanon is a remote province under the control of Baron Oren Vanalund. The gold and precious gems that are mined from the Maaken Range yield an important source of revenue for Sommerlund.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<h4>The County of Tyso</h4>
<p>Control of this small but wealthy coastal region rests with the Seneschal of Tyso: Baron Tor Medar. In addition to his county duties, the Baron holds the office of Chancellor of the Realm, and is one of the King's most trusted advisors.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<h4>The Baronial Province of Anskavern</h4>
<p>This northern agricultural province is controlled by Baron Avan Caldar, Steward of the Royal Court and Commander of the Royal Fleet. The city of Anskavern has long had a naval tradition, with its fishing fleet being the largest in all the Lastlands.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<h4>The Fryelund of the Kai</h4>
<p>The lands contained by the River Tor in the north, and the River Unoram to the south, traditionally have belonged to the warrior lords of the Kai; although it was not until after their massacre that the province was declared 'fryelund', and given into the command and protection of Lone Wolf, the last of the Kai.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<h4>The Southlund Marches</h4>
<p>This vast province to the south of Holmgard, falls under the jurisdiction of Baron Vea Galt. It is an honorary title, for the Southlund Marches are a rolling expanse of plains, farmed by fryemen of the realm who are outside the feudal order of Northern Sornmerlund. The 'keeping of the King's peace' is enforced by the Border Rangers, who in turn answer to Baron Galt in Holmgard. The Baron is also Keeper of the Privy Seal.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<h4>The Kirlundin Isles</h4>
<p>There are six islands in the Kirlundin chain, and collectively they fall under the baronial fiefdom of Knight-commander Baleon Medar, brother of Tor, the Baron of Tyso. The inhabitants of these rocky isles are famed seafarers, their ships protecting the coastline from Anskavern to Holmgard.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Saga of Sommerlund</title>

<h2>Sommerlund</h2>

<h3>The Saga of Sommerlund</h3>

<p>In the year <span class="caps">MS</span> 3434, a host of fair-haired warriors led by a fierce and lordly king called Kian, came to the Lastlands in ships of yellowed oak. They had sailed across the northern void, through storm and ice, to turn back a tide of great evil that threatened to consume all. For three centuries the Darklords had conquered the lands of Northern Magnamund, destroying everything in their path. But the arrival of the Sommlending reversed their victories in the east and drove them back beyond the Durncrag mountains, into the wastelands that they themselves had created.</p>

<p>And so it was that the kingdom of Sommerlund was born in a land of fertile beauty, saved from destruction at the hands of Lord Vashna and his champions of evil. King Kian's victory was but the first battle in a long and vindictive war to be waged over the coming centuries. Vashna had sworn to destroy Sommerlund and in the depths of his stronghold, within the black city of Helgedad, he schemed and plotted the downfall of the sun-realm. In the face of this constant threat, King Kian ordered the construction of four great cities: Holmgard, Toran, Anskaven and Tyso, and a number of smaller fortifications to guard the mountain passes through the Durncrag Range. Command of these cities, forts and surrounding lands was given into the charge of the Barons of Sommerlund, high-ranking warrior lords who had achieved great honour and distinction during the war against Vashna. The barons ruled over the Sommlending who lived and worked their lands, and they in turn were bound to serve the king, supplying him with soldiers to protect the realm. Although King Kian had decreed that 'every Sommlending must have a lord', most men, except the poorest, considered themselves free. Many skilled craftsmen, especially in the cities, banded together to form guilds, and officials, such as the Mayor and Lord-Justice of the City Court, were often elected from their ranks. Rich merchants or wealthy farmers were sometimes declared 'Fryemen of the Realm', a rank which freed them from service to a Baron. For acts of great honour or bravery, too, the King could award the title 'Fryearl of Sommerlund', a rare and greatly coveted title that raised a man to the level of a Baron in wealth and standing.</p>

<p>With the threat of war so constant, every child (girl and boy) was trained in the use of weapons from an early age. This training was organized by the barons and took place in the grounds of their castles. Any child who displayed a natural instinct for combat was placed into the household of a Knight of the Realm, where they were groomed for the Sommlending army. Similarly, the magician's guild, the Brotherhood of the Crystal Star, recruited children into their ranks at an early age. Those who showed exceptional intelligence or a natural ability to grasp the secrets of their craft were raised and educated into the ways of magic at their guildhall in Toran.</p>

<p>Following the defeat of Lord Vashna at the Great Battle of Maakengorge, the Baron of Toran, a noble warrior who had distinguished himself during that battle, began a quest for the ancient Lorestones of Nyxator in order to acquire their wisdom. His quest was successful and in the year <span class="caps">MS</span> 3810, he took the name 'Sun Eagle' and established the Order of the Kai Lords, an elite warrior caste whose study of martial disciplines was to ensure the future security of Sommerlund. But in spite of that victory at Maakengorge, and the birth of the Kai Lords, the kingdom of Sommerlund was often attacked in the coming centuries. Only the strength of its people, and its alliance with the free kingdom of Durenor proved steadfast and unshakable in these years of conflict.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Warriors of Sommerlund</title>

<h2>Sommerlund</h2>

<h3>The Warriors of Sommerlund</h3>

<p>The people of Sommerlund have always lived in the shadow of war, and the threat of Darklord invasion has demanded that they remain constantly prepared for battle. For centuries, they have grown strong in the face of this intimidation, and their army, although small, is the best equipped, trained and motivated force in all of Magnamund.</p>

<p>Supreme commander of this force is the King, to whom all Sommlending swear an oath of loyalty upon reaching their seventh birthday. It is called the 'Oath of Fehmarn', and it is celebrated and renewed once a year, on the first day of spring, to remind all Sommlending that their highest duty is to protect their country by serving their King in time of need. A standing army, composed of the Royal Guard and Border Rangers, is maintained at all times, and new recruits for these regular units are trained and supplied by the Barons and Knights of the Realm. In war time, the Barons call upon each knight in their province to supply a troop of 200 soldiers, known as a 'charge'. Several charges combine under the command of a baron to form a 'cassel', and three to five cassels comprise an army. Additional troops are supplied by the city guilds in the form of Townsmen Regiments, led by Guildmarshals, and militia whose role it is to defend the city walls and protect the civilians.</p>

<p>The Brotherhood of the Crystal Star are called upon to provide sorcerers gifted in battle magic. They are attached to a cassel where they aid and advise the commander. Prior to their massacre, the Kai Lords formed a cassel of mounted and unmounted warriors, and Kai Masters were placed in command of Sommlending armies.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<p>Baron Tor Medar - Seneschal of Tyso
<br />Baron Medar is Chief Advisor to the King. In his possession is the Great Seal of Sommerlund, under which are issued all the important royal proclamations. His wealthy county has 2400 well-trained retainers.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<p>Kirlundin Naval Marine
<br />The ships that guard and patrol the coast carry a retinue of marines to search suspicious vessels. They are often involved in ship-to-ship combat with rogue traders from Ragadorn, and pirate raiders.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<p>Ruanese Man-at-Arms
<br />The miners who work the gold-rich Maaken Range are frequently attacked by hostile bandits and ferocious Giaks. The Baron maintains a charge of Men-at-Arms to defend them.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<p>Toranese Archer City Guilds Regiment
<br />Comprised of apprentices to the guilds of Toran, this regiment is regarded with fear by Sommerlund's enemies. They carry a range of special arrow-heads and their accuracy is unmatched.</p>

<p class="illustration"><tt>[illustration]</tt></p>
<p>Sommlending Knight of the Realm
<br />This noble knight owns a castle and lands in Anskaven. His household trains young warriors for battle, and he personally commands a charge of his own landed retainers (200+ men) in times of war. He is an expert horseman and a master of battle lore. His war horse responds instantly to the commands of the rider. Its ferocity in combat is matched only by its indefatigable stamina.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Jac Taynor - Farmer's Son</title>

<h2>Sommerlund</h2>

<h3>Jac Taynor - Farmer's Son</h3>

<p>My name is Jac Taynor and I live in the village of Stonefurrow with my mother, my father and my brother Lon. Stonefurrow consists of the village hall and thirty-one cottages, mostly built on either side of the highway leading to Tyso. There is a blacksmithy, an alehouse, a water mill, and beyond the cottages there are five great fields in which we grow our crops. No one, except Reeve Ladnor, has ever travelled further than thirty miles away, though my younger brother and I have often been to the market at Tyso, which is ten miles to the north. All the land of Stonefurrow belongs to the lord of the manor, Knight Evald of Worlan. Since he cannot work the land himself, it is shared among the villagers and in return they pay him their taxes. My family moved here from the neighbouring village of Boonwold when I was very young. Our old cottage blew down in a storm, and my father was given permission to build a new one near Stonefurrow stream. He's a farmer and I help him work in our fields behind the cottages. We're lucky because we own four oxen and a plough. My father steers the plough and I rake the broken earth with my harrow before planting our wheat seed. Come the spring, the ploughing starts again, but this time I sow barley instead. It's hard work but I enjoy it, especially at harvest time when Knight Evald comes to the village hall and gives a feast. There are minstrels, dancing and all kinds of entertainments, but none have been as good as last year's Harvestfest; it was then I learnt all about magic.</p>

<p>It was a hot and sunny day. Since early morning there had been sports such as wrestling, archery tournaments and casting the stone and, as the sun began to set, the festival moved into the village hall. My brother and I had found a hiding place up in the rafters where we could watch everybody dancing and singing without them seeing us, and I had my fishing line which I used to hook cakes from the table below. An hour after sunset, the Knight's heralds sounded a fanfare on their shiny brass trumpets and the floor was cleared. A magician, all the way from the city of Casiorn, came in and stood on the table directly below where my brother and I were hiding, and called for everyone's attention. I'd seen the street-magicians of Tyso before, but they were not as impressive as this brown-skinned man with his hat and cape of silk. He said he was 'Zalatar the Magnificent', and with a wave of his hand there was a flash and bang and suddenly he was sitting astride a little white donkey. Everyone began cheering and clapping as he rode around the hall, and they threw half-crowns into his silk hat which he held at arm's length. My brother and I tried not to laugh, for high in the roof we could see that Zalatar had hidden his donkey under the tablecloth. The flash must have blinded the villagers, for they seemed not to notice the magician pulling him out. But we had seen how his magic was worked. I thought it was all good fun until I suddenly noticed how much gold he was taking from the villagers: his tricks were stealing all they had earned from the harvest. It was then that I decided to try some magic of my own.</p>

<p>As the performance came to an end, he returned to the table below to gather his belongings together. In his haste he didn't notice the fishing line hooking his pouch of ill-gotten gold. I gave a swift tug and the pouch flew up in the air and landed in my lap. You should have seen his face as he reached the door and discovered that the money had disappeared! My brother and I jumped down from the rafters to tell Knight Evald what we had seen. He praised our honesty, and as the heralds returned the gold to the startled villagers, he warned them in future to take greater care of their money.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Magnamund Then and Now</title>

<h2>Magnamund Then and Now</h2>
<h3>The Ages of Magnamund</h3>

<p>All time is reckoned by the date on which the Moonstone (<span class="caps">MS</span>) was created by the Shianti. The years before its creation are dnoted by the date first, e.g. 4906 <span class="caps">MS</span>. The years after its creation by the date after, e.g. <span class="caps">MS</span> 3799. All historical information in this book is relevant to the year <span class="caps">MS</span> 5050.</p>

<h4>Chronological Tables of Events</h4>

<dl>
<dt>Age of the Dragons (13000 - 10148 <span class="caps">MS</span>)</dt>
<dd>
 <ul>
 <li>(12750) Dragons emerge from the oceans</li>
 <li>(12209) Nyxator creates the Lorestones</li>
 <li>(11890) The War of the Wyrms</li>
 <li>(10869) Cynx destroyed</li>
 <li>(10148) Nyxator exiled to the core of Magnamund</li>
 </ul>
</dd>
<dt>Age of Entropy (10148 - 9000 <span class="caps">MS</span>)</dt>
<dt>Age of Chaos (9000 - 6750 <span class="caps">MS</span>)</dt>
<dd>
 <ul>
 <li>(8560) Tentarias splits Magnamund</li>
 <li>(8011 - 6750) Volcanic activity re-shapes most of North/South Magnamund</li>
 </ul>
</dd>
<dt>Age of Eternal Night (6750 - 4608 <span class="caps">MS</span>)</dt>
<dd>
 <ul>
 <li>(6700) Agarash the Damned rises in Magnamund</li>
 <li>(4906) The Great Dragon Nyxator is slain by Agarash - Lorestones Captured</li>
 </ul>
</dd>
<dt>Age of War (4608 - 3572 <span class="caps">MS</span>)</dt>
<dd>
 <ul>
 <li>(4608) Elder Magi appear (central Magnamund)</li>
 <li>(3572) Defeat of Agarash &amp; destruction of Naaros</li>
 </ul>
</dd>
<dt>Age of Old Kingdoms (4608 - 1600 <span class="caps">MS</span>)</dt>
<dd>
 <ul>
 <li>(2514) Great Plague Decimates Drodarin &amp; Elder Magi</li>
 </ul>
</dd>
<dt>Age of Awakening (1600 <span class="caps">MS</span> - 0)</dt>
<dd>
 <ul>
 <li>(1600) Shianti appear</li>
 </ul>
</dd>
<dt>Golden Age of the Shianti (0 - <span class="caps">MS</span> 3004)</dt>
<dd>
 <ul>
 <li>(0) Moonstone created by the Shianti</li>
 <li>(2591) Drakkarim invade North Magnamund</li>
 <li>(3004) Ishir appears to the Shianti - Moonstone returned to the Daziarn plane - Exodus begins</li>
 </ul>
</dd>
<dt>Age of the Black Moon (<span class="caps">MS</span> 3004 - 3799)</dt>
<dd>
 <ul>
 <li>(3072) Darklords appear in Magnamund - Giaks bred</li>
 <li>(3150) Drakkarim nations ally to the Darklords</li>
 <li>(3192) Rise of Vashna</li>
 <li>(3400) Doomwolves, Kraan &amp; Zlanbeast bred in Helgedad</li>
 <li>(3434) Sommlending arrive in North Magnamund - Darklords pushed back beyond Durncrag Mountains</li>
 <li>(3450) Holmgard built</li>
 <li>(3520-50) Helghast Wars</li>
 <li>(3785) Vashna begins the Black Muster in preparation for war with Sommerlund</li>
 </ul>
</dd>
<dt>Age of the Sun-Star (<span class="caps">MS</span> 3799 - )</dt>
<dd>
 <ul>
 <li>(3799) Battle of Moytura Pass - Defeat of Darklord Vashna at Great Battle of Maakengorge - Death of Ulnar I</li>
 <li>(3810) Kai Monastery established</li>
 <li>(3952) Ljuk built</li>
 <li>(4219) Siege of Kai Monastery</li>
 <li>(4401 - 18) War of the Lorestone (Stornlands)</li>
 <li>(4434) Book of the Magnakai lost</li>
 <li>(4551) Rise of Vassagonian Empire</li>
 <li>(4702) Great Khordaim War</li>
 <li>(4771) Death of the Black Zakhan</li>
 <li>(5050) Invasion of Sommerlund - Massacre of the Kai - Defeat of Darklord Zagarna - Grey Star leaves Isle of Lorn</li>
 </ul>
</dd>
</dl>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: Title Page</title>

<h1>The Magnamund Companion</h1>
<h2>The Complete Guide to the World of <br>Lone Wolf &amp; Grey Star</h2>

<p class="title">Joe Dever and Gary Chalk</p>

<p>Internet Edition published by <a href="http://www.bigfoot.com/~TheAonProject/">The Aon Project</a>. Because of the graphical nature of the original publication, we've made many adaptations. Where we have made corrections, they will be noted in the <a href="errata.htm">Errata</a>.</p>

<p>Publishing Date:</p>

<p>Copyright &#169; 1986 Joe Dever. Distribution of this Internet Edition is restricted under the terms of the <a href="license.htm">Aon Project End User License</a>.</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Vaderish/Aluvian Nations</title>

<h2>The Nations of Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Vaderish/Aluvian Nations</h3>

<h4>The Kingdom of Lencia</h4>

<p>Ruler: King Sarnac <span class="caps">III</span> 
<br />Capital: Heimstorm 
<br />Population:  92,000 + 
<br />Resources: Copper, silver, tin, agriculture, fish, shipbuilding
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<p>This rich and fertile land was the first to be settled by the Vaderish peoples in <span class="caps">MS</span> 1007. Migration continued rapidly into other provinces, but the elder Vaderish settled in Lencia and built many ports, including the great city port of Helmstorm. They prospered from their command of the western Tentarias until the arrival of the Drakkarim in <span class="caps">MS</span> 2591. Nyras, formerly Northern Lencia, was lost to them during the Darkdawn War (<span class="caps">MS</span> 2606-10) and, in spite of many Lencian crusades, it has remained under their control ever since.</p>

<h4>The Kingdom of Magador</h4>

<p>Ruler: King Vanagrom <span class="caps">VI</span> 
<br />Capital: Helgor 
<br />Population: 82,000 + 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, copper, bronin, gold, silver, furs
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>
<p>The peoples who settled in this territory at the source of the River Storn were mixed groups of Vaderish and Aluvian origin. The ore-rich mountains of its northern provinces were extensively mined, and brought great wealth to its people. However, the treasures of Magador soon attracted outlaw bands and robber barons who fought for possession of the land. In <span class="caps">MS</span> 3657, the royal household was murdered, and the pretender Prince Dolgorn acceded to the throne. It is rumoured that the present ruler, King Vanagrom <span class="caps">VI</span>, is a puppet of the Darklords.</p>

<h4>The Kingdom of Lyris</h4>

<p>Ruler: King Konral <span class="caps">XI</span> 
<br />Capital: Varetta 
<br />Population: 40,000 + 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, iron ore, mercenaries 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

<p>With the founding of the city state of Varetta (<span class="caps">MS</span> 1270), reputedly upon the site of the ancient realm of Cynx, the migration of the Vaderish peoples slowed to a halt and gradually the precincts of the city expanded to encompass the lands bordering the River Storn. During the War of the Lorestone, the power of the King was usurped by his sons, each claiming an equal right to his throne. Their greed led to civil war and conflicts with neighbouring states eager to exploit this disunity. The current ruler has little control over the warmongering princes of Lyris.</p>

<h4>The Freelands of Talestria</h4>

<p>Ruler: Queen Evaine 
<br />Capital: Garthen 
<br />Population: 53,000 + 
<br />Resources: Timber, fish, agriculture 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<p>The river valleys of Talestria were wrested from the Agarashi during the Wars of Restitution (<span class="caps">MS</span> 1660). Under the banner of King Varnos <span class="caps">II</span>, the Talestrians pushed the creatures of darkness back into the stagnant swamps of the Danarg and built border forts to defend their new realm. Strong alliances with Bor and Palmyrion ensured peace, but with the coming of the Drakkarim this peace was shattered. Persistent raids and incursions from Ogia have decimated the once-fertile northland, and the Talestrians are now hard pressed to defend their homeland from the Ogian aggressors.</p>

<h4>The Protectorate of Cincoria</h4>

<p>Ruler: Margrave Vactor <span class="caps">XXIV</span> 
<br />Capital: Quilla 
<br />Population: 68,000 
<br />Resources: Timber, agriculture, shipbuilding, silver 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Kingdom of Delden</h4>

<p>Ruler: King Naumon <span class="caps">III</span> 
<br />Capital: Luyen 
<br />Population: 65,000 + 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, timber, shipbuilding, ore 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

<h4>The Unified Principalites of Eldenora</h4>

<p>Ruler: Prince Cillan of Tyssek 
<br />Capital: Duadon 
<br />Population: 137,000 + 
<br />Resources: Timber, agriculture, silver, shipbuilding 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

<h4>The Principality of Eru</h4>
<p>Ruler: Prince Graygor 
<br />Capital: Humbold 
<br />Population: 13,000 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, copper, tin, gold, gems 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Dukedom of Malia</h4>
<p>Ruler: Duke Isak, Freelordain of Halia 
<br />Capital: Saidor 
<br />Population: 12,000 
<br />Resources: Timber, tin, copper 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Leaguelands of Ilion</h4>
<p>Ruler: League of the Sword (council of Elder Knights) 
<br />Capital: Feravan 
<br />Population: 55,000 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, shipbuilding, copper, horses 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Grand Duchy of Kasland</h4>
<p>Ruler: Archduke Chalamis 
<br />Capital: Casala 
<br />Population: 180,000 + 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, timber, fish, shipbuilding, copper 
<br />Currency: Orla (2 Orla = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Great Union of Lunarlia</h4>
<p>Ruler: King Aluvaria <span class="caps">XV</span> 
<br />Capital: Avalar 
<br />Population: 300,000 + 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, iron ore, timber, shipbuilding, copper, gems, bronin 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Republic of Palmyrion</h4>
<p>Ruler: Elector Manatine of Vanamor 
<br />Capital: Vanamor 
<br />Population: 156,000 + 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, timber, fish, shipbuilding 
<br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<title>The Magnamund Companion: The Vassa Nations</title>

<h2>The Nations of Magnamund</h2>

<h3>The Vassa Nations</h3>

<h4>The Empire of Vassagonia</h4>
<p>Ruler: Zakhan Moudalla 
<br />Capital: Barrakeesh 
<br />Population: 1,000,000 + 
<br />Resources: Gold, gems, rare minerals, spices, agriculture, silver, platinum, copper, bronin, iron ore, fish, shipbuilding 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown 
<p>This rich and powerful empire owes its wealth and status to the ruthless imperialism of the Black Zakhan, a former ruler, of Vassagonia. Under his iron rule, the nomadic Vassa tribes of the Dry Main united and waged war on their weaker neighbours, capturing much land and many resources in the north and west. The current ruler is old and has no heir to claim his throne - one of the richest thrones in all of Magnamund.</p>

<h4>The Empire of Shadaki</h4>
<p>Ruler: Shasarak the Wytch-king 
<br />Capital: Shadaki 
<br />Population: 850,000 + 
<br />Resources: Fishery, agriculture shipbuilding, timber, iron ore, gold, copper, bronin, silver, rare gems, horses, spices 
<br />Currency: Noble (1 Noble = 1 Gold Crown) 
<p>Formerly a collection of remote city states which were defeated and subsequently ruled over by the invading nomads of the Sadi desert, this nation rose to power under the rulership of Shasarak the Wytch-king. Its capital was built to celebrate the unification of the Vassa and Sadi peoples, and to mark the fall of Jazer, the original province of Shadaki. Shasarak dedicated himself to the expansion of the realm building a mighty iron-clad fleet in preparation for the War of the Winds. Victory in this war brought the downfall of the neighbouring states and their occupation by Shadakine armies. Elated by victory, the Shadakine empire chose to declare war on their distant relatives - the Vassagonians of Northern Magnamund. A massive invasion ended in disaster for the Shadaki at the Battle of the Tentarium, in which both the fleet and the army were devastated. This disastrous war paved the way for rebellion among its subjugated neighbours, and led to the uprising of Karnali.</p>

<h4>The Wildlands</h4>
<p>Ruler: Overlord Lachlan 
<br />Capital: Ragadorn 
<br />Population: 20,000 
<br />Resources: Fish, shipbuilding
<br />Currency: Gold Crown 
<p>Formerly Northern Cloeasia, this region was laid waste during the formation of the Maakengorge and the geological upheaval that followed. The city state of Ragadorn, by virtue of its coastal-location was the only major city to survive. It attracted a motley crowd of bandits and fugitives from justice who, by fair means and foul, took control of the city's administration. In spite of its sordid past, Ragadorn has become a major free trade port of Northern Magnamund.</p>

<h4>The Free State of Casiorn</h4>
<p>Ruler: High-Mayor Kordas 
<br />Capital: Casiorn 
<br />Population: 30,000 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, commerce 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown 
<p>Casiorn, the city of merchants, was constructed in <span class="caps">MS</span> 3074 as a fortified city state. Its merchants have grown exceedingly rich from trade between the Lastlands and Central Magnamund, yet their influence has spread no further than the immediate environs of their city. Their leader, High-Mayor Kordas, is reputedly one of the richest men in Northern Magnamund, with an estimated personal fortune in excess of ten million gold crowns.</p>

<h4>The Great Sadi Desert</h4>
<p>Ruler: Shasarak the Wytch-king 
<br />Capital: None 
<br />Population: 80,000 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, gems, gold, silver 
<br />Currency: Noble (1 Noble = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Zultanate of Cloeasia</h4>
<p>Ruler: Zultan Guldarra 
<br />Capital: Kadan 
<br />Population: 28,000 
<br />Resources: Iron ore, copper, agriculture, shipbuilding, fish, rare cloths, gems 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

<h4>The Republic of Anari</h4>
<p>Ruler: President Dabudei 
<br />Capital: Tahou 
<br />Population: 61,000 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, minerals, gold, silver, timber, iron ore <br />Currency: Lune (4 Lune = 1 Gold Crown)</p>

<h4>The Imperial Emirate of Kakush</h4>
<p>Ruler: Emir Chotan
<br />Capital: Nikesa 
<br />Population: 76,000 
<br />Resources: Agriculture, timber, iron ore, gold, minerals, bronin 
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

<h4>The Lakuri Isles</h4>
<p>Ruler: Captain Khadro
<br />Capital: Kita Cove
<br />Population: 1500
<br />Resources: Piracy
<br />Currency: Gold Crown</p>

-->

  <section class="numbered" id="numbered">
   <meta><title>Numbered Sections</title></meta>

   <data>


    <section class="numbered" id="sect1">
     <meta><title>1</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>A sense of foreboding hangs over you as you mount your horse and head towards the city's south gate. There, a couple of tired night guards grumble wearily at your demand for the gate to be opened.</p>
      <p>'What's the hurry?' they growl. The door finally opens and you gallop through the arch.</p>
      <p>Half a mile beyond a stone bridge you see a signpost. An arrow pointing to the south says, 'Meadowood 1/2 mile/Holmgard 80 miles', and the other arrow, pointing west says simply, 'Old Mine Road'.</p>
      <choice idref="sect7">If you wish to continue south along the highway, <link-text>turn to 7</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect55">If you decide to take the road heading west, <link-text>turn to 55</link-text>.</choice>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect2">
     <meta><title>2</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Shouting your power-word, you point at the snarling Giaks. The lightning bolt breaks into several smaller energy pulses that rip into the evil warriors, sending them tumbling in all directions. Seizing the opportunity, you turn and run deeper into the ruined temple.</p>
      <choice idref="sect32"><link-text>Turn to 32</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect3">
     <meta><title>3</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Reining your horse to a halt, you stare down at the two dead Rangers. Their chests are scorched as if they were both struck by lightning. A Sword and a Mace lie close by. You may take either of these weapons.</p>
      <choice idref="sect31"><link-text>Turn to 31</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect4">
     <meta><title>4</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The one-roomed hut is damp and deserted. You scan the moss-covered walls for a good hiding place and your attention is caught by a large stone fireplace. You waste no time in climbing up the flue. Minutes later you hear the Giaks enter the hut in search of you. You try to keep as still as possible but you are desperate to sneeze.</p>
      <choice idref="sect74">If you have the spell of Silence, <link-text>turn to 74</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect22">If you do not possess this spell, <link-text>turn to 22</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect5">
     <meta><title>5</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>A search of the cupboards uncovers 2 Gold Crowns, enough food for one Meal, and the old man's Silver Warhammer. If you wish to take this, mark it on your <a idref='action'>Action Chart</a> as a Special Item which you carry tucked into your belt.</p>
      <choice idref="sect15"><link-text>Turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect6">
     <meta><title>6</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>'Quickly, take cover in the forest,' you shout to Daron and Thelda. But their little pony is terrified by the black-winged Kraan. It panics and gallops off into the trees on the other side of the highway. You are forced to ride deeper into the forest to avoid the black arrows of their Giak riders.</p>
      <choice idref="sect73"><link-text>Turn to 73</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect7">
     <meta><title>7</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>A few minutes later you see a line of wagons on the highway ahead. A group of merchants are arguing with a patrol of Border Rangers who stand guard at a barricade. The Rangers are refusing to allow anyone to pass through the village of Meadowood. 'No good you trying,' calls a disgruntled coachman.</p>
      <choice idref="sect48">If you wish to ask the Rangers to allow you through, <link-text>turn to 48</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect57">If you wish to stop and talk to the coachman, <link-text>turn to 57</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect8">
     <meta><title>8</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You cast your spell and catch all three of them by surprise. They struggle to free themselves but to no avail. The Kraan, fearing its riders have fallen into the clutches of a hideous monster, flies away to avoid a similar fate. The path is now clear and you seize your chance of escape.</p>
      <choice idref="sect47"><link-text>Turn to 47</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect9">
     <meta><title>9</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Suddenly, a wave of pain makes you scream out. Two arrows have passed through your chest and back, smashing the air from your lungs. You fall from the saddle, crashing to the soft earth with a terrible jolt.</p>
      <p>The last thing you hear are gasps of horror as the Rangers recognize your sky-blue robes.</p>
      <p>Your life and your mission end here.</p>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect10">
     <meta><title>10</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>As night falls, you reach the tiny village of Oak Hill, less than twenty miles from the Monastery of the Kai. There is no tavern here, but the blacksmith is well known for his generous hospitality.</p>
      <choice idref="sect66">If you wish to stop at the blacksmith's house, <link-text>turn to 66</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect79">If you choose to sleep out in the open, <link-text>turn to 79</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect11">
     <meta><title>11</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>For over an hour you move stealthily through the trees, straining for the sound of an approaching Giak patrol or nearby Kraan.</p>
      <p>Gradually the trees begin to thin out and you can see the ruins of an ancient temple. You take refuge beneath a fallen pillar. As you catch your breath, you remove the Guildmaster's envelope from your robe. Now that war has begun, it will be safer to commit its contents to memory rather than allow it to fall into enemy hands.</p>
      <choice idref="sect42"><link-text>Turn to 42</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect12">
     <meta><title>12</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>As you rush into the fray, the familiar sound of Kraan wings return. Hovering above you are six of the fearsome creatures. The peasants panic and flee, leaving you to face the Kraan alone.</p>
      <choice idref="sect37">If you wish to stand and fight, <link-text>turn to 37</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect59">If you wish to try to escape, <link-text>turn to 59</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect13">
     <meta><title>13</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Hurriedly, you cast the spell, circling your palm behind your head to form the shield. An instant later, two arrows just miss your back. Your magic has saved your life, but it has not protected you from a third arrow that gouges your left leg. Lose 3 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points.</p>
      <p>Wincing with pain, you press on until you have left the archers far behind.</p>
      <choice idref="sect15"><link-text>Turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect14">
     <meta><title>14</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You soon learn that your companions' names are Daron and Thelda, and that their father owns a bakery at Searsby.</p>
      <p>An hour has passed when you hear the beat of huge wings. A great cloud of black-winged creatures appears flying in a vast formation that darkens the sky. Your heart sinks. The Darklords, the ancient enemy of your people, are attacking. War has begun.</p>
      <choice idref="sect49">If you wish to continue along the highway, <link-text>turn to 49</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect6">If you decide to seek the shelter of the forest, <link-text>turn to 6</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect15">
     <meta><title>15</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The track continues for several miles down a steep wooded hillside to arrive at a little bridge spanning a deep, crystal-clear stream. A young woman dressed in padded leather armour stands there, warily watching you approach.</p>
      <p>'Where are you bound for, young wizard?' she asks.</p>
      <choice idref="sect54">If you wish to tell her your destination, <link-text>turn to 54</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect76">If you demand that she allow you across the bridge, <link-text>turn to 76</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect16">
     <meta><title>16</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The Giaks form a semi-circle, holding you at bay with the points of their spears. Suddenly, a clutch of Kraan glide across the trees and drop their riders almost on top of you. Their leader screams 'Darg!' and, as one, the Giaks charge.</p>
      <choice idref="sect37"><link-text>Turn to 37</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect17">
     <meta><title>17</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>As you whisper the spell-chant, a wave of fear numbs your senses.</p>
      <p>You are in the presence of a great and malicious evil. The woman senses your fear and a smile spreads across her face.</p>
      <choice idref="sect54"><link-text>Turn to 54</link-text>.</choice>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect18">
     <meta><title>18</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Your quick thinking saves you from the full impact of the lightning bolt. It passes close by your head, blistering the skin on your cheek and causing your hair to smoulder. The Helghast screams a terrible cry that claws at your mind (lose 3 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points), but the pain quickly fades as you gallop away from the village.</p>
      <choice idref="sect46"><link-text>Turn to 46</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect19">
     <meta><title>19</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>As you leave your hiding place, a cry echoes in your ears. 'Ogadak - Dok taag!' You thrust the envelope back into your robes and clamber across the ruins. Giaks appear as if from nowhere; one has his arm drawn back ready to throw a spear.</p>
      <choice idref="sect2">If you have the spell of Lightning Hand and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 2</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect51">If you wish to try to dodge the spear, <link-text>turn to 51</link-text>.</choice>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect20">
     <meta><title>20</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You whisper the spell under your breath. A shiver runs the length of your spine as you sense evil. It comes, not from the cabin, but from the wooded hills beyond. It is many miles away but you can feel it drawing closer.</p>
      <choice idref="sect67">If you wish to hide in the cabin, <link-text>turn to 67</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect15">If you wish to turn away from the approaching evil and press on through the forest, <link-text>turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect21">
     <meta><title>21</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You arrive in time to witness a handful of peasants armed with pitchforks attacking two Giaks on Doomwolves. Although superior in numbers, they are no match for these ferocious fighters who have already killed many of their kinfolk.</p>
      <choice idref="sect12">If you wish to aid the peasants, <link-text>turn to 12</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect47">If you choose to avoid the fight, you can run back along the track by <link-text>turning to 47</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect22">
     <meta><title>22</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You cannot hold back the sneeze. Within seconds, three ugly Giak faces are squinting up the chimney at you, prodding your feet with their spears. You hurriedly climb the flue only to find a couple of Kraan hovering above. They drop their Giak riders on the roof, and a voice shrieks: 'Dok ek!'</p>
      <choice idref="sect37"><link-text>Turn to 37</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect23">
     <meta><title>23</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The innkeeper's cheerful mood changes to a stony stare. 'Get out o' here!' he shouts angrily.</p>
      <choice idref="sect75">If you have the spell of Mind Charm, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 75</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect7">If you wish to leave the tavern, <link-text>turn to 7</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect24">
     <meta><title>24</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>As the smiling Ranger walks nearer, your horse becomes nervous and skittish. It takes a great deal of effort to bring him under control. When you glance at the Ranger once more, your skin prickles with dread at the change that has come over him. The skin of his face is writhing. It is changing colour, growing darker and tighter on his skull. His eyes glow with a red fire and fangs sprout from his bottom lip. A wave of panic leaves you breathless as you realize he is a Helghast, a hellish agent of the Darklords. A blue flame ignites at the tip of his staff and a searing charge of energy leaps towards your chest.</p>
      <choice idref="sect41">If you possess the spell of Invisible Shield, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 41</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect58">If you possess the spell of Counter Spell, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 58</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect72">If you have neither of these spells, <link-text>turn to 72</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect25">
     <meta><title>25</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You invoke the spell and, to the astonishment of the Giaks, leap over the edge. You are able to control your rate of descent, and gently you come to rest in a shallow ravine. You can hear the cries of Kraan and Giaks echoing through the forest. The trees are thicker to the south and you press on in that direction.</p>
      <choice idref="sect45"><link-text>Turn to 45</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect26">
     <meta><title>26</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Spreading the fingers of your right hand wide apart, you breathe the spell-runes. The net wraps around the old man, pinning him firmly to his chair. As you step forward to take away his Warhammer, the yellow bird swoops down and gouges your cheek before flying out of an open window. Lose 2 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points.</p>
      <p>'Leave me be,' whimpers the old man. 'Take what little I have but spare my life.'</p>
      <choice idref="sect39">If you wish to free him from the net, <link-text>turn to 39</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect5">If you decide to leave him tied up and search his cabin for useful items, <link-text>turn to 5</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect15">If you choose to leave the cabin and continue on your mission, <link-text>turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect27">
     <meta><title>27</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>After waiting several minutes for a unit of Giaks to march away you whisper the spell and take to the air. Unfortunately, the effects wear off as you near the middle of the lake, and gradually you descend into the cold dark waters of Lake Pewas.</p>
      <p>You are forced to discard all your equipment, except for your Crystal Star Pendant and Guildmaster's Envelope, for fear of drowning (erase all but these two Special Items from your <a idref='action'>Action Chart</a>).</p>
      <p>Eventually, you reach the far side and stumble ashore, cold and bedraggled. However, if you possess the spell of Mend, you may restore 5 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points to your current total, for you were able to cast the spell whilst swimming across the lake.</p>
      <choice idref="sect11"><link-text>Turn to 11</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect28">
     <meta><title>28</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The captain is insulted by your attempt at bribery. He knocks the coins from your hand and forces you away from the barricade at the point of his sword. Erase half the number of Gold Crowns that are noted on your <a idref='action'>Action Chart</a>.</p>
      <p>There is little you can do except try to circle the village under cover of the forest.</p>
      <choice idref="sect63"><link-text>Turn to 63</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect29">
     <meta><title>29</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You bite your lip as an arrowhead gouges a deep furrow across your thigh (lose 4 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points). The pain makes you swoon but you manage to press on until you have left the Rangers far behind.</p>
      <choice idref="sect15"><link-text>Turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect30">
     <meta><title>30</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You sense no evil in these children and you have no cause to doubt their word. They smile with joy when you agree to join them on the ride south.</p>
      <choice idref="sect14"><link-text>Turn to 14</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect31">
     <meta><title>31</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>From around a bend in the street ahead, a Ranger appears. He is carrying a long black staff. He smiles and waves at you to slow down.</p>
      <choice idref="sect24">If you wish to slow down and see what he wants, <link-text>turn to 24</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect38">If you decide to ignore him and gallop on, <link-text>turn to 38</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect32">
     <meta><title>32</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>A Giak, taller than the others and dressed from head to foot in black chainmail, curses and whips his troops with a barbed flail to get them to pursue you.</p>
      <p>Suddenly, a figure dressed in green leaps out of the undergrowth wielding an axe. Your heart skips a beat as he raises the weapon to strike, but he fells a Giak lurking behind your back - not you! The stranger has saved your life.</p>
      <choice idref="sect40"><link-text>Turn to 40</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect33">
     <meta><title>33</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>'Welcome to my humble home, welcome,' beams the wrinkle-faced old man.</p>
      <p>As you close the door, a sudden shriek sets your nerves on edge. 'Now, now, Galir!' says the old man, reproving a large yellow-feathered bird perched on a mirror above the mantelpiece. Irritably it flaps its wings and emits a curious warbling sound that the old man appears to understand. The man's expression becomes less friendly and his fingers tighten around the silver handle of an ornate Warhammer.</p>
      <choice idref="sect26">If you have the spell of Net, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 26</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect44">If you wish to draw your sword and attack the old man, <link-text>turn to 44</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect15">If you wish to escape into the forest, <link-text>turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect34">
     <meta><title>34</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>As the foul creature dies it tumbles from the bridge and is washed away by the fast-flowing stream. If you have the spell of Mend, you can take this opportunity to restore lost <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points by wading into the water and casting the spell. Before remounting your horse, you must eat a meal or lose 3 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points.</p>
      <choice idref="sect10">Now <link-text>turn to 10</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect35">
     <meta><title>35</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The Kraan heads west and soon lands in a clearing teeming with Giak soldiers. Roughly you are dragged from the saddle and thrown into a deep pit that holds three other humans, all Sommlending like yourself.</p>
      <choice idref="sect78">If you have the spell of Levitation, <link-text>turn to 78</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect65">If you do not possess this spell, <link-text>turn to 65</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect36">
     <meta><title>36</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You wake at dawn, refreshed and eager to continue your mission. The blacksmith's nephew and niece join you for a hearty breakfast and then accompany you to the stable to collect your horse. They share a small black pony called Bobin.</p>
      <choice idref="sect14"><link-text>Turn to 14</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect37">
     <meta><title>37</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You put up a brave struggle but you are soon overwhelmed. They tie your hands and confiscate everything you possess, except for your Crystal Star Pendant, and the Guildmaster's Message, both of which they fail to discover.</p>
      <p>'Dok ziran,' shouts a Giak officer pointing at you, 'Dok kag eg oknar oka.'</p>
      <p>Suddenly you are grabbed and thrown across the saddle of a Kraan. An ugly-faced Giak sits behind you, his knife held to your throat as the beast takes to the air.</p>
      <choice idref="sect60">If you have the spell of Lightning Hand, <link-text>turn to 60</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect35">If you do not have this spell, or do not wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 35</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect38">
     <meta><title>38</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The Ranger raises his black staff and aims it at your chest. A wave of nausea knots your stomach as suddenly you witness a terrible change. The skin that covers the Ranger's face is writhing, growing darker and tighter on his skull. His eyes glow red and great curved fangs have pushed themselves through his lower jaw. You stifle a scream as you realize he is a Helghast, a powerful shape-changing agent of the Darklords. A blazing blue flame ignites at the tip of his staff and a bolt of energy leaps towards your chest.</p>
      <choice idref="sect58">If you have the spell of Counter Spell, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 58</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect52">If you do not have this spell you can try to dodge the energy bolt by <link-text>turning to 52</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect72">Or you can try to trample the Helghast beneath your horse's hooves. <link-text>Turn to 72</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect39">
     <meta><title>39</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>'Take it easy, old man. I mean you no harm,' you say, as you cut the magical netting that binds him to his rocking chair. 'Your yellow bird seems to have misjudged me, for I have not come here to rob you.'The old man listens with interest to your explanation and gives you some advice on how to reach the Monastery of the Kai.</p>
      <p>You thank the old man and as you turn to leave he offers to exchange his Warhammer for any two items in your Backpack (excluding Meals). If you wish to make the exchange, erase two items of your choice and mark the Silver Warharnmer as a Special Item which you carry tucked into your belt.</p>
      <choice idref="sect15"><link-text>Turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect40">
     <meta><title>40</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>On seeing the green-cloaked stranger emerge from the woods, the Giak officer orders his troops to run to the shelter of the forest. For the time being, the danger has passed.</p>
      <p>Wiping the sweat from your brow, you turn to thank your unexpected rescuer and, as you do so, you recognize the clothes he wears: they are the green tunic and cloak of a Kai initiate.</p>
      <choice idref="sect80"><link-text>Turn to 80</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect41">
     <meta><title>41</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Drawing your hand across your face to invoke the spell, you form an invisible shield between yourself and the bolt of energy. Unfortunately, the bolt is magical, and it passes through the shield unhindered.</p>
      <choice idref="sect72"><link-text>Turn to 72</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect42">
     <meta><title>42</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The message is a warning that the Darklords have mustered a vast army beyond the Durncrag Range. The Guildmaster urges the Kai to cancel the feast of Fehmarn and prepare immediately for war. He fears that Sommerlund has been betrayed by a wizard of the brotherhood, called Vonotar.</p>
      <p>Suddenly, you hear the crunch of iron-shod boots on stone, and before you can destroy the Guildmaster's message, a Giak booms: 'Zazgog rek okaka.'</p>
      <choice idref="sect62">If you wish to stay where you are, <link-text>turn to 62</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect19">If you wish to move deeper into the ruins, <link-text>turn to 19</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect43">
     <meta><title>43</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The Border Rangers of Sommerlund are expert archers, and as you hear the hiss of their arrows speeding towards your back you pray that luck is on your side.</p>
      <choice idref="sect13">If you possess the spell of Invisible Shield, <link-text>turn to 13</link-text>.</choice>
      <p>If you do not have this spell, pick a number from the <a idref='random'>Random Number Table</a>.</p>
      <choice idref="sect69">If the number you have chosen is 0-2, <link-text>turn to 69</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect9">If the number is 3-7, <link-text>turn to 9</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect29">If the number is 8-9, <link-text>turn to 29</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect44">
     <meta><title>44</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You strike at the old man's head, but he parries your blow with his Warhammer. To your horror, your sword blade disintegrates as soon as it touches the weapon's silver haft. Cackling with glee, the old man leaps into the attack, brandishing his enchanted Warhammer above his head.</p>
      <p>Old Tadeus <typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ> 18 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> 18</p>
      <p>You must deduct 4 points from your <typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ> for you are now unarmed. If you have the spell of Vigour, you may cast it to increase your <typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ>, but be sure to deduct 3 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points accordingly.</p>
      <choice idref="sect15">You may evade combat after three rounds, by escaping to your horse. <link-text>Turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect5">If you win the combat, <link-text>turn to 5</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect45">
     <meta><title>45</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You come to the edge of a small lake where many Giaks and Drakkarim are being marshalled into units. You sense that the Kai Monastery lies on the other side of the lake, and you try to think of a way to get across the water unseen.</p>
      <choice idref="sect27">If you have the spell of Levitation, and you wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 27</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect53">If you want to swim across the lake, <link-text>turn to 53</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect68">If you decide to skirt around the lake, under cover of the forest, <link-text>turn to 68</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect46">
     <meta><title>46</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You have ridden several miles before you dare rest. You stop by the banks of a stream and allow your horse to drink. If you have the spell of Mend, you can take this opportunity to restore lost <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points by standing in the stream and casting the spell. Before you remount and continue, you must eat a Meal or lose 3 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points.</p>
      <choice idref="sect10">Now <link-text>turn to 10</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect47">
     <meta><title>47</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You climb through a tunnel of trees and emerge at the top of a rocky knoll. About three miles to the south you can see a huge cloud of Kraan circling a grey stone building. You watch with grim fascination as they tear at the walls with their talons. Suddenly, you are disturbed by the sound of rustling undergrowth, and you spin around in time to see a handful of Giaks charging towards you. You turn to run, but find yourself teetering on the brink of a steep drop.</p>
      <choice idref="sect25">If you have the spell of Levitation, <link-text>turn to 25</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect16">If you do not have this spell, or do not wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 16</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect48">
     <meta><title>48</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The Rangers are not impressed by your request to be allowed through Meadowood. A Ranger captain tells you to return to Toran. They are searching for a spy who has murdered three of his men. Until he is caught, nobody can pass through Meadowood.</p>
      <choice idref="sect77">If you have the spell of Mind Charm, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 77</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect28">If you do not have this spell, you can offer him some Gold Crowns, by <link-text>turning to 28</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect63">Or you can try to circle Meadowood by riding through the forest. <link-text>Turn to 63</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect49">
     <meta><title>49</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>A dozen black-winged creatures appear overhead. They are Kraan, and on their backs are shrieking Giaks eager to fight. Suddenly, the Kraan swoop.</p>
      <choice idref="sect56">If you have the spell of Lightning Hand, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 56</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect6">If you wish to evade the attack by entering the forest, <link-text>turn to 6</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect50">
     <meta><title>50</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The foul-mouthed Giaks cackle with joy as they close in for combat. You must fight all three as one enemy.</p>
      <p>Giaks <typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ> 16 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> 18</p>
      <choice idref="sect70">You can evade combat after three rounds by running into the forest. <link-text>Turn to 70</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect47">If you win the combat, you can escape along the south path by <link-text>turning to 47</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect51">
     <meta><title>51</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You dive aside and the spear whistles past your arm, tearing the cuff of your robe but drawing no blood. Quickly, you scramble to your feet and run deeper into the ruins.</p>
      <choice idref="sect32"><link-text>Turn to 32</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect52">
     <meta><title>52</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You have barely seconds to act. Desperately you jerk your horse to the left to avoid the crackling blue pulse of flame.</p>
      <p>Pick a number from the <a idref='random'>Random Number Table</a>.</p>
      <choice idref="sect18">If the number you have chosen is 0-6, <link-text>turn to 18</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect72">If the number is 7-9, <link-text>turn to 72</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect53">
     <meta><title>53</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You leave all you carry (except for your Crystal Star Pendant and Guildmaster's Envelope) on this side of the lake, for fear of drowning.</p>
      <p>After fifteen minutes you reach the far side and stumble ashore, cold and bedraggled. However, if you possess the spell of Mend, you may restore 5 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points to your current total, for you were able to cast the spell whilst swimming across the lake.</p>
      <choice idref="sect11"><link-text>Turn to 11</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect54">
     <meta><title>54</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>She unsheathes a black sword and emits a hideous laugh. The skin on her face is starting to writhe and change colour, growing darker with each passing second. Her eyes glow with red fire and long fangs appear from her lower jaw as she creeps slowly towards you. Shock leaves you breathless as you realize that she is a Helghast, a powerful shape-changing servant of the Darklords. Before you can think of using one of your spells, the Helghast hauls you out of the saddle. You land heavily on the stony ground and fumble in desperation for a weapon as the creature's black sword whistles towards your head.</p>
      <choice idref="sect64">If you have a Silver Warhammer, <link-text>turn to 64</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect61">If you do not possess this Special Item, <link-text>turn to 61</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect55">
     <meta><title>55</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>This road is little better than a rough forest track. Soon all trace of it disappears. You urge your horse through a mass of tangled undergrowth until you happen upon a moss-covered log cabin.</p>
      <choice idref="sect67">If you wish to take a closer look at the cabin, <link-text>turn to 67</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect15">If you wish to press on and try to find traces of the old mine road, <link-text>turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect20">If you have the spell of Sense Evil, and if you wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 20</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect56">
     <meta><title>56</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You release a bolt of lightning at the first of a number of Kraan screaming towards you. The pulse of energy tears through its chest, flipping it backwards and scattering its Giak crew like rag dolls. Two Kraan collide with it in mid-air and come crashing down in a tangled heap.</p>
      <p>However, your magic has attracted more Kraan and quickly you realize you must take to the forest if you are to avoid being overwhelmed.</p>
      <choice idref="sect6"><link-text>Turn to 6</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect57">
     <meta><title>57</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You learn that the Rangers are searching for a Darklord spy. Last night he killed three Rangers, here in Meadowood. He escaped but is still somewhere in the area. The Rangers have sealed off the highway and are not letting anyone through until the spy is caught or killed.</p>
      <choice idref="sect48">If you wish to approach the Rangers and ask them to allow you to pass, <link-text>turn to 48</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect55">If you decide to ride back to the junction at Old Mine Road, and try to circle the village, <link-text>turn to 55</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect58">
     <meta><title>58</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You shout the spell-words and feel a chill as some of your body warmth drains away to form the counter spell. A flat sphere of translucent red mist suddenly appears in the path of the oncoming bolt and, as they collide, a splash of violet flame erupts in front of your eyes. A tremendous shock wave knocks you back in the saddle and your startled horse rears up, but somehow you manage to regain control. The Helghast emits a cry that rakes your mind (lose 2 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points), but the pain quickly fades as you gallop away from Meadowood.</p>
      <choice idref="sect46"><link-text>Turn to 46</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect59">
     <meta><title>59</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You race back along the forest track, but a Kraan swoops down and drops three Giaks on the path ahead. They unsheathe curved swords and utter vile curses as they stalk nearer.</p>
      <choice idref="sect8">If you have the spell of Net, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 8</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect50">If you wish to draw your weapon and fight these three Giak soldiers, <link-text>turn to 50</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect70">If you wish to escape into the forest, <link-text>turn to 70</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect60">
     <meta><title>60</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Carefully, you point your finger at the grinning Giak rider and say the power words. There is an intense flash of blue light and a scream as your bolt decapitates him. His body somersaults backwards off the Kraan which begins to climb, its load instantly halved. The spell has burned through your bonds and now you can pull yourself into a sitting position. With blows to its head and neck, you force the Kraan to land in the forest. As soon as its clawed feet touch the soil, you leap from the saddle and run for cover.</p>
      <choice idref="sect11"><link-text>Turn to 11</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect61">
     <meta><title>61</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The creature laughs manically as it raises the sword to strike again. Valiantly you try to fend off the attack, but you are greatly weakened through loss of blood. The last thing you hear as the black sword descends is the Helghast's mocking laugh of victory.</p>
      <p>Your life and your mission end here.</p>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect62">
     <meta><title>62</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You place the envelope back into your robe and peek carefully over a broken marble slab. A squad of Giaks have entered the ruins and are systematically searching every square inch. Suddenly, a group appear to your left. They see you and raise the alarm: 'Ogadak!'</p>
      <choice idref="sect2">If you have the spell of Lightning Hand, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 2</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect32">If you wish to evade the Giaks, <link-text>turn to 32</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect63">
     <meta><title>63</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The dense foliage makes it difficult to pass through the trees on horseback, so you keep to a narrow track. Suddenly, a patrol of Rangers rush out of the trees behind you. They have bows and are preparing to fire them at you.</p>
      <choice idref="sect9">If you wish to call out to them to hold their fire, <link-text>turn to 9</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect43">If you decide to escape along the track as fast as your horse will carry you, <link-text>turn to 43</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect64">
     <meta><title>64</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>A crackle of blue flame bursts from your enemy's sword as it strikes the haft of your Silver Warhammer. The Helghast recoils from the blow, allowing you to stagger to your feet, but it soon recovers and attacks again. You cannot evade combat and must fight this creature to the death.</p>
      <p>Helghast <typ class="attribute">COMBAT SKILL</typ> 21 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> 28</p>
      <p>If you have the spell of Vigour, you may cast it before combat begins.</p>
      <choice idref="sect34">If you win the fight, <link-text>turn to 34</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect65">
     <meta><title>65</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Three hours pass before a Drakkarim officer appears at the edge of the pit and stares down at you with contempt. He barks an order and a circle of Giak archers appear. The last thing you hear is the hiss of their deadly black arrows.</p>
      <p>Your life and your mission end here.</p>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect66">
     <meta><title>66</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You knock on the door of the blacksmithy. It opens and a small plump woman stands before you, hurriedly wiping her hands on her chequered apron. She smiles and calls for Tym, her husband, as she ushers you into the dark warmth of the smithy. Tym the blacksmith welcomes you with a firm handshake. 'My word, Petrea, we're honoured to have a journeyman with us tonight,' he says to his wife.</p>
      <p>You enjoy a delicious supper, during which the blacksmith asks a favour of you. His nephew and niece, who are staying at the blacksmithy, are due to return home to their village in the morning. They live in Searsby, which lies to the south, where the road to the Kai Monastery branches off from the main highway. All he asks is that you accompany them home. You can hardly refuse the blacksmith's request, especially after enjoying his food and hospitality.</p>
      <choice idref="sect36"><link-text>Turn to 36</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect67">
     <meta><title>67</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You dismount and tether your horse before climbing the rickety steps to the cabin door. Through a cracked window pane you can see an old man sitting in a rocking chair. He is smoking a clay pipe and reading a leather-bound book. As you approach the door, you tread on a twig that snaps with a loud crack.</p>
      <p>'Who's there?' calls the old man.</p>
      <choice idref="sect33">If you wish to enter the cabin, <link-text>turn to 33</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect15">If you decide to press on through the forest, <link-text>turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect68">
     <meta><title>68</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Cautiously you move through the enemy-infested trees, but less than a hundred yards from the water's edge you are spotted by a Kraan patrol. You cannot evade them.</p>
      <choice idref="sect37"><link-text>Turn to 37</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect69">
     <meta><title>69</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You weave back and forth across the track, to present the archers with a harder target. Your tactics pay off, for although an arrow grazes your scalp (lose 1 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> point), it is just a flesh wound. Wiping a trickle of blood away, you press on and soon leave the archers cursing your escape.</p>
      <choice idref="sect15"><link-text>Turn to 15</link-text>.</choice>
     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect70">
     <meta><title>70</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Crashing headlong through the bracken, you fight to stay on your feet as you make your escape. Everywhere you hear the cries of Kraan and Giaks echoing through the trees. After ten minutes, the trees start to thin out and you can just make out the shape of a stone hut nestling at the bottom of a shallow ravine.</p>
      <choice idref="sect4">If you wish to hide in this hut, <link-text>turn to 4</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect45">If you wish to push on deeper into the forest, <link-text>turn to 45</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect71">
     <meta><title>71</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You ask her once more to let you cross, this time using your spell of Mind Charm to persuade her you are friendly. Unfortunately, your spell does not have the desired effect.</p>
      <choice idref="sect54"><link-text>Turn to 54</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect72">
     <meta><title>72</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>The energy bolt smashes into your unprotected chest and hurls you out of the saddle. Your chest is ablaze and tongues of orange flame flicker before your eyes - but you feel no pain. Only numbness and the irresistible urge to sleep fill your body. As your eyes slowly close, you do not see the Helghast raise its black staff to finish you off.</p>
      <p>Your life and your mission end here.</p>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect73">
     <meta><title>73</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Your heart is pounding fit to burst as you urge your horse through the ever-thickening foliage. The forest soon becomes too dense to continue on horseback and you are forced to press on by foot. You force your way through the rich vegetation until you discover a track. To the north you can make out some huts; to the south the path disappears into wooded hills.</p>
      <choice idref="sect21">If you wish to head north towards the huts, <link-text>turn to 21</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect47">If you wish to go south towards the hills, <link-text>turn to 47</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect74">
     <meta><title>74</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You invoke the spell just in time, and your violent sneezing goes undetected by the Giak soldiers searching the hut below. You wait several minutes before leaving your hiding place and pushing on through the forest to the south.</p>
      <choice idref="sect45"><link-text>Turn to 45</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect75">
     <meta><title>75</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>Under the influence of your magic, a calm descends on the man and his anger is swiftly replaced by his usual jollity. 'I'm sorry,' he says, 'please forgive my rudeness. I don't know what came over me.'</p>
      <p>He ushers you to a table near the fireplace that is set for dinner, and calls to his son to prepare you a meal. The food is delicious: restore 2 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points to your total before leaving the tavern and continuing on your way.</p>
      <choice idref="sect7"><link-text>Turn to 7</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect76">
     <meta><title>76</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>She answers by grasping the hilt of a weapon sheathed at her side. Her expression is stern and unfriendly.</p>
      <choice idref="sect71">If you have the spell of Mind Charm, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 71</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect17">If you have the spell of Sense Evil, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 17</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect54">If you decide to offer her some Gold Crowns to let you cross the bridge, <link-text>turn to 54</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect77">
     <meta><title>77</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>To the surprise of his men, the Captain orders the barricade to be drawn aside. You are allowed to pass, but as you are riding towards the village, you hear the Captain shouting: 'Stop that rider!'</p>
      <p>Your spell has begun to wear off. Spurring your horse to a gallop, you race along the deserted main street of Meadowood. Two bloodstained bodies lie on the road ahead; they are Rangers and they appear to be dead.</p>
      <choice idref="sect3">If you wish to stop and examine the bodies, <link-text>turn to 3</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect31">If you decide to ride on as fast as you can, <link-text>turn to 31</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect78">
     <meta><title>78</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>One of your fellow captives, a young hill farmer, unties the cords that bind your wrists. With your hands free once more, you whisper the spell of Levitation and slowly rise to the edge of the pit. The others are amazed but they stay silent so as not to jeopardize your escape. Patiently you wait for the right moment before emerging from the pit and diving into the cover of the trees.</p>
      <choice idref="sect11"><link-text>Turn to 11</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect79">
     <meta><title>79</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You awake shortly after dawn to a chill morning and, unless you possess a blanket, you must deduct 2 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> points. You are rising to your feet when suddenly you realize you are being watched. Two children, a boy and a girl, are sitting astride a little black pony, staring at you in disbelief.</p>
      <p>'Have you been asleep here all night?' asks the young girl. You nod.</p>
      <p>'You should have called on our uncle,' says the boy, 'he's the blacksmith of Oak Hill. He would have given you a bed for the night.'</p>
      <p>The little girl leans forward and offers you some bread and cheese. Gratefully you accept her kind offer (restore 1 <typ class="attribute">ENDURANCE</typ> point).</p>
      <p>'We're on our way to Searsby for the feast of Fehmarn,' says her brother. 'Are you going that way?'</p>
      <p>The village of Searsby lies to the south, where a road to the Kai Monastery branches off from the main highway.</p>
      <choice idref="sect14">If you wish to accompany the children south, <link-text>turn to 14</link-text>.</choice>
      <choice idref="sect30">If you have the spell of Sense Evil, and wish to use it, <link-text>turn to 30</link-text>.</choice>

     </data>
    </section>

    <section class="numbered" id="sect80">
     <meta><title>80</title></meta>

     <data>
      <p>You offer your hand in friendship and it is gratefully received. After introducing yourself, you hand over the Guildmaster's Envelope. The Kai Lord studies the message and a great sadness fills his eagle eyes.</p>
      <p>'Alas, the wisdom of this warning has arrived too late to save my kin. The war has already begun and my brothers in arms were the first to fall to the evil host of Helgedad. They are dead, and I am all that remains of the Kai. Your mission is complete, Banedon, but mine has only just begun. I, Lone Wolf, must journey to Holmgard to warn the King. He will know what must be done to save our land.'</p>
      <p>Instinctively, you remove your Crystal Star Pendant and hand it to the last Kai warrior. It is a talisman of good luck and you pray that it protects him on the perilous road ahead.</p>
      <p>Your mission is complete!</p>

     </data>
    </section>
   </data>
  </section>

  <!-- Backmatter -->

 </data>
</section>

</gamebook>
